<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The leaves of the tree of life: for the healing of the nations. Opening all the wounds of this kingdome, and of every party, and applying a remedy to them: by which we come to a right understanding between King and Parliament. A universal agreement and peace on all sides, and the kingdom restored and setled upon a sure and unmoveable foundation: by the light of God shining upon William Sedgwick.</title>
            <author>Sedgwick, William, 1609 or 10-1669?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 245 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92862</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2386</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E460_40</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204719</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864183</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864183</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116405</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92862)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116405)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 73:E460[40])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The leaves of the tree of life: for the healing of the nations. Opening all the wounds of this kingdome, and of every party, and applying a remedy to them: by which we come to a right understanding between King and Parliament. A universal agreement and peace on all sides, and the kingdom restored and setled upon a sure and unmoveable foundation: by the light of God shining upon William Sedgwick.</title>
                  <author>Sedgwick, William, 1609 or 10-1669?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 103, 108-121, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. for Giles Calvert, at the black spread-Eagle, at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a final contents leaf.</note>
                  <note>Text is continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "August ye 25".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Peace --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116405:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116405:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> LEAVES OF THE TREE OF LIFE: <hi>For the healing of</hi> THE NATIONS. Opening all the <hi>wounds</hi> of this <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> and of every party, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying a <hi>remedy</hi> to them: By which we come to a <hi>right underſtanding</hi> between <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament.</hi> A univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal agreement and peace on all ſides, and the <hi>Kingdom</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored and ſetled upon a ſure and unmoveable Foundation:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By the Light GOD ſhining upon</hi> WILLIAM SEDGWICK.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doe you not know that the Saints ſhall Judge the World?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>H.</hi> for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the black ſpread-Eagle, at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:116405:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116405:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE WHOLE KINGDOME.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ead, and wonder, I know thou wilt, to ſee the <hi>Lord</hi> ſo ſoon up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Engliſh ground:</hi> you are <hi>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized,</hi> taken faſt <hi>aſleep:</hi> Awake, ſtand up, <hi>Tis the Lord: he is come to ſave us:</hi> he was with us upholding our former <hi>proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity,</hi> and we knew it not; he is now with us fighting againſt our <hi>worldly ſtate,</hi> in ſuch a <hi>dark cloud</hi> as we are more ignorant of him; he will now <hi>unvail himſelf,</hi> and you <hi>ſhall ſee him in open face</hi> of love and Salvation, and ſay, <hi>This is the Lord.</hi> While you are under him in the World, you will finde <hi>his feet as
<pb facs="tcp:116405:3"/>fine braſſe burning in a furnance::</hi> His ſteps will be hard to break you in peeces; <hi>fiery to conſume you;</hi> yet <hi>fine,</hi> holy and juſt: ſuffer that and he will take you <hi>up into his armes, and binde you to himſelfe with a golden girdle of love,</hi> and ſhew you a face as <hi>bright</hi> as the <hi>Sun ſhinning in his ſtrength,</hi> giving you rich <hi>love, life</hi> and <hi>light:</hi> he is <hi>ſevere</hi> that will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſh; but mercifull that will <hi>comfort:</hi> he is very low in the bottome of your ſinnes and miſeries; there the fleſh will <hi>deſpiſe</hi> him, but your wants will <hi>rejoyce in him and ſay, ſuch a high Prieſt we need:</hi> but exalted very high in the largneſſe of lovingkindneſſe, ſure that will pleaſe you, and the evil one only can be troubled at it: <hi>England</hi> it is thy <hi>Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd,</hi> the <hi>Porter will and muſt open to him: and the Sheep will hear his voice,</hi> while he calleth them by their names, they <hi>will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him,</hi> and he will lead them out of their
<pb facs="tcp:116405:3"/>
               <hi>miſery:</hi> and he goeth before them (In eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way of ſuffering and deliverance he is firſt) ſure you will not follow a ſtranger, but flee from him: he ſaith, <hi>All that went before me are theeves and robbers: they are hirelings</hi> (and come for wages) they come not but to <hi>ſteal,</hi> to <hi>kill</hi> and to <hi>deſtroy</hi> (ſo have all done yet) <hi>They are hirelings, and the ſheep are not</hi> theirs: <hi>But I am the good Shepherd, I lay down my life for the Sheep: I am come that they might have life</hi> (after their death) <hi>and that they might, have it more abundantly</hi> (then ever they had it) <hi>J will ſeek that which is loſt,</hi> and bring again that which was driven away; <hi>and will binde up that which was broken;</hi> and will ſtrengthen that which was ſick: <hi>and J will feed them in a good paſture, upon the high mountains ſhall their fold be</hi> &amp;c. I know the narrownes of mans heart will ſay, <hi>who hath heard ſuch a thing? Who hath ſeen ſuch things? Shall the earth
<pb facs="tcp:116405:4"/>bring forth in one day? ſhall a Nation be born at once?</hi> Will <hi>Chriſt</hi> appear in the <hi>earth? or if in</hi> the earth, in a whole <hi>Nation?</hi> what <hi>Chriſt</hi> under the ſinnes of the <hi>Kingdome? his blood ſhed</hi> in a <hi>Nation?</hi> a <hi>Saviour</hi> of the Earth? and this in ſo ſhort a ſeaſon, all at once? To this I only anſwer: <hi>My thoughts are not as your thoughts, nor my waies as your waies: but as far as heaven is above earth; ſo far are my waies above your waies, ſaith the Lord:</hi> This I doe rejoyce in, and ſo wilt thou, that heer is light to be ſeen, and eyes to ſee with: that he can open and enlarge the mindes of men, and bring them out of priſon, and make them able to receive the truth, <hi>This is truth, light to ſhew this truth in, eyes to receve it,</hi> and <hi>love to rejoyce in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee have no enemy but the <hi>devil,</hi> and he will make all the reſiſtance he can: poor, weak man may doubt, fear, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but <hi>Satan</hi> will <hi>blaſpheme, rage and ſay,</hi> tis impoſſible, tis
<pb facs="tcp:116405:4"/>
               <hi>blaſphemy,</hi> tis againſt God, againſt man: But thou enemy thy diſcovery is thy ruine: thou ſhalt not ſpeake a word againſt this Lord but it ſhall be manifeſt tis thou a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, a lyer, a deſtroyer, that hath no por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this thing, and therefore wouldeſt deſtroy that that will deſtroy thee, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver the <hi>Kingdome</hi> out of thy deſtroying hands: thou art caſt down; thy <hi>Kingdom</hi> of darknes is broken by the <hi>light</hi> of the day of God: thou ſhalt prevail no longer <hi>in this Kingdome:</hi> O <hi>Leviathan</hi> we now can draw <hi>thee</hi> out with a hook, and thy tongue with a cord; thou ſhalt now make <hi>ſupplications to us,</hi> and ſpeak ſoft words to us: we now take thee for a ſervant, play with thee as with a <hi>bird,</hi> and our <hi>companions</hi> ſhall make a ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet of thee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore depart thou as ſmoak before the preſence of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Heer is one that hath the Keys of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> that can enter into the <hi>Kingdome, bring
<pb facs="tcp:116405:5"/>forth the priſoners,</hi> judge them and ſave them from <hi>Satans</hi> cruelty and wrath: Theſe are the <hi>Leaves,</hi> not the fruit <hi>of the Tree of life;</hi> the cure is upon the Nation in general, that is the ſubject in hand; not men in their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and perſonal eſtate, that is yet to come: This is <hi>Elijah</hi> who comes before the <hi>great and dreadfull day of the Lord: to turne the heart of the Fathers to the Children, and the heart of the Children to their Fathers; leſt J come and ſmite the earth with a curſe:</hi> The Lord in the ſpirit of <hi>Elijah,</hi> the <hi>dawning of the day upon the top of the mountain,</hi> waſhing and cleanſing the outward skin of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to prepare for further and greater glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and to remove the preſent curſe of hell, and wrath that is <hi>devouring</hi> of you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I have no more to ſay to you, but ſtand ſtill and patiently hear your doom from the <hi>Throne</hi> of God advancing it ſelf in</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>WILLIAM SEDGWICK.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116405:5"/>THE LEAVES OF THE TREE of LIFE, For the healing of the NATION.</head>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. I.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Shewing the happy and flouriſhing condition in which the Kingdome of England once ſtood, and the ground of it.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Earth is the Lords and the fulneſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the world and all that dwelſs therein: For he hath founded it upon the Seas,</hi> &amp;c. The divine goodnes delights to bring forth it ſelfe in the whole creation: and upon all things <hi>ſtamps</hi> his own likenes.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially the heavenly man, takes pleaſure to bring forth a brief <hi>Epitome</hi> of himſelf in his image man: The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116405:6"/>of Heaven have <hi>ingraven</hi> their likenes upon the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of the Earth: The new Jeruſalem the City of God, beſtowes her ſhape and beauty upon theſe Cities: But the higheſt glory of God in his Kingdome, is drawn forth in the Kingdomes of this world, and therefore they are above all, <hi>The Kingdomes of our Lord and of his Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Above all the Nations, this of <hi>England</hi> (with her two ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi>) is with peculiar favour ſeperated from the World: Being an Iſland imbraced with armes and Seas of righteouſneſſe, peace, ſafety, and the knowledge of God: The boſome of the earth where the divine glory chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to treaſure up his richeſt <hi>Jewels:</hi> His private <hi>lodging</hi> whereinto he delights to <hi>retire himſelf,</hi> and out of which he pleaſes firſt to ariſe, and thence to proceed to viſit the whole World.</p>
            <p>Nothing heer but is ſpoken by God; made by the <hi>Word</hi> of God; and doth again ſpeak God. A fruitfull and beautifull Earth, meeting with and <hi>married</hi> unto a pleaſant and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull Heaven, in a healthfull and temperate Spirit and Ayre doe bring forth abundance of excellent fruit: Eſpecially thoſe rich Flocks of <hi>Sheep</hi> that cover the Earth, ſhewes the Soyle to be the <hi>Lambs,</hi> and to were his <hi>Livery;</hi> and ſo to be his <hi>Store-houſe,</hi> from whence he will cloath the world with garments of Salvation.</p>
            <p>In the diſpoſition of the People of <hi>England</hi> ſhine many ſparkes and beames of divine majeſty, ingenuity and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; gentleneſſe and mildnes; zeal and devotion; gravity and wiſdome; ſtoutnes and courage; noblenes, and greatnes of ſpirit; aptnes for generall and high undertakings: which renders them feard, honored and beloved abroad; and fit inſtruments of good to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe.</hi> As other Nations are furniſht with mines of <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>ſilver: England</hi> with rich
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116405:6"/>minds full of true worth; indeed a <hi>Race</hi> and <hi>ſeed</hi> of heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Lords</hi> obſcured under earthly infirmities, yet ſo, as their <hi>luſter</hi> doth diſcover it ſelfe and ſhine out.</p>
            <p>But that which indeed exalted us to Heaven was this: That this excellent People, in a happy Country, were by the Miniſtry of mighty Angels, moulded into a govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment after the pattern of the higheſt and perfecteſt glory of God; in Father, Son and Spirit: Or to make <hi>England</hi> a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py <hi>Canaan,</hi> Father, Son and Spirit agree together to dwell in it, and to beſtow themſelves upon it in their ſeverall fulnes: and doe themſelves, vail'd and covered over with fleſhly formes, unite and govern us in righteouſneſſe and peace.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the <hi>Father</hi> advances the <hi>King</hi> in his own likeneſſe, and by living in him, makes him to be <hi>Pater patriae</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his Country: the Head and Supreme: The Huſband and Lord of the Kingdome. In him (as in God the Father) is all the Majeſty, Honour, Juſtice and Riches of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. In unity, bound up cloſe in one Perſon: all in its Center: hence it comes, and hither it returnes.</item>
               <item>2. In Head and Fountain; the originall from whence honour and juſtice flowes.</item>
               <item>3. In Priority or prerogative: in him as higheſt and Supreme.</item>
               <item>4. But more hid and deeply conceald, not ſo outward and viſible as in others.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Hence is the King the <hi>Anointed</hi> of God: God eminently: <hi>I ſaid ye are Gods:</hi> in neareſt conjunction unto God: The greateſt repreſentative of God: His Vicegerent: Next un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God: in immediate fellowſhip with God: God and the King.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Sonne appears in the People (eſpecially
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116405:7"/>as they are form'd in one Repreſentative the Parliament) and by his fulneſſe, makes them the Body of the Head: The Wife, the Spouſe; And ſo gives them all the Majeſty, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, juſtice and Riches of the Kingdome: and that that is in the King to be in them.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Divided and multiplied; not bound up in center, but drawn forth into circumference, and come forth in many.</item>
               <item>2. In ſtream, and flowing forth for the uſe and benefit of others.</item>
               <item>3. In ſecond place, in ſubordination to the firſt.</item>
               <item>4. Imbodied and drawn forth into open view, more viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and manifeſt unto others.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Thus are they the <hi>Kings</hi> yoak-fellows, a meet help &amp; have what ever he hath; his Son and heire. And being raiſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Parliament by the Kings <hi>Writ,</hi> are then fit <hi>mediators</hi> tween the King and the People: by whom the People offer up gifts to the King, and the King gives favours, pardons, and priviledges to them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The <hi>Spirit</hi> the third Perſon, he by the Law, and by mutuall Covenants bindes theſe two together, and is the <hi>marriage</hi> that joynes them, or the houſe of love in which they both live in peace and happines with each other, and diſpoſes both into a juſt and equall diſtance; yet a perfect agreement; or give them both to ſubſiſt in proper and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Rights, and both in union together; that they both fully have what is due to them; and both have what each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have: the ſame; and that equally without robbery; without injury or wrong to each other. The Law gives to the King his <hi>Prerogative,</hi> his authority in <hi>unity;</hi> in <hi>Fountain,</hi> &amp;c. And diverſifying or <hi>multiplying</hi> give the ſame in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way to the body; and yet takes nothing from the King. So gives it to the King as is moſt advantagious to the body;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116405:7"/>and ſo to the body as is moſt advantagious to the <hi>head.</hi> The body hath it beſt in the Kings having of it, with that <hi>honour, ſafety</hi> and <hi>union</hi> as ſhee cannot have it in her ſelf. And the <hi>head</hi> hath it beſt in the <hi>bodies</hi> having of it with that <hi>fruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> and <hi>ſtrength</hi> that he cannot have it out of them: Yea, in this <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Law,</hi> in this bond of perfection they both have it in each other; and could not, nor cannot have it long nor well, if they have it not together. The <hi>Royalty</hi> of a <hi>King</hi> as a <hi>fountain,</hi> freely giving it ſelf into the Authority of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> as a huſband giving himſelf to his wife: and the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> only being what <hi>ſhee</hi> receives from the <hi>King;</hi> ſo they mutually nouriſh, ſupport &amp; uphold each other; and being divided and ſeperated, they preſently wither away and dye. They both have it and both <hi>give</hi> it; the <hi>body gives</hi> it to the <hi>head,</hi> and receives it from the <hi>head</hi> in ſeverall waies; and this is its life and perfection, that it paſſes by <hi>vines</hi> and <hi>arteries</hi> from one to another, and are knit together by nerves and ſinewes; ſo that what honour the <hi>King</hi> hath, he <hi>gives</hi> to his <hi>People,</hi> and what riches and ſubſtance the <hi>People</hi> had, they <hi>gave</hi> it to the <hi>King:</hi> the <hi>People</hi> honorable in the <hi>Prince,</hi> and the prince mighty and ſtrong in the <hi>People.</hi> The <hi>body</hi> breaths, ſees, taſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the <hi>head;</hi> &amp; the <hi>head</hi> workes, walkes, and digeſts in the <hi>body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>Trinity</hi> are truly <hi>The foundamentall Lawe &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Kingdom;</hi> which is the cauſe of <hi>ability, ſtrength</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom:</hi> the <hi>Pillars</hi> that kept it upright: the <hi>health</hi> and <hi>ſoundne</hi> of it, where by it was able to ſubſiſt in proſperity, and floriſh in it ſelf, and to defend and maintain it ſelf <hi>againſt</hi> enemies from abroad.</p>
            <p>In this eſtate we for a while flouriſhed and enjoyed a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven upon earth, or an earthly heaven: a ſweet figure or ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of the Kingdome of glory: and but a ſhadow; yet ſuch
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116405:8"/>a ſhadow as was in union with the ſubſtance: King and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple being knit together by the Spirit, and by the ſame ſpirit <hi>knit</hi> to God &amp; Chriſt. Such a figure as had the original living in it in infirmity and weakneſſe. Twas the true light <hi>ſhining</hi> in darkneſſe; <hi>but the darkneſſe comprehended it not:</hi> We knew not our own filicity: God was nigh to us, the Kingdome of God in all his glory was in the mid'ſt of us and we were not aware of it. The Lord did <hi>Reign</hi> amongſt the Children of men, and they knew it not; while he was preſent, they ſet him of a diſtance; and would not receive their own life: but in enmity did cover the face of God, the majeſty and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, and gloried in their poor ſhadow.</p>
            <p>Twas a beautifull but earthly veſſel raiſed up for a time, a temporary greatnes, a corruptible Crowne: that we have ſeen ſtanding and flouriſhing in proſperity, but its period of happineſſe is come: and you ſhall now ſee it in its decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, diſeaſed, corrupt eſtate end falling.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. II.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Shewing the Kingdome of England in its cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and declining eſtate.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>YOu have ſeen the fair inſide of <hi>England;</hi> now you ſhall ſee the filthy outſide of it. The holy God took it into conjunction and felowſhip: now caſts it off into rejection and reprobation. In the firſt, his glory ſhin'd: in this its abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable wickedneſſe and wofull ruine appear.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:116405:8"/>
            <p>This Heavenly glory, being in love with the earthly ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of it ſelf, deſires to approach nearer unto it, and to dwell with it, in a more intire and perfect union, and to ſwallow it up into it ſelf, that it might no longer ſubſiſt out of him, but be found in him: But as God approaches, this earth fled from his brightnes, being a fraid to be ſwallowed into its own Life: and being weake and jealous of the great love of God; choſe rather to continue its old form, and its earthly happineſſe. The goodlines and majeſty of God was cloathed and hid in this worldly Kingdome; as a treaſure in an earthen veſſel: Twas his pleaſure to break the veſſel, to rend and tear the old <hi>garment,</hi> that he might come forth and cloath that with his glory, that cloathed him with its baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: But the Pot-ſherd did ſtrive with his Maker, and would not yeeld or offer up it ſelf to God: but doated upon it ſelfe and its own beauty: Therefore God threw it off into a dark and inordinate idolizing it ſelf: to a worldly and ſatanicall ſeperation from God; and love of it ſelf: making it ſelf the ſubſtance, and God the ſhadow; and ſo grew to an earneſt minding of its preſent happines, and threw off God into a ſtrangeneſſe and diſtance; not to be converſed with in this world; but referd him to another; making thoſe two which God hath made one. Hence grew in the whole Nation, King and People in all parts, an eagar love of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things: and as God threatens to take it down, that he might ſet up the heavenly, ſo much the more earneſtly did they cleave to it, and fall further and further from God, and more and more laboured to load themſelves with thick clay; and ſo the whole Kingdome in oppoſition to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine will, are in ambition and covetuouſneſſe ſet to advance their worldly ſtate: heer is the fatall breach betwixt God and man, twixt Heaven and <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:116405:9"/>
            <p>This breach is made by the Devil, the wicked one, the God of this World: by which the Kingdome is become Satans, and divided from God.</p>
            <p>And being thus cut off from its <hi>head</hi> and <hi>life</hi> God, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but fall into diviſions: The Spirit of God fayling the band of <hi>union,</hi> it muſt quickly be in diſtraction: There was a deſtroying in the whole; but it firſt appeared twixt head and body: Thus.</p>
            <p>All parts finding their foundation fayling, and ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe and diſturbance in the body, each begin to ſtickle for it ſelf and its own intereſt, as diſtinct from the other.</p>
            <p>The King having a miſgiving that his greatnes did not increaſe, but rather ſinck; thirſts after more abſoluteneſſe: thinks it a <hi>debaſing</hi> to his <hi>Royalty</hi> to have any in conduction with him: as good be no King as to be in dependance upon others: and ſo growes weary of the Parliament.</p>
            <p>The People finding their liberty and priviledge ſinking too, begin to be jealous of their Prince; and accounting him a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> afraid they were going into <hi>ſlavery;</hi> finding an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in the <hi>body,</hi> that favour did not flow ſo freely from the <hi>head</hi> as it uſe to doe, diſdaining to be kept at a diſtance from <hi>Government</hi> and the affaires of <hi>States;</hi> growing impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of the <hi>Princes</hi> waies, cenſure his actions, and to have a longing itch after government.</p>
            <p>Drawing thus ſeverall waies, there growes of <hi>head</hi> and <hi>members</hi> two <hi>factions.</hi> The <hi>Count</hi> and Royall, and epiſcopall party: and the Country People and <hi>puritan</hi> party: Theſe two grow from jealouſies and diſcontents to <hi>malignity</hi> one againſt another; to watch for advantages one againſt the other, and to ſeek the advancing themſelves and the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ining of each other; labouring all that the could to rob each other, and to pull and ſnatch from each other to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116405:9"/>ſtrengthen themſelves; and ſo growing to a deadly enmity: and when the <hi>body</hi> meet in a Parliament, and ſo head that <hi>party,</hi> they are ſtrongly divided; and the whole <hi>Kingdome</hi> being ſhaken and broken fall to peeces according to the working of their ſeverall and various principles.</p>
            <p>To the <hi>King</hi> goes men of honour, as the Nobility and Gentry much: whoſe honour is predominate over their reaſon and <hi>Religion.</hi> The <hi>Epiſcopall</hi> patty being <hi>Monarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call; growing</hi> out of the <hi>root</hi> of the <hi>King;</hi> and <hi>paternall</hi> much the Fathers of the <hi>Church;</hi> men of <hi>impliſſit Faith,</hi> whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is much regulated by their <hi>ſuperiours;</hi> men that are high and great admirers of <hi>Kinglineſſe;</hi> taken much with that Ordinance of a <hi>King.</hi> And a vaſt number of looſe men men of no <hi>Religion;</hi> but the <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the <hi>Parliament, men</hi> who of a lower ſtate, and exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their own reaſons in <hi>Religion:</hi> zealous and wel-affected People; men of induſtry and labour, that love freedome and to be ſomthing themſelves: Men whoſe conſciences are their owne and ſo ſtrict in them: Cities, Corporations, Bodies; and men that highly honour the Parliament; men zealous for generall and common Good.</p>
            <p>And by the acceſſe of theſe Parties to each other, they are ſtrengthened in their oppoſition of each other, and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for their mutuall ruine.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:116405:10"/>
            <head>Chap. III.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Shewing the Kings Errors.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>The Kingdome being divided into two par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the King firſt carries away <hi>The Golden ball of Government;</hi> who (though taken off, and ſeperated from his true Baſis, <hi>The King of Kings</hi>) yet is aſſiſted by a mighty Angell, by whoſe help he rules awhile alone; and with more good, and leſſe evill then thoſe that ſucceed: In which hee appeares in <hi>High and maſculine vertue:</hi> as a Father, <hi>mighty, ſevere, and terrible:</hi> The great and undoubted Image of God living in a <hi>ſupremacy,</hi> beyond and above all queſtons; honoured <hi>with fear and devotion:</hi> But alas, being alone he ſoon declines, his <hi>good Angel leaves him,</hi> and ſo not able long to manage the Scepter; But oppreſſed with his owne <hi>guilt, and the curſe of</hi> GOD, quickly is forced to reſigne it to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>It hath been the Kings plea That he is accountable for his actions to none but God; and therefore hath frequently in his Declarations appealed from man to GOD. And Divine juſtice hath reſerved your cauſe to Himſelf, and kept your Parliament a long while from accuſing you of any thing, <hi>only charging your instruments.</hi> And when they attempted to bring forth any thing againſt you, as they did in their Declaration <hi>upon their Votes to make no more addreſſes to you:</hi> They were manifeſtly weak and miſtaken; and not being
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116405:10"/>to prove any thing, they were forced preſently to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract what they had done; and ſhew they produced nothing <hi>but their own ſhame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſtand therefore before the Throne of God, and are found guilty of tranſgreſſing againſt <hi>that foundamental Law</hi> from which thou holdeſt thy Crown, <hi>The majestie of God the Father,</hi> and haſt broke Covenant firſt, with God, ſecondly with thy People.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Thou haft ſlain and killed thy Father, <hi>The Lord of glory;</hi> this is thy <hi>Parricide;</hi> That the great King lies to this day <hi>buried in thee,</hi> as in his <hi>Sepulcher.</hi> That in all thy <hi>Reigne,</hi> thou haſt not ſuffered the <hi>Majeſty</hi> of God to break forth; but haſt ſmothered and denied his <hi>light</hi> to ſhine <hi>through thee</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men. Thou haſt owned the title and name of the <hi>Lords Anointed, CHARLES by the Grace of God,</hi> but haſt not owned the ſubſtance of that <hi>Anointing</hi> and that <hi>Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hadſt thou known and owned that fountain of <hi>Divine light and wiſdome</hi> which lives in thy <hi>ſacred Head and Breaſt,</hi> Thou wouldeſt have underſtood the meaning of that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, <hi>The King cannot Erre;</hi> and ſo would'ſt alwayes walke by a certain and never-failing <hi>rule:</hi> But thou (forſaking, yea, profeſſing againſt that Spirit) haſt followed the falſe and crooked <hi>rule</hi> of thy owne carnall reaſon, and cuſtomes and examples of other Princes, and the dark counſell of <hi>poor petty</hi> Politicians.</p>
            <p>Hadſt thou known that Immortal fountain of Majeſty, that is in thee, thou wouldeſt have known the meaning of that poſition, <hi>The King cannot dye;</hi> and would never through fear and jealouſy fled from thy People and Parliament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of Tumults: Was not that a turning away <hi>that Royall face of God</hi> that is able to have allayed and ſtill'd the raging of thoſe waves? Had you known that Divine power that is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116405:11"/>in you, you would have met ſuch tumults, as Chriſt met thoſe that came to apprehend him; and ſaid as he did, <hi>I am he, whom ſeeke yee?</hi> And then you had had the ſame effect, <hi>They would have fallen before you.</hi> Or if you had ſuffered, you had layd down your Crown in diſhonour, it would have been raiſed in honour <hi>as his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to fly to a place of ſtrength, <hi>Digbies counſell,</hi> who taught Majeſty to <hi>Digge,</hi> to earth it ſelfe into <hi>by</hi> and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect paths of darkneſſe. Ther's no place of ſtrength equall to your owne Royall heart: It was to teach the Sun to hide it ſelfe in the earth for fear of clouds, or to depart from his <hi>ſphere</hi> to avoyd miſts. Or hadſt thou lived in the <hi>Anointing</hi> that is in thee, thou hadſt not needed to have feared, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the high demands of thy ſubjects ſeeking thy <hi>prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives</hi> from thee, or the diminiſhing thy <hi>greatnes</hi> by it; but mighteſt have freely powred forth to much honour as would have burſt them if they had been corrupt and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their deſigne; or it would have aſſured thee that there is ſuch a Sun of Majeſty in thee, as could not be leſſe by ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon them; and that Majeſty is not in titles, names, cuſtomes, the power of <hi>a Militia;</hi> but naturally inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in thee, fixt and ſure as God, and ſo inſeperable from thee.</p>
            <p>It was meaneſſe and poorneſſe of ſpirit that did not give more fully then they could aſk, and ſo have over-come them; or if thou hadſt made them Kings, thou hadſt been, as truely thy coppy is, KING of KINGS; ſo that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed thy Error hath been, Thou haſt not been Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſticall enough: or lived in the height and abſolutneſſe of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, When thou hadeſt broken the bond of u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion twixt the Eternall and thy Kingdome, by which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116405:11"/>thy Kingdome was become a Kingdome of darkneſſe, a Worldly one; and ſo ruled by the god of this World, the Devill.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt in oppoſition to the judge of all men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to the uttermoſt to uphold and maintain that vaine Idoll, and falſe power, when the holy one hath ſent out <hi>Watchers</hi> to deſtroy it, and haſt Pertenaciouſly refuſed to give it up to bee ſlain by Gods juſtice: The more God ſhewed himſelfe againſt it to breake it, the more didſt thou perſiſt in ſtriving for it: And not committing it to him whoſe it firſt was, and from whom thou didſt receive it, haſt gon into baſe, carnall and filthy waies to preſerve it: This is the reaſon that a long time thou haſt run a courſe of weak, dark and black waies, being lead about by Satan at his pleaſure.</p>
            <p>It was this that ſent thee in ſecret waies to beg aide and aſſiſtance of Forraign Princes, and not of Princes only, but by thy agents haſt unworthily ſought to private perſons for reilefe, the <hi>almes houſes,</hi> called <hi>religious houſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou haſt been dealing in a cloſe and under-ground way with the Bloudy Iriſh and that party; Haſt wander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from thy ſteadineſſe, to all intereſts and parties in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> and ſo been forced to moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable and unequall ſhifts, denying thy actions, falſe ſaying and ſwaring, to various formes and ſhapes, to ſave thy Worldly Greatneſſe from Divine ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</p>
            <p>Thou in purſuance of it haſt pawned thy word, engaged thy eſtate, thy Crown, jewells, undone thy friends; and al theſe things eaten up with contending againſt a curſe doomd by God; not knowing yet, <hi>that he that ſaveth
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116405:12"/>his Crown, ſhall loſe it,</hi> and <hi>hee that loſeth it</hi> now <hi>ſhall ſave it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As thou haſt ſinned againſt the holy God, ſo againſt thy People, and haſt fail'd in thy Government towards them; not anſwering your heavenly pattern and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Law.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Thou haſt not lived with thy <hi>wife,</hi> thy <hi>body,</hi> the People in the love of a Head: Thou ſhouldſt have loved her <hi>as Chriſt loved his Church, and gave himſelfe for it, to ſanctify it</hi> &amp;c. Tis true thy <hi>ſpouſe</hi> was unclean, proud, high in demands, ſtriving with thee; the true way to have <hi>waſht</hi> her was to have given thy ſelf freely for her. Thy Majeſtie envied while detain'd from her; If it had been ſhed-abroad amonſt them would have <hi>heald their distempers, and pierced and overcome their hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou haſt <hi>ſlighted</hi> and <hi>neglected</hi> thy body, <hi>not honoured</hi> her; and haſt with-held thy ſelfe and thy favour from thy People in <hi>Generall,</hi> and haſt narrowed thy ſelfe into a <hi>few friends,</hi> and haſt heaped all thy favours upon them. Thou haſt broken the <hi>Marriage knot,</hi> and haſt accepted <hi>others</hi> into thy wives bed to be ſharers in thy Government. Thou haſt refuſed thy Parliament, and haſt admitted into thy boſome and heart of Government, thy Wife, a Woman a Stranger; thy minions, favourites and friends, <hi>Thats thy owne and her Adultery:</hi> Heerin thou haſt proſtituted thy Royalty to every flatterer, and given the ſwaying of the great affaires of your Kingdome, to private and inferiour perſons, who have brought forth, inſtead of Noble and Righteous Lawes, a <hi>brood</hi> of <hi>low jugling</hi> tricks, a <hi>rabble</hi> of Monopolies, Pattents and ſuch brats. True, thou haſt exactly ſerved thy perſonal relations, a loving Huſband, a tender Father, a conſtant Friend; but haſt been ſhort in thy <hi>Office</hi> as a Prince; the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116405:12"/>
               <hi>greatneſſe of a KINGS heart</hi> hath been ſhrunke up and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered into the nature of a private man: And thy private and Domeſticall ſtate hath drowned thy Publike and Royall.</p>
            <p>As thou haſt been defective in love and faithfullneſſe, ſo in ſufficiency and ability of a Head: Thou haſt not <hi>dwelt with her as a man of knoweldge.</hi> There hath been in the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on many high and ſtrong workings of ſpirit towards a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter perfection in <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Justice,</hi> which (though ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with many unholſome vaporus, and clog'd with great weakneſſe) might by an able head have been <hi>digested</hi> (the <hi>evill</hi> being purged out) into good ſpirits, advantagious for the further grouth and increaſe of the body; Theſe are ſpilt, and for want of wiſdome to manage them, the Kingdome ſpilt with them.</p>
            <p>This Nation was of a fruitfull and teeming conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, apt to bring forth <hi>gallant and noble</hi> increaſe of <hi>light, knowledge, government;</hi> great improvement in vertue: which you in weakneſſe of fear and jealouſy laboured to ſtifle, and in a ſuperſtitious opinion of former times, confine this <hi>age</hi> to their example: And <hi>being ſhy,</hi> and not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the waies of God, have left the body to her ſelf, or to other perſons; whence ariſeth this <hi>hideous and misſhapen</hi> birth, in Church and Common wealth. This univerſall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order and confuſion, which the wiſdome <hi>only of the Head, and Father of the family</hi> can, or could, prevent.</p>
            <p>Ile but adde this one, When thou hadſt provoaked thy Parliament into a diſtemper by thy miſ-government, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrangeing thy ſelf from her; then <hi>un-naturally, un-Kingly, irrationally, un-christianly,</hi> to forſake her, &amp; betake your ſelfe to force; an act ſo full of folly, revenge, ſo unbelieving, ſo unlike God as along time durſt not look up, would not bee
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116405:13"/>confeſt: This cropt the ſweet flower of <hi>Englands peace,</hi> broke that great vein from whence ſuch ſtreames of <hi>bloud</hi> have flowed.</p>
            <p>In ſum, The majeſty, juſtice, mercy and goodnes of the <hi>great</hi> God hath not been held forth in thy Government: but hid and buried in thee: their appearing viſibly in thee nothing but the weaknes, inconſtancy, injuſtice, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of vile man.</p>
            <p>Your evils have been great, and ſo are your Judgements: you are fallen into a deep pit of miſery: the chief offender, and the chief ſufferer: great now in nothing but in loſſe and affliction.</p>
            <p>You have ſlain the <hi>Kingly glory,</hi> or the true <hi>glory</hi> of a <hi>King;</hi> and therefore your Authority and dominion muſt needs die: you have laboured to ſave an earthly greatneſſe againſt Heavens diſpleaſure; the onely way to have it ruin'd: to expoſe it to a multitude of ſtroakes of warth.</p>
            <p>You have divided your ſelf from your People, your Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and ſo they become of a help, a <hi>plague</hi> to you, and are by others rent and detained from you. You Idolized your <hi>Wife</hi> and friends, and are therefore ſeperated from them. Blaſted and accurſed in all your attempts. Your <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> is full of <hi>miſeries,</hi> and you the <hi>Center</hi> of them all, and muſt bear in all and for all: Become the ſhame of the <hi>World,</hi> by horrid confuſion and diſtraction. Deprived of all power of <hi>dominion.</hi> Thy Revenue and <hi>dignity</hi> ſhared by others. The majeſty of thy <hi>Government</hi> like a <hi>Potters veſſell</hi> daſht in peeces into <hi>Committees; &amp;c.</hi> Thy Mame wounded, yea, bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried under foul and black <hi>oblique:</hi> become the ſcorne of <hi>Pampletters:</hi> Thy <hi>Prerogatives</hi> and the higheſt priviledges of the Crown, banded and toſſed about the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:116405:13"/>in the mouthes and hands of common men.</p>
            <p>When thou hadſt left the Lord thy ſtabillity, ſee what a race of miſery thou haſt run: When thou didſt leave the Parliament, and wenteſt into the <hi>North;</hi> Thy <hi>Sun ſet,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother roſe in <hi>England:</hi> From that time its a dark <hi>night</hi> with majeſty; &amp; Kinglineſſe is laid upon a <hi>ſick bed,</hi> and thoſe No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles &amp; gentlemen like blazing torches attending upon you: All your waies then were <hi>weak, faint, ſick-ſnatches</hi> at a <hi>Crown,</hi> unnaturall and violent, ſtriving after a fading <hi>glory,</hi> while your <hi>Kingdome</hi> lay wallowing in its own bloud: At laſt the <hi>Lamp</hi> wants <hi>Oyle,</hi> and <hi>Majeſty</hi> dies and <hi>gives up the Ghoſt;</hi> when you left your <hi>Regalia,</hi> your <hi>Seal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Crown, Councel</hi> &amp;c. at <hi>Oxford;</hi> now you indeed put of the ſtate of a <hi>King,</hi> and in the condition of a private perſon, wander as a ſpirit in the <hi>Ayre,</hi> till at laſt found in the North <hi>Apud inferos:</hi> thrown amongſt thoſe leane hungry <hi>hagges</hi> the <hi>Scots,</hi> who <hi>greedily</hi> devour this ſweet <hi>morſel,</hi> a <hi>King:</hi> and in their ambitious and covetous <hi>luſts</hi> prey upon him. Forced amongſt thoſe that he had little before proclaimed traytors and enemies to his Crown and dignity, and were devils in his thoughts to him. heer he is for a while tormented; <hi>mockt</hi> with the title of a <hi>King,</hi> but indeed a <hi>Captive; nipt, ſcurged</hi> and <hi>laſht</hi> with their rebukes; tempted to blaſpheme God in his own <hi>Royaltlty:</hi> and at laſt valued at leſſe then his quoin; ſold for mony into another hell.</p>
            <p>He is reſigned up into other hands, <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> where he is again to be ſqueeſd and wrackt by <hi>Propoſitions</hi> to give up the heart of <hi>Regall power:</hi> ground tween the <hi>Milſiones</hi> of both Nations: not admitted to come to his <hi>Parliament;</hi> but <hi>Holdenby;</hi> thruſt into a corner while others <hi>frolick</hi> in his <hi>Dominion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now hurried into another hell; ſnatched out of this as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116405:14"/>too honorable, and taken away by agitators and common ſouldiers: They muſt have their turn to vex this peece of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery; They that had often chaſed him, purſued him with death, he muſt be their prey, and be carried about as <hi>Army baggage:</hi> They now will have the moulding of him, and will cut out a new garnent of <hi>Royalty</hi> to cover his nakedneſs, But tis ſhrunk in the making, and they have diſpoſed of the cloth to their own turnes.</p>
            <p>Poor wretch, frighted from hence by a new and ſtrange fiend to Regallity, <hi>Levellers:</hi> and after another <hi>Pilgrimage,</hi> he arrives at the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Wight;</hi> where he is again Impriſoned. Labouring to pleaſe his maſters, ſtudying how to content all parties, and ſeeking favour and relief of all, not forbearing <hi>(being in great torment)</hi> to aſk the <hi>Levellers, a drop of water to coole his tongue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At laſt the pit ſhuts her mouth upon him in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments Votes <hi>to make no more addreſſes to him;</hi> which is confirmed by the power of the Army; and ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever rejected as an abominable thing, never to be medled with.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. V.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Shewing the Parliaments errors.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>WHen the <hi>King</hi> had involved himſelfe in difficulties and weary of toyling, to extaicate himſelfe, hee ſeeks at length to lay down his <hi>head</hi> in the lap of the Parliament, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116405:14"/>to ſeek help of his owne Spouſe to compoſe the diſorders of his Family.</p>
            <p>And the Parliament appeares at firſt, aſſiſted by a love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſweet <hi>Angell,</hi> as the tender Mother of all our liberties, as the womb in whom our Civil rights lay; <hi>as Jeruſalem that is from above, the Mother of us all:</hi> having the face of <hi>Jeſus, a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> from all our troubles; ſpeaking nothing but a generall and univerſall love, and a care of all; as a rich treaſury full of all bleſſings that might make us happy: But that <hi>Angell</hi> leaving her, ſhe quickly diſcovers her weakneſſe and inabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and ſinks into confuſion under her ſins, and Divine diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p>Your evils are <hi>againſt Christ, against the King,</hi> and <hi>againſt the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chiefly againſt your <hi>Fundamentall Law,</hi> Chriſt the Sonne of God, who is in you, and with you, and you know him not; yea, deny him, and in expreſſe words, ſcorne his Spirit. You ſome times profeſs for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt, but do indeed <hi>put him to open ſhame;</hi> burying the Wiſdome, Beauty, Righteouſneſſe of Chriſt; and hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth viſibly nothing but an abominable heap of folly, diſorder and unrighteouſneſſe: you are indeed the ſeat of all the fullneſſe of Chriſt, the houſe of God where God would dwell; and ſo a body of <hi>Heavenly wiſdome, religion, justice, goodneſſe,</hi> and everything that is Excellent: But you have departed from this principle, yea, wholly kild it; and walk after the imaginations of your owne hearts, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the cuſtomes of men; yea worſe, after the will and minde of others; not following the ſtable rule, The <hi>Lord;</hi> you are become ſubject to People, City, Scots, Army, any.</p>
            <p>And having loſt the true life and ſpirit of a Parliament,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116405:15"/>the preſence and Majeſty of God; you are become a dead Idol, ſtanding in the power of darkneſſe, in direct oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to God: This poor empty name, this vanity do you with all your might maintain, zealous for your Priviledges, as if all happineſſe lay in them; and while you labour to uphold them, you doe moſt deſtroy them; ſelling your ſelves for relief in any danger to any that can but ſeeme to help you; making your ſelves cheap and common, <hi>mercenary;</hi> and ſo the great betrayers of your own <hi>rights.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In your rebellions againſt the holy God you have trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the ſteps of <hi>your Father the King,</hi> and <hi>in his</hi> may <hi>ſee</hi> your own iniquities.</p>
            <p>But particularly, You are guilty of hipocriſy and deceit in that great pretence of Reformation, ſeeing ſuch a ſpirit acting in the People, to keep them ſure to you; and by that to gaine advantage againſt your adverſaries: you aſſume this title, <hi>The Cauſe of God, and Reformation;</hi> without either love to it, or judgement to know how to go about it.</p>
            <p>Tis known you are men your ſelves unreformed, men of corupt and looſe lives; and that whereupon yon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt moſt, you are moſt guilty of, <hi>Arbitrary power;</hi> every one being in diſpoſe of his eſtate a Tirant, and wrack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Tennants</hi> according to his own will; which is the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſin of the Nation, every one labouring to oppreſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to advance himſelfe: And ſince you came together walking in a continuall courſe of illegall and arbitrary po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. You are groſly ignorant of the Heavenly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, The true Patterne out of which the Kingdome was taken and form'd, and into which it muſt bee Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formd.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:116405:15"/>
            <p>As you want judgement, ſo want you power, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving trampled under your feet the power and Spirit of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> your Ordinances are all ſpiritleſſe, weake and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable.</p>
            <p>But having layd this <hi>Egge</hi> of Reformation, you make this uſe of it, When you want an Army to help you, you carry it to <hi>Scotland</hi> to bee hatched there; and thence it brings forth an imperfect, earthy, crawling Cockatrice, <hi>Presbytery,</hi> which never yet did any good, but vex the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and help your friends to get into fat livings: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you want the help of active men heer of different judgements, they ſit upon the <hi>Egge,</hi> and bring forth liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of conſcience, and with it, a monſtrous heap of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhapen errors and opinions; which you cannot ſuppreſſe by <hi>conviction,</hi> nor dare reſtrain by power.</p>
            <p>The Church, tis true, was extreamly corrupted, full of tyranny, darkneſſe, worldly pride, and great diſorder; But you have brought nothing to it but utter ruine and defacement: Not having that <hi>Spirit of judgement and burning, to ſeperate twixt</hi> the <hi>precious</hi> and the <hi>vile</hi> in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy <hi>&amp;c.</hi> you have in a blinde conformity with <hi>Scotland,</hi> and to ſupply your own needs of their <hi>lands,</hi> untter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demoliſht all.</p>
            <p>Your errors againſt the <hi>King</hi> are, <hi>not following your foundamentall constitution;</hi> He a Huſband, you his body; he a Father, you a Son.</p>
            <p>Hee being plunged in his <hi>government,</hi> and in neceſſity,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:116405:16"/>he cals you together and ſeeks your help; which was a fair opportunity for you by fair carriage and dutifulneſſe to regain his reſtranged heart: but you grow upon his neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and in ſtead of inſinuating into him by love, you at firſt rigidly and harſhly capitulate for priority and privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; and fell into a violent and illegall forcing, the ſword, the <hi>Militia,</hi> out of his hands; a ſtrange and un-naturall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt (having no other <hi>bottom</hi> but jealouſy and feare of <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering</hi>) for the <hi>Wife</hi> or <hi>Sonne</hi> to diſarme the <hi>Husband</hi> or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. You have unkindly, unjuſtly requited his error: who would have <hi>Reigned</hi> without you, made you <hi>ciphers,</hi> and kept the ſubſtance of <hi>Government</hi> from you. You deal ſo with him, would take all <hi>power</hi> from him, and leave him to be a <hi>ſtate ceremony, a great nothing; a gaudy thing ſet out with Titles,</hi> for <hi>pomp</hi> and <hi>faſhion</hi> ſake to be <hi>looked upon;</hi> a <hi>ſervant</hi> having <hi>power to doe neither good nor hurt.</hi> And that which every man as a man <hi>contends</hi> for, to be <hi>Arbitrary,</hi> or to have the exerciſe of his <hi>will,</hi> without which we are the <hi>greateſt ſlaves</hi> in the World; that is wholly denied him in <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Your endeavours is to <hi>impriſon</hi> the <hi>Throne;</hi> to infeeble your <hi>Lord,</hi> and diſable him from doing the <hi>Kingdome</hi> any <hi>good:</hi> ſuch an empty weak <hi>thing,</hi> would be a <hi>heavy curſe to the Nation;</hi> a <hi>diſhonour</hi> and <hi>ſhame</hi> to you, and that which you would quickly be weary of.</p>
            <p>Tis moſt true you have <hi>Royalty</hi> in you in the ſecond <hi>place, being bone of his bone, and fleſh of his fleſh; the expreſſe image of his perſon:</hi> but to ſet up this <hi>above</hi> the <hi>head,</hi> or by this to thruſt out the <hi>other,</hi> is <hi>falſhood,</hi> and <hi>diſloyalty</hi> to your <hi>head:</hi> That any thing in you ſhould live in <hi>diſtinction</hi> from, or <hi>oppoſition</hi> to your <hi>head</hi> and <hi>Father;</hi> tis to <hi>commit Adultry</hi> with your <hi>ſelves,</hi> or <hi>ſhadow</hi> of your <hi>Lord:</hi> to <hi>faſhion</hi> up a <hi>notionall King amongst your ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:116405:16"/>
            <p>When he was departed from you, you ſhould even to <hi>death</hi> have <hi>followed him:</hi> and not <hi>rejoyced in his abſence,</hi> and <hi>ſhut the door upon him:</hi> all <hi>jollity, mirth</hi> and <hi>confidence</hi> in his going was <hi>un-naturall:</hi> Then your <hi>civill life</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> went; and it had been your way to have <hi>loſt your ſelves</hi> with him; or to have ſat as <hi>widow</hi> till you had recovered him.</p>
            <p>When there was in him a minde of <hi>returning,</hi> as at <hi>Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham,</hi> you ſhould then have opened your <hi>hoſomes to him:</hi> but having poſſeſſion of all in your hands, you were <hi>high, peremptory, churliſh</hi> and <hi>froward</hi> towards him, and ſo refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him,</p>
            <p>He hath done you <hi>wrong,</hi> and ſince offered you ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which you have not accepted: but require <hi>unjuſt</hi> and <hi>unreaſonable tearmes:</hi> he offended in perſonall <hi>acts;</hi> but you inſiſt upon <hi>hereditary</hi> ſatisfaction from him and his <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren:</hi> He hath <hi>offended himſelfe,</hi> and <hi>ſuffers for it:</hi> but you would have <hi>reſtitution</hi> from the <hi>Office,</hi> which is <hi>Gods,</hi> and that never <hi>offended.</hi> You have quite loſt that <hi>reverence</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> that is due to him, and <hi>look not upon him as he is in the Book of God:</hi> you <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Head,</hi> and his <hi>Anointed:</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver minding God in him (though <hi>buried</hi> under a heap of <hi>droſſe</hi>) and ſo never durſt put any <hi>confidence</hi> in him or in the <hi>Divine Ordinance:</hi> but looking upon him through the <hi>Glaſſe</hi> of your own weak jealouſies and feares, in which he is ſtill preſented to you, as a <hi>black<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul miſchievous</hi> perſon: you count it the greateſt <hi>ſafety</hi> to keepe at diſtance from him.</p>
            <p>To ſatisfy the People and your owne conſciences, you promiſed to make him the greateſt Prince in the World; and alwaies ſwore and Covenanted to defend his Perſon, honour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſince you have conquered his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:116405:17"/>and gotten all into your poſſeſſion there appears no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but high neglect or him: inſtead of putting any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour on him; becauſe he doth not tamely ſit down under your weak and abſurd frame of government, of Church and common wealth; you impriſon his perſon and honour.</p>
            <p>You have greatly tranſgreſſed againſt the <hi>People</hi> who have intruſted you.</p>
            <p>You have by your folly and weakneſſe, and unworthy managing that truſt committed to you; betrayed the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and greatneſſe of Parliaments into ſcorne and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and for ever (except the hand of God wonderfully appear) ruind and deſtroyed, the Kingdomes great intereſt and the Peoples right, a Parliament.</p>
            <p>You have groſly diſowned the People of <hi>England,</hi> and have been led after others to ſave your ſelves; becoming not ours, but now the Armies; then the Cities; then the <hi>Scots</hi> Parliament.</p>
            <p>You are cut off and diſ-joynted from us; making uſe of us for no other purpoſe, but to bear your intolerable bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of <hi>Exciſe, Taxes &amp;c.</hi> by which yon have almoſt waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us; and minde onely your ſelves: we receive not acts of favour, juſtice, <hi>Peace</hi> or <hi>honour</hi> from you: you doing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing effectually but reward your <hi>own Members:</hi> ſuck and draw into <hi>your ſelves,</hi> the <hi>honour, wealth</hi> and places of the <hi>Kingdome:</hi> the whole <hi>Kingdome</hi> languiſhing in miſery; <hi>you</hi> onely and <hi>ſome</hi> few of <hi>your creatures</hi> getting wealth: Not a <hi>Parliament;</hi> but a trade <hi>now,</hi> a great <hi>Menopoly</hi> of <hi>honour, wealth, Law, dignity,</hi> and every thing that's <hi>good</hi> in the <hi>Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You never would or durſt ſuffer any thing for us; if you would (as by right you ſhould) have <hi>ſuffered</hi> for the <hi>People,</hi> we might have been ſaved from ruine; but you <hi>constantly</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:116405:17"/>it in your ſelves and expoſe us to it: ſo cowardly that you dare not ſtand by your own <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>otes, Ordinances, Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples;</hi> but upon all occaſions for fear <hi>diſert</hi> them, <hi>justice</hi> and us.</p>
            <p>Wee charge you with weakneſſe and inability to manage the affaires in your hands; for want of judgement and ſore-ſight, you have brought your ſelves into a <hi>maze</hi> of <hi>confuſion,</hi> and know not which way to go <hi>either backwards or forwards,</hi> and ſo will loſe your ſelves and us at laſt in a <hi>wilderneſſe</hi> of <hi>woe</hi> and <hi>perplexity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As you waſte our eſtates, ſo are you prodigal of our <hi>bloods;</hi> you never were tender enough of <hi>peace;</hi> but too <hi>forward in war.</hi> As the King was guilty of beginning; ſo you of uphold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>plague</hi> of <hi>war:</hi> as not in ſeeking <hi>peace,</hi> ſo not in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting of it when it was <hi>offered:</hi> eſpecially in continuing of an <hi>Army</hi> in the <hi>Kingdom</hi> when there <hi>was no enemy to hurt;</hi> wherein you ſhewed your diſtruſt of <hi>Gods protection;</hi> &amp; the <hi>Peoples</hi> affection: your feeling the <hi>guilt</hi> of your <hi>unreaſonable</hi> and <hi>unjuſt Government;</hi> which made you keep up <hi>force</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend your <hi>Turkiſh Tyranny.</hi> This being certain, publicke ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice &amp; <hi>righteouſnes requires no protection but it ſelf in a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> Had you <hi>univerſally diſtributed right to all,</hi> and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed peace and righteouſnes you needed no <hi>force.</hi> So that as the King begun the former, you are the beginners of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>war</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and ſo guilty of the blood that is ſhed.</p>
            <p>Your groſſe and conſtant breach of faith and Covenant with all; whereby the <hi>Faith</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> is become a <hi>ſcorne</hi> and reproach; and our expectations of good from you are continually fruſtrated: and for all our loſſes of eſtate and blood we are repayd with nothing hut ſhamefull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion in Church and common wealth.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:116405:18"/>
            <head>Chap. VI</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Shewing the Judgement upon the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>NO <hi>Error</hi> can be ſmall in a Parliament; yours have been exceeding great: and <hi>great evils</hi> muſt bring <hi>great Plagues:</hi> and your <hi>evils</hi> hold propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with your ſins and ſtanding; the greateſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils that can befall ſuch a body as you are.</p>
            <p>Along while you have laboured under the diſeaſe and diſtempers of <hi>blindneſſes, malice, frightings, faction, &amp;c.</hi> waſting by them into faintneſſe and feebleneſſe; and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into many indirect and falſe waies: but at laſt comes your diſſolution, when you were rent and torne a peeces by <hi>women</hi> and <hi>boyes, Apprentices:</hi> forced by them to their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and ſo broken into two peeces, one part <hi>flying, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother part staying,</hi> and both in <hi>armes</hi> one againſt another; ſhewing by open <hi>war</hi> your former inward conteſts: ſo bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as none could tell which was the <hi>Parliament:</hi> neither part (being in deed but parts) able to <hi>challenge the being of the whole Parliament:</hi> the ſtanding <hi>peece</hi> pretends moſt <hi>right;</hi> but the other the beſt <hi>ſword:</hi> this breach not heald, but <hi>ſmothered up:</hi> as they were broken, <hi>ſo compoſed by force:</hi> and ſo to this day they ſtand not a <hi>naturall, free;</hi> but a <hi>violent forced Parliament:</hi> not <hi>bottomb'd</hi> upon Chriſt, or ſtanding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Pillars</hi> of the <hi>Kings</hi> writ, the <hi>Peoples free choyce,</hi> and their own joynt conſent; but as an accurſed <hi>broken Idoll;</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held by neceſſity and <hi>Armies force,</hi> and in profeſſe enmity
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116405:18"/>one againſt another: A body of <hi>death</hi> in the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> ſubſiſting and acting in <hi>Satan;</hi> ſtanding not to ſave the <hi>Nation;</hi> but to be a parpetuall <hi>plague</hi> to themſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. They have the nature of <hi>hell,</hi> a <hi>civill hell,</hi> full of <hi>groſſe darkneſſe;</hi> in <hi>chaines</hi> of <hi>darkneſſe;</hi> in ſuch a thick <hi>mist</hi> they cannot tell how to take one <hi>right ſtep,</hi> but tis into miſery; void of true wiſdome; all their actions <hi>poor petty ſhifts, weak devices,</hi> improper, <hi>independent,</hi> irrational things. Alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy miſerable, undone, labouring under their own &amp; the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> ruin: but ſo <hi>incompaſſed</hi> with miſery, that attempting to get out, they meet with <hi>greater.</hi> The deſtroyer hath the upper hand of them and is their <hi>maſter;</hi> they are in a <hi>pit</hi> of <hi>destruction,</hi> and ſo ſhut up that that which ſhould <hi>ſave</hi> them is <hi>deſtruction</hi> to them. If they <hi>look</hi> to the <hi>King;</hi> their evill conſciences (the great difference tween him and them) aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures them if he come to have power will be revenged of them.</p>
            <p>If they look to the People, they are fild with indignation againſt them. If to the <hi>Army,</hi> thats miſery enough to have the <hi>ſword</hi> to be their <hi>Lord;</hi> they know they then muſt be their <hi>ſlaves;</hi> twere well they could not be; but thats dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full too; and therefore they muſt continue, in the <hi>great wrath</hi> of an <hi>angry God,</hi> who hath left them, &amp; given them up to this <hi>wretched</hi> ſtate; <hi>blaſted</hi> &amp; <hi>accurſed</hi> in every thing they take in hand: ſetting a <hi>stamp</hi> and <hi>marke</hi> of <hi>diſpeaſure</hi> upon all their undertakings; every thing that come forth from them, <hi>ſign'd</hi> with <hi>vengeance,</hi> that we may reade <hi>vanity</hi> and <hi>death</hi> upon all that paſſes from them; and ſo cold and ineffectuall that its buried in neglect, <hi>as ſoon as tis brought forth.</hi> In <hi>great</hi> ſhame and confuſion, fallen from <hi>great honour</hi> and <hi>Majeſty,</hi> to be the ſcorne and contempt of the meaneſt People; utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpoyld of all <hi>renown,</hi> and laid open to the <hi>revilings</hi> of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:116405:19"/>baſeſt. And in hideous confuſion, not knowing where they are; how they come in, or which way to get out; not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſtate of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> or their own affairs; fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a vaſt <hi>wilderneſſe</hi> of numberleſſe <hi>evils,</hi> not knowing how to ſettle <hi>King, People, Army or any</hi> on peece in his right place.</p>
            <p>In perpetuall diſtraction and diviſion, continually gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and paind with the rending of their own bowels being tormentors to themſelves, they need not others to miſchiefe them; if they were alone they would continually miſchiefe themſelves: they are in perfect hatred, and deadly feare one of another: and broke and ſhattered into ſuch variety of <hi>factions</hi> that they can't handſomly ſide; but every ſide hath his ſubdiviſions; and ſo his owne ſide (when he hath joyned to ruin others) will ruin him.</p>
            <p>There is this of hel too, They are reſtleſſe; perpetually <hi>agitated and toſſed</hi> about <hi>from ſide to ſide, from party</hi> to <hi>party; from one thing to another:</hi> full of contradiction to themſelves; <hi>drunke with the wine of the wrath of God,</hi> they <hi>reele</hi> and <hi>ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> to and fro from one thing to another: condemn a thing for <hi>Treaſon</hi> one while juſtify it another: a <hi>King</hi> and no <hi>King;</hi> Vote and un-vote; and that not in triviall, but in the <hi>weightieſt things of the Kingdome,</hi> childiſhly and miſerably uncertain.</p>
            <p>Thus are you, of a remedy, become a wofull diſeaſe; of Saviours, deſtroyers of Church and Common-wealth. Our great fence againſt <hi>tyranny</hi> and oppreſſion, become the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of <hi>tyranny</hi> and opreſſion. Mighty and ſtrong in nothing but to keep miſery and deſtruction together that it leave us not. Evil imbodied; ruine form'd into a ſtate; wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe in a Law; all folly and confuſion inthroning it ſelfe; ſecuring it felſe; and ſitting in the great <hi>Councell of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to contrive for the People <hi>new vexations.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:116405:19"/>
            <p>This is your doom, For leaving <hi>the light and wiſdome of the Lord Jeſus, and for exalting your ſelves above him,</hi> left in wrath, caſt off, and become the <hi>Kings,</hi> your own, and the peoples <hi>hell.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. VII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Shewing the ſin and puniſhment of the people of both parties.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>HAving ſeen the ſin &amp; judgement of theſe two great <hi>earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly powers,</hi> let us <hi>deſcend lower</hi> and view the <hi>People of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> as they are divided by theſe <hi>two heads King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> into <hi>two streames, Round-heads and Cavailiers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You are both deeply guilty of the evil of both your <hi>heads,</hi> and therefore <hi>justly fall into the ſame condemnation:</hi> look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your <hi>King,</hi> and in him ſee your <hi>tranſgreſſions,</hi> and propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably your <hi>ſufferings from a righteous God.</hi> Look you upon your <hi>Parliament,</hi> and in them behold <hi>your wickedneſſe,</hi> and <hi>your just afflictions: you have joynd your ſelves to them, or leand upon them, and are fallen with them; or you upheld them and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported them in their wicked waies, and they are fallen with al the burthen of Gods wrath upon you, and ſo breake you to peeces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But particularly, and beſides theirs, you are guilty,</p>
            <p>Firſt of the ſame things <hi>in a leſſer way:</hi> You are <hi>tyrants and oppreſſors</hi> in your eſtates, in your families; <hi>as husband</hi> &amp; <hi>wife, father and children;</hi> and do all live, <hi>not in the light of God and Chriſt,</hi> but in the <hi>darknes of Satan and this world:</hi> &amp; if you had not <hi>a generall,</hi> you would be devoured <hi>with private vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> the ſame evils being broken forth <hi>upon the world in fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, trades, bargains; deceits, coſonage, ſuites, ſtrife, warrs, jarres, differences;</hi> &amp; <hi>if the light of God appear not for your deliverance</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:116405:20"/>you will bee utterly ruined, and the joy and comfort of theſe things utterly waſted; for the whole frame of things is out of courſe, and there is ſecret curſes ſtolne into all rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and things; which much ſhakes and diſtracts, though not quite over-throwes their peace.</p>
            <p>There is in your taking of parts, blinde zeale, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of God and of the Kingdomes conſtitution, and groſſe Idolizing man. Every one hurrying on in his way without judgement or conſideration; <hi>forgetting God and making fleſh your arme;</hi> mad of your particular Idols, KING and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which now you ſee are empty, vaine and helpleſſe things.</p>
            <p>In taking ſides, you are carried much by <hi>ſinister</hi> and <hi>by reſpects,</hi> each ſeeking to make himſelfe ſomething by the warre, and to advance themſelves whil'ſt they ſeeke to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance their party; all aiming at a worldly and carnall eaſe, proſperity, and preferment; and while you ſtrived to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt your ſelves, you have loſt the <hi>ground and foundation</hi> of all your hopes; and every one ſeeking to make himſelfe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, hath made the whole nothing; in ſeeking to adde to what you had, you have loſt the whole.</p>
            <p>There was alſo much <hi>revenge,</hi> bloudy malice againſt <hi>your neighbours, and malignancy against each other;</hi> thirſty after the ruine of each other, and <hi>glad</hi> of oppertunities of doing miſchief <hi>one againſt another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for theſe wicked things are become partners in the miſery of the <hi>King and Parliament;</hi> as you have their and your owne <hi>ſinnes,</hi> ſo you ſuffer their and your owne <hi>plagues:</hi> Their deſtruction is yours, you can't but be miſerable in their miſery; in their diviſions your very hearts are divided; The <hi>very foundations</hi> are out of courſe; and you are left in a ſtate of calamity without meanes or hopes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:116405:20"/>
            <p>Beſides, The wrath of God is daily waſting of you, and you are waſting one another; the <hi>Nation</hi> becoming ſuch a <hi>hel</hi> of confuſion, that men are Divels one to another; <hi>maligning and hating</hi> each other to death: Theſe waies would utterly waſte you if you had <hi>ten thouſand times</hi> more then you have. The fruit of all your long labours ſweept away from you in a moment by miſchievous <hi>villains;</hi> to have your bread taken from you, and your ſelves, and wives and children ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannized over by free quarterers.</p>
            <p>Honeſt induſtry quite diſcouraged, being almoſt uſe-leſs: moſt men that have eſtates betrayed by one ſide or other, plundered, ſequeſtered. Trading (the life and ſubſiſtance of thouſands) decaying, eaten up with taxes: your poor rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to famiſh, or to riſe to pull reliefe from the rich mens hands by violence: the heavens and earth jarring in unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable weather; and ſummer and winter <hi>fighting together, and invading</hi> each others quarters; which threatens <hi>famine</hi> upon you. Squeeſd by taxes, wrack'd with war, the <hi>anvill indeed</hi> of miſery, upon which all the ſtroakes of <hi>vengeance</hi> fall. A wofull Nation! once the freeſt people in the world, now the verieſt ſlaves: ſlaves not to one, but to many Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; and thoſe many, of <hi>various and different</hi> tempers: by whom you are forced to be ſometimes one way, ſometimes another. And the Church, which is the joy of <hi>Saints,</hi> ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confounded; that none almoſt knows his owne, or his Neighbours Religion; in ſuch a miſt of darkneſſe are you.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:116405:21"/>
            <head>Chap. VIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Shewing the wickedneſſe of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, or Clergy and their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THe <hi>Clergy</hi> (ſo called) have a great hand in the evills of theſe times, and require an eſpeciall diſcovery; But I purpoſe more fully herafter to open the ſtate of the Church, and to ſhew the particular evils and good of every ſect, with their defects, the reaſon of their difference: and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them all to their proper place and order; which is the true <hi>vniformity;</hi> And therefore, ſhall only at this time take notice of them briefly, and as reſpecting theſe evill diſtractions.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Clergy</hi> are deeply concernd, and eſpecially eyed by Divine juſtice: a corrupt generation, and horribly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from their Lord and Rule, Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The Son of God, <hi>the Prophet, the Preſt, the Biſhop,</hi> is the life, original and <hi>true</hi> patterne of al Miniſtry: And there is no true office that Chriſt doth not conſtitute by his owne preſence, nor no right diſpenſation of that office, if Chriſt himſelfe do not adminiſter, and be the thing adminiſtred; and therefore all others are <hi>Antichriſtian and Babylonian,</hi> In whom the Spirit and power of the Holy <hi>Anointing</hi> lives not.</p>
            <p>Its true that the <hi>Clergy of England,</hi> all ſorts of them that have appeared upon this preſet ſtage; <hi>Epiſcopacy, Presbytery
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:116405:21"/>and Independency</hi> have their particular excellencies from particular Angels aſſiſting them. The Biſhops grave, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſteriall Authoratative Honourable; and having <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed</hi> upon them a dark and earthly form of Chriſt, <hi>The great Biſhop;</hi> and of him in his Lordly, or <hi>Royall prieſt-hood</hi> as he is exalted.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Presbyters</hi> being laborious, painfull, zealous, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, affectionate; carrying an image of the Elders and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of the Church.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Independent</hi> delighting in a more particular and intire union with his people, of greater ſtrictneſſe and exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and perſonal care of his flock; is more truely in the Paſtors or Teachers place: But they are all earthly and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, darkning the true light of Chriſt in their miniſtry; and holding forth the name of Chriſt, but not the power; but their owne parts, opinions, readings, humane and weak affections: yea have wickedly departed from their Maſter, and do not worſhip in the <hi>Temple,</hi> in Heaven, in the <hi>new Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem;</hi> but in Aegypt and Babylon of this world, <hi>where the Lord is crucified:</hi> and ſtand at a diſtance from, and enmity to the Spirit of Chriſt. They profeſſe Chriſt in their way; that is in enmity to him, they profeſſe they are not with him nor he with them; <hi>glory in their ſhame,</hi> which is a Worldly, and a Devilliſh life. They are ignorant of heaven; came not from heaven; are not in heaven; neither returne they to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: they judge not things in the light of heaven, nor know things as they are in the <hi>booke of life,</hi> the Scriptures of truth; as they are in the Spirit of God; but as they are written, and ſpoken of in the world: and ſo are blinde guides, and have led the blinde people of this Nation into a ditch of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction on all ſides.</p>
            <p>Their great unlikenes to Chriſt appeares in theſe things,</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:116405:22"/>
            <p>Firſt, Chriſt is Anointed <hi>with the Spirit of God:</hi> he is ſent of God; he comes from the Father: <hi>Hath all power given him in Heaven and Earth:</hi> But theſe men all of them, derive not their <hi>ministry</hi> but from men: at beſt according to the <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward faſhion</hi> of the letter of the <hi>Word,</hi> and ſo from <hi>Paul &amp;c.</hi> and that they <hi>follow</hi> moſt <hi>lamely,</hi> and ſo far only as ſerves their turne; taking indeed their <hi>ministry</hi> themſelves from their <hi>earthly Fathers,</hi> according to the cuſtomes and <hi>traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of men: &amp; therefore have no power at all but the <hi>power of their own reaſon,</hi> which being <hi>weaknes it ſelf,</hi> they preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly run to the power of the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> and ſtrengthen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with that, whithout which they are moſt <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible</hi> and <hi>deſpiſable</hi> things. The <hi>Biſhops,</hi> take away the <hi>King</hi> and what becomes of them? The <hi>Presbyters</hi> if the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> fail, they fall into the <hi>ditch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Chriſt emptied <hi>himſelf</hi> and became of no <hi>repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; took upon him the form of a ſervant:</hi> but theſe men are one all ſides <hi>stickling</hi> for <hi>worldly greatneſſe;</hi> contending by all waies of <hi>cunning</hi> and <hi>policy</hi> to raiſe themſelves to the <hi>higheſt</hi> point of preferment, in their ſeverall <hi>ſpheres,</hi> plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for their <hi>honour</hi> from the <hi>People, urging</hi> and <hi>forcing</hi> from the <hi>People</hi> reſpect to the <hi>Miniſters:</hi> each party in their ſeaſons labouring <hi>might</hi> and <hi>main,</hi> with <hi>blood,</hi> to uphold that <hi>inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt</hi> in the <hi>Nation,</hi> that they have <hi>gotten;</hi> and preſſing upon <hi>mens conſciences</hi> to <hi>fight</hi> for <hi>Religion,</hi> which is, their means, places, honours and ſafeguards.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Chriſt fore-told and <hi>deſired his ſufferings: The Baptiſme that he was to be baptized with.</hi> But theſe men never knew their own or the <hi>Kingdomes ſufferings,</hi> to <hi>give</hi> or <hi>take warning:</hi> but fild with the <hi>viſions</hi> of their own <hi>hearts, prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> pleaſing things in their <hi>ſeaſons:</hi> The <hi>glory</hi> of the <hi>Church; bleſſed</hi> times; <hi>great</hi> and <hi>wonderfull</hi> things. And if their <hi>ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:116405:22"/>hath been declared to them by God, they would not hear it; but as <hi>Peter,</hi> in his ſatanicall pride: <hi>Maſter be it far from thee:</hi> and when they had gotten into the <hi>mount</hi> of <hi>Court</hi> and <hi>Parliament favour,</hi> then they cry, <hi>Its good to be heer;</hi> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horring the thoughts of ſuffering: And would be <hi>reigning</hi> upon the <hi>Throne,</hi> before they <hi>touch</hi> upon the <hi>Croſſe.</hi> Theſe <hi>carnall Goſpellers</hi> are in all their thoughts enemies to the <hi>Croſſe</hi> of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Chriſts <hi>Miniſtry was glory to God on high: on Earth Peace,</hi> &amp;c. But theſe mens is <hi>glory</hi> to themſelves, and to their <hi>King</hi> and their <hi>Parliament,</hi> and for want of this a ſword, fighting; like <hi>Satans</hi> Prieſts, <hi>Preaching</hi> and <hi>ſpeaking</hi> the fire of their <hi>rage;</hi> Pulpit <hi>incendiaries;</hi> pronouncing <hi>curſes</hi> and <hi>judgements</hi> upon their <hi>brethren,</hi> and ſo <hi>giving</hi> them up to the ſword of one another. Prieſts indeed; not to offer up their honours, places, preferments and lives to <hi>purchaſe</hi> peace a Chriſt did: and they ſhould. But have offered up the <hi>Kingdome</hi> a <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> to their own blinde zeale and carnall luſts together. In ſtead of ſtanding in the <hi>gap,</hi> have made a <hi>gap;</hi> and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the diviſions of the times; caſting not <hi>water</hi> to quench; but <hi>Oyle</hi> to inflame the differences of the Nation: not lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down their lives, but ſeeking the lives of others to ſerve their ends.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Your bitter and violent perſecuting each other when you have gotten power into your hands. You have been in your ſeverall ſeaſons the ruine of each other; deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing each other ſubſiſtance, or the exerciſe of each others gifts: Far from the love of Chriſt or his People. <hi>Paul</hi> in caſe of <hi>greater</hi> difference then theſe outward formes of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wiſh'd himſelf <hi>accurſed</hi> for his brethren: but you in the ſpirit of <hi>Satan,</hi> blaſpheme and curſe one another: Both upon falſe and alike hipocriticall grounds. The <hi>Biſhops</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:116405:23"/>tending the <hi>peace</hi> of the Church, <hi>conformity, Oath, ſubſcrepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, obedience to the Kings Lawes.</hi> And the <hi>Presbyters, Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, Covenant, uniformity, and obedience to the Parliaments Ordinances:</hi> but mainly tis your intolerable pride, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bear any to diſſent from you: a conſcience <hi>guilty</hi> of your own weak foundation; that makes you fear that every one will ſupplant you: and earneſt contending for ſelf-honour, ſelf-ſecurity; and wicked <hi>malice</hi> againſt your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
            <p>They are but fellow ſervants, not judgess as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume though they <hi>beat</hi> their fellows. Both ſervants, living at a diſtance from God; in the World; not upon the <hi>Throne</hi> in <hi>Heaven:</hi> and but fellowes; ſet each to do their ſeverall works in their ſeverall waies, and that much upon equall tearmes: though they admire themſelves, and think highly of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and deſpiſe others as of no <hi>uſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But of the two, its moſt ſtrange to ſee the <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> who the other day was oppreſt by the <hi>Biſhop</hi> for his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in point of <hi>Sabbath, &amp;c.</hi> who could not long ſince live without the favour of the <hi>Biſhop;</hi> ſhould now thruſt out thoſe (under whom he lived) for not taking the Covenant; which is contrary to their conſcience; and ſhew leſſe favour to them then he received from them; and doe that which he condemned in <hi>others;</hi> and this upon <hi>weak</hi> and fleſhly <hi>grounds;</hi> admiring his own way, which is to <hi>pray</hi> and <hi>preach</hi> longer and more then another: to be ſtrict in repetitions on <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath daies,</hi> and ſome ſuch poor, formall things: To ſet up this as the power of <hi>godlineſſe</hi> and reformation, to the ruine of another who it may be is a man of more <hi>juſtice, ability,</hi> and wiſdome; more <hi>ſobriety;</hi> more <hi>ſtability;</hi> more <hi>patience,</hi> and conſtancy in <hi>ſuffering.</hi> The perſecution of the <hi>Biſhop</hi> was wicked and abominable: but this being now acting
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:116405:23"/>(and the other part and almoſt blotted out and forgotten by their ſufferings) is eſpecially to be noted.</p>
            <p>Did theſe men live in the largneſſe of heavenly love that comprehends all theſe parties; and in the light and wiſdom of God, who brings forth all theſe out of himſelf, and for his own holy purpoſe manages all in order. The <hi>Biſhops and</hi> the <hi>Presbyters</hi> might <hi>agree,</hi> as well as Chriſt and the Apoſtles: and be ſo far from deſtroying, as they would ſupport each other; did they know that heavenly order, that is in divine things, they might live in as ſweet a <hi>fellowſhip,</hi> as the one <hi>throne of Christ and twenty four Thrones of the Elders</hi> or <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, Rev.</hi> 4. All three might live in one <hi>Family,</hi> as elder and yonger <hi>brethren;</hi> as <hi>Fathers, children and grand-children;</hi> who while they live in <hi>Satan</hi> the accuſer, and in the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the World, they oppoſe and deſtroy each other.</p>
            <p>You are worldly; live in the World, and ſuffer the calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the World: and are partners, great ſharers in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of the Nation: being publick perſons are of publick concernment; theſe evils doe lie in a large and more generall way upon you: in theſe deſolations, the <hi>Prophet that teaches lies he is the tayle:</hi> The lower and baſer kinde of judgements fall upon you; the deep ſcorne of the People: you are caſt out by God from your honour and <hi>glory</hi> as an abominable branch, <hi>as ſalt wanting ſavour,</hi> to the Dunghill.</p>
            <p>Whats become of the Epiſcopall glorious Church, his lordly <hi>Palaces, ſtately worſhip,</hi> adorn'd <hi>Temples, great Revenues?</hi> Made <hi>deſolate torne in peecs,</hi> left to the <hi>Satire, Schrich-owle,</hi> to <hi>Zim</hi> &amp; <hi>Gim;</hi> under what a hideous curſe do they lie? What's become of the <hi>great Reformation</hi> of the other party that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed ſuch glorious daies: pure <hi>Ordinances;</hi> power of <hi>godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes? become a breach in a wall; a rotten and putrifid ſore; abotch; a filthy iſſue:</hi> nothing appears in it but wretched diſorder:
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:116405:24"/>their eyes ſinke in their heads while they look for ſalvation: they inwardly <hi>cut themſelves</hi> as <hi>Baals Prieſts,</hi> crying to God to deliver them, and finde no reliefe but ſcorne; tormented with feares to be torne in peeces by the people.</p>
            <p>Paleneſſe and blackneſſe fills your faces, and horrour and confuſion you ſpirits on both ſides; To ſee your world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly glory burning in the fire of Divine jelouſy; your Idols broken to pouder &amp; caſt into a Sea of confuſion, your fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beauty <hi>eaten up with worms</hi> of <hi>rottenneſſe</hi> and putrefacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: To ſee your confidences in your Idols rejected; your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying lyes of a glorious time, by Gods hand confuted; your faſtings and multitude af ſolemne prayers caſt as dung in your faces, not regarded: your zealous covenants wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you thought to ſave your ſelves, broken in peeces and trampled under foot; your much admired worſhips <hi>of Directory and Service-booke, Creeds, Confeſſions, Articles,</hi> of no profit; uſe-leſſe and helpleſſe things, laid by the wals, ſcornd and deſpiſed: your Churches and People taken from you, ſcattered ſeverall waies: your gifts dying in you, or dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their uſe, and ineffectuall.</p>
            <p>The Church which is heaven, ſhining in the light <hi>and</hi> preſence of God, in unity peace and order, in holineſſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and righteouſneſſe; through your dark and wicked government, through your weaknes, worldlines, and want of Divine power and wiſdome, become a curſed field o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-run with <hi>thistles, briers and thornes;</hi> a wildernes full of <hi>wild beaſts;</hi> a hel full of blaſphemies, malice, revilings, ſcornings, deriſion, railing, errors, miſtakes, heriſies of all ſorts: the greateſt pillars of truth, <hi>Trinity, Father Son</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> Chriſt his death, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> defaced with foule er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors; ſo many, ſo various, ſo abundant, as it is a confuſed heape of folly and madnes; and coming in upon you in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:116405:24"/>ſuch a torrent that they drown you; and are ſo high and prevalent that not a man of you dares, or can appeare in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny power or ſtrength againſt them; but are forced to lye-down and expoſe <hi>the truth,</hi> your crown, if ever you had any, <hi>to be ſtamped in the dirt by them.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. IX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Shewing the iniquity of the Army and its judgement.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THE Army, though but a branch of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and a particular part, yet in theſe civill warres the power of the <hi>ſword</hi> hath been <hi>great,</hi> and got the upper hand of the <hi>Civill.</hi> The <hi>Army</hi> deſcended from the Parliament as its <hi>Childe,</hi> but the Parliament growing old and weake, and leand ſo long upon the treſſels of the Army that its power at laſt, <hi>ſunk into the Army:</hi> (manifeſt in the Members flying to the Army in its approach to <hi>London.</hi>) The power or the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>head,</hi> fell into the <hi>breaſt and ſhoulders,</hi> the Parliament; and thence deſcended into the <hi>legs, the Army;</hi> but there they make a ſwelling diſeaſe quickly, and ſhew themſelves to be in an un-naturall courſe.</p>
            <p>The Army a company of honeſt and active men, fitted excellently by a ſtrong <hi>Angell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> for the work they were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to: under whoſe conduct they diſpatcſht their buſineſſe ſpeedily, and honourably; walking in waies of juſtice, cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, induſtry, love, mercy, they were favoured with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:116405:25"/>mirable ſucceſſe; relieving the Kingdome from war. And while they were contented with their ſtate, the condition of ſervants to the Parliament, they ſhined in honour and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation (though malignd and envied) while their maſters daily impaired: I hey ſhine in the eyes of the Nation, and were the peoples hopes; yea an Idol, upon whom many had placed their confidence of a worldly deliverance.</p>
            <p>When the Parliament, or a party of them, in ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and malice againſt the favours God beſtowed on them, would have them diſbanded, as ſtanding in the way of ſome malicious deſigne; They united, imboldned, and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened <hi>by their just and honeſt intentions,</hi> refuſe; and ſo grew to be a body of their owne, independant; and to ſtand upon their owne bottom.</p>
            <p>For a while they appeare in this forme very faire and cleare, Propoſing honeſt and generall good, fixing <hi>upon juſt and good things;</hi> and obtaine (by the aſſiſtance of <hi>their good Angell</hi>) ſucceſſe againſt their adverſaries: But alas, <hi>How ſhort lived is thy goodneſſe?</hi> A very morning dew that preſently paſſes. Thou haſt only the power to <hi>propoſe</hi> and <hi>offer good,</hi> but <hi>none to performe;</hi> or a ſcourge to others, <hi>a ſickle</hi> to cut <hi>down</hi> the <hi>withered King</hi> &amp; Parliament but no power to build up: when thou didſt begin a new frame, thy folly, ſelf-love, in-juſtice worldlines quickly appeares; and thou art left and forſaken in the ſame pit of darknes with others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thy Iniquities and Judgements are,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Thou waſt ignorant of the preſence of the <hi>Lord of Hoſts</hi> with thee, and of that extraordinary power that guided thee: thou didſt talk of it, but falſly; and didſt not ſimply and abſolutly follow the LORD, and walk in his power; but didſt mingled <hi>God and Baall,</hi> do things haltingly and imperfectly; in baſe fear, reſpect and ſtooping to men:
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:116405:25"/>and declining the <hi>noble, high</hi> actings of the Spirit of God, didſt <hi>conſult with fleſh and bloud,</hi> with ſenſe and reaſon, worldly cuſtomes and wayes; which diſabled thee to bring forth any excellent or honourable thing: Thou durſt not truſt in GOD alone, but deceitfully turnd away from him to thy own ſenſe and reaſon.</p>
            <p>Thou weart weak and unable to manage the affaires of ſtate in this ſtorme in which it is; but being called to it, haſt in thy inſufficiency brought it to another, and worſe wrack.</p>
            <p>Thou undertookeſt a work beyond thy power, and loſeſt thy ſelf and the Kingdome by it: When the Nation lay at thy door begging for reliefe, and thou hadſt an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to reſtore it, a prize in thy hand and kneweſt it not: But dideſt ſtifle, and by unbeliefe and carnall policie ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the wiſdome and power of the Lord in thee, and not ſuffer him to come forth for the Nations ſalvation; but bring forth thy own fooliſh waies to the Nations farther ruine.</p>
            <p>When thou begun thy work through fear of the Kings party (whom thou hadſt conquered and brought to thy feet) thou didſt weakly and without judgement, take up the King in his filthy curſe, and as a peece of a ruind wall, to ſtrengthen your ſelves: and when you had fouly promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, you as fouly brake with him; and ſo become guilty of all his iniquity in taking him un-waſht; and of his unjuſt ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in leaving of him.</p>
            <p>When you had broken the Parliament, trampled up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, defiled its authority, beſmeared it with your diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, diſhonoured it, inſlaved it by force; you then in hope to ſecure your ſelves by it, in confidence in it, ſet up this broken Idol againe in all its maſſe of folly and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:116405:26"/>injuſtice and oppreſſion; without giving any ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to God or man.</p>
            <p>You in oppoſition to the Spirit of the Lord, that is pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down worldly power, <hi>ſet them up, patch and bodge them together in a confuſed and broken way; and ſet your ſelves to heal the breaches that God makes;</hi> and ſo ſtand in the way of <hi>Divine diſpleaſure to be conſumed by it.</hi> And now imploy your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, which God ſet to pull down unjuſt and corrupt powers (in which you did prevaile) <hi>to uphold and maintaine thoſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers no whit better</hi> (in which you cannot prevaile) your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my is now the <hi>girdle of ſtrength</hi> that holds together <hi>the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, and oppreſſing power of Parliament:</hi> or the <hi>fence, and wall</hi> to keep out the <hi>vengeance of God</hi> from coming farther in upon men; and it is ſo far from <hi>keeping it out,</hi> that it keeps <hi>vengeance in, or upholds them in a state of wrath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You, when you were lifted up, <hi>begun to pleaſe your ſelves, to admire and bleſſe the Army; to magnify your ſelves as the Kingdomes Lords and conqerors; to make your Army intyre; to conceive a neceſſity of continuing an Army, to get preferments in it; to bethinke your ſelves of living richly in it; of recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Pay and arreares:</hi> And upon theſe grounds to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue the Army upon the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> with taxes and free-quarter; the greateſt oppreſſion that <hi>England,</hi> or any other <hi>Nation</hi> ever bore: ſo that now you are the <hi>laſt, and heaviest</hi> of the <hi>Nations</hi> burthens; that promiſed to ſave and deliver, <hi>and turne the greateſt Tyrants; loſe all the good you have done; ſet up a forcible Government; turne warre into a trade, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land into a Campe; perpetuate desteruction, and provoak new commotions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have at laſt, deceived all parties; promiſed <hi>much,</hi> but <hi>done nothing;</hi> broken your word; fruſtrated all expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of good from you: become a <hi>broken reed,</hi> which while
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:116405:26"/>men <hi>leand upon, runne into their hands;</hi> and ſo become of a remedy a <hi>great diſeaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You <hi>judgement</hi> is the ſame with your Mother, <hi>the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament;</hi> and with all Power upholding it ſelfe, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining it ſelfe <hi>in enmity to God;</hi> Accurſed of God: your ſtanding is in the darkneſſe of Satan and the World. The <hi>King in the pit;</hi> the Parliament the <hi>pit it ſelf of confuſion;</hi> and you <hi>ſhut the mouth of it;</hi> the Porters of this <hi>Nationall hell;</hi> to keep them in torment that are there; to <hi>conjure downe</hi> thoſe keep them in torment that are there; to <hi>conjure downe</hi> thoſe ſpirits that would come forth by theſe <hi>riſings;</hi> and to ſet bounds to this <hi>Sea of confuſion</hi> that it do not over-flow: The rock againſt which <hi>theſe proud waves</hi> daſh themſelves in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; the walls to contain, and inſtruments to inflict evill on the People; <hi>againſt which they continually fome and fret:</hi> or the fetters and ſhakels of the <hi>Nation</hi> in priſon <hi>under you:</hi> the <hi>chaine</hi> in which the <hi>mad Kingdome</hi> is bound and tied: for their folly and rage you are to inflict more <hi>evill on them;</hi> and becauſe they will not bear what is laid on them patiently, <hi>you are to lay on more;</hi> and as you <hi>lay plagues on them;</hi> ſo you receive ſome <hi>blowes from them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo are <hi>ſunke</hi> from that great favour <hi>to be the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes hope, a ſaviour,</hi> to be a <hi>jaylor;</hi> vexing and being vexed: able to keepe men in miſery, but in no way at all to deliver them.</p>
            <p>And to this are you tied and bound. A way of peace and quietneſſe hath been ſet before you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; <hi>that way of peace you have not known;</hi> but being inſnared and caught <hi>in this net</hi> of trouble, you are <hi>ingaged by honour, ſelf-preſervation</hi> &amp;c. to go on in this helliſh trade.</p>
            <p>You are in darkneſſe and know not which way to goe; having got a courſe of fighting, you <hi>go on to fight,</hi> for you know not who, nor what: Not for the Parliament; you
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:116405:27"/>know if ever they have opportunity, they will remember your war againſt them, and make it Treaſon: and if you had the ſame opportunity you would doe as much for them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain as you have done; maſter them. So your cauſe is loſt: and you only fight becauſe you are an Army; <hi>becauſe fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is your buſineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All that you did in your greateſt undertaking againſt the Parliament and City is blaſted and undone: <hi>Members resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Houſe;</hi> the <hi>Tower</hi> in the ſame hands it was; which <hi>writes vanity</hi> upon your proceedings: and ſhewes what foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <hi>builders you were,</hi> that when you had <hi>power</hi> in <hi>your hand</hi> inſtead of <hi>doing good too and for all, you minded nothing</hi> but your own, and your <hi>friends advancement;</hi> having indeed not the <hi>generall nature of the whole,</hi> but the <hi>affection</hi> of a party and faction. Your <hi>waies are not now paved with love and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> as heer to fore: but full of <hi>briers and thornes:</hi> your <hi>work hard and knotty,</hi> meeting with a <hi>fierce, bloody, inraged Enemy, ſharpned and provoaked againſt you,</hi> by a ſenſe of their own and the <hi>Kingdomes ruine: harſh and angry weather.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>True, you have ſubſiſtance ſtill: but not in <hi>honour, peace, greatneſſe;</hi> but in <hi>war, in vexation:</hi> and that <hi>increaſing</hi> ſo faſt upon you, as threatens your <hi>overthrow,</hi> or at leaſt ſhew you ſo much <hi>worke</hi> to doe, that you muſt go on <hi>butchering men</hi> as <hi>long as you live:</hi> for as faſt as one <hi>party is cruſht</hi> another riſes: that tels you the <hi>ſpirit of the Nation is against you</hi> and that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing power upheld by you: ſo that you muſt fall under their <hi>fury,</hi> or the <hi>Nation</hi> be <hi>conſumed</hi> by you: either you muſt give <hi>way</hi> to their <hi>rage,</hi> which you can't; or continue to be the <hi>ſcourge</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> ſtill; a <hi>wretched life:</hi> This <hi>Woolfe</hi> you have by the <hi>ears</hi> in this <hi>dark</hi> and <hi>black path</hi> you walk in.</p>
            <p>If you think you are well becauſe you live, becauſe you are not come to nothing; you know, not to be an <hi>Army,</hi> or to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:116405:27"/>be in the <hi>cnodition of private perſons</hi> would be your mercy; but you are ingaged to bee in diſhonour, in warre, ſhame, tormentors and being tormented.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. X.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Shewing the ſtate of the Levellers.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THe <hi>Levellers</hi> are men that are <hi>justly ſenſible</hi> of the miſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of all that are gon before them, ſee &amp;c their corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, how they have <hi>ſwarved and declined,</hi> &amp;c thats <hi>not heard;</hi> but in applying a remedy, they are as much miſtaken as any. His excellencies is not great; aſſiſted he is by a <hi>diſcerning An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell,</hi> that diſcovers the falſhood, injuſtice and wicked waies of others; and opens this truth more then any, how all po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and authority aſcends out of the People; or deſcends from the People; making <hi>in a kinde</hi> them the chiefe: But alas, this <hi>Angell</hi> is low and weak that ſpeakes and writes in a corner; but come forth into action he cannot; but ſinkes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the fall of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and his own <hi>mistake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thy errors are theſe,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou canſt not bear the Kingdomes ſuffering under the hand of God, nor thy owne; but in a <hi>carnall love of this world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtate,</hi> ſeekeſt to uphold it againſt the juſtice of God; and ſo falleſt into the ſame evil of thy Fathers, ſelf-love and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, in enmity to the LORD. To ſave thy ſelf, that the <hi>over-flowing ſcourge may not come nigh thee;</hi> thou makeſt <hi>a Covenant with hell,</hi> and <hi>an Agreement with death:</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:116405:28"/>the <hi>Agreement of the People,</hi> who are turned by the Divine juſtice <hi>into a hel and death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou art ignorant of that wiſdome of God, that only can ſave the <hi>Nation;</hi> and having gathered ſome ſcraps of <hi>earthly knowledge</hi> from others, thy proud heart is lifted up, and thou conceiveſt highly of thy ſelf, as if thou art able <hi>to ſave the Kingdome;</hi> and ſo preſumeſt upon that which thou art not called unto.</p>
            <p>Tis true, The <hi>King</hi> is by the <hi>People;</hi> and <hi>the People are the originall of power:</hi> but this is an imperfect peece; and take it <hi>alone</hi> it is very deſtructive. The <hi>King</hi> is of the <hi>People;</hi> ſo is <hi>Man by the Woman;</hi> yet the Woman muſt not ſhake off her <hi>yoke of ſubjection; For as the Man is by the Woman, ſo the Woman is of the Man, and for the Man:</hi> ſo the People are <hi>taken out of the King,</hi> and are <hi>for the King;</hi> as well as the KING <hi>by the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>KING and Parliament are, in relation to the people, <hi>as Chriſt to David;</hi> He is the <hi>root and of-ſpring of David. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> Son, yet <hi>Davids</hi> Root; and <hi>David in ſpirit calls him Lord.</hi> So is power in <hi>King or Parliament;</hi> the <hi>root</hi> and <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring</hi> of the People. The <hi>King</hi> is Son to the People, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too; and <hi>ſo in ſpirit is called Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>While you take one part in darkneſſe and leave the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you confound and diſorder the whole.</p>
            <p>In your actings (to ſet up a worldly power <hi>now</hi>) <hi>you are of the earth earthly:</hi> The <hi>Nation</hi> ground to powder, or duſt: <hi>duſt thou art, and to dust</hi> &amp;c. the Serpents meat. You confeſs no Father, acknowledge none above you; and therefore art, <hi>Terroe-filius;</hi> or <hi>filius populi;</hi> Son of the Earth; or Son of the People. The baſe Son of the <hi>Parliament; begotten in her A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery;</hi> growing out of her principles: <hi>The people muſt not be left without a remedy to ſave themſelves</hi> &amp;c. Self-ſaviours;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:116405:28"/>your cry is the People; all power is diſolved, and the people muſt judge. <hi>Tis according to your wiſh:</hi> the people in divers parts do take the power; and above all, would mine you; their greateſt <hi>indignation</hi> is againſt you: ſo you <hi>runne from God to hell for help.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tis your portion to ſuffer in the common calamity, and to be as mad men, ſtriving with your <hi>fetters</hi> as <hi>a Bull in a net,</hi> toyling your ſelves: or <hi>agitators</hi> not reſting quietly in the <hi>grave</hi> of publicke miſery, waiting for a <hi>reſurrection:</hi> but <hi>disturbed, agitated duſt in a whirlewinde of divine wrath.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. XI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Shewing the Judgement of the City of London.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> the chief and <hi>Mother</hi> City of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; hath been the place of reſidence of the great <hi>glory</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> the houſe that gives <hi>entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to the head the <hi>King,</hi> and body the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> and theſe floriſhing together in <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſſe:</hi> The <hi>Heaven wherein theſe dwell, and chiefly ſhine forth themſelves:</hi> The habitation of theſe <hi>Majeſties,</hi> in which they are comprehended: That is inriched by them with <hi>honour, ſtate, greatneſſe;</hi> and doth again ſupply and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich them with plenty of <hi>cloaths, food,</hi> &amp;c. And thou haſt held up thy head high in theſe times, and been mightily preſerved by a <hi>great Angell</hi> in thy many dangers.</p>
            <p>Thy evils of ſinne and puniſhment are; beſides the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:116405:29"/>guilt and plagues of the Nation.</p>
            <p>Thou art wholly ignorant of thy heavenly <hi>originall;</hi> thy true foundation upon which thou ſtandeſt: <hi>The new Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem that is from above.</hi> Neither haſt thou ſhined with that bleſſedneſſe and holineſſe; but upheld a worldly and dive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh darkneſſe, and ſo art become a filthy <hi>Sodome;</hi> a vile and poluted thing; living not as the <hi>Lambs wife;</hi> but in filthineſs of <hi>adultery,</hi> with the <hi>pomp</hi> and <hi>greatneſſe</hi> of the World: glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying in thy own <hi>Riches, Power, Multitude,</hi> and not in the Lord.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt been <hi>proud</hi> and lifted up, and every way haſt vaunted and boaſted of thy <hi>government, Militia, wiſdome</hi> &amp;c. and haſt boldly preſſed into the <hi>Throne</hi> of the <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome;</hi> and at pleaſure haſt interpoſed <hi>authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively</hi> beyond thy place: Common Citizens in great confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of their ability to rule the ſtate, buſily intermedling in things much above their underſtandings, and quite out of the ſphere of their callings.</p>
            <p>You have often given check both to King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and lifted up your head above the power of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> and that <hi>raſhly, effeminately,</hi> and without judgement; in <hi>rude, bold,</hi> violent and tumltuous waies.</p>
            <p>You have not in a Mother wiſdome and moderation en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured the compoſing theſe differences, it was thy place to ſpread thy Armes of love to imbrace both King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, to have incloſed and begirt them both in unity: But thou haſt headily, paſſionately, according to thyſex engaged with the Parliament, and wert far too eagar and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate in promoting war; and partiall in thy affection and laying out thy ſtrength.</p>
            <p>Tis thy property to be rich: and wanting it in a naturall and juſt way of trade; you are many of you turned Officers,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:116405:29"/>publicans, Exciſe men, others buying <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Iriſh Lands:</hi> an unnaturall way of <hi>Merchant adventurers;</hi> to ſtrive to catch the ruines of the Kingdome as they fall; or to <hi>grow rich</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on publick miſeries; this is un-bleſt wealth: there is a curſe followes it.</p>
            <p>Thou ſuffereſt deeply in the <hi>common calamity:</hi> and the <hi>ſpoyling</hi> and plundering in the <hi>Nation,</hi> muſt be put upon thy <hi>accompt;</hi> thou art <hi>pillaged</hi> in moſt parts of the <hi>Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>great</hi> and intolerable loſſe of <hi>King</hi> &amp; <hi>Court</hi> to ſhine in thee in peace &amp; <hi>righteouſnes; proena damni:</hi> the peſence of the King in thee, <hi>living in agreement with his People is thy true life and glory, and makes thee a heaven;</hi> and the want of it is to thee intolerable and makes thee a <hi>Hell.</hi> After the recovery of this <hi>happineſſe</hi> doeſt thou inſatiably thirſt, and canſt not live without <hi>re-enjoyment of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thy <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>reward</hi> hath been ſtained; thy <hi>greatneſſe</hi> brought down by the <hi>Army.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thy trade is loſt and broken; thy <hi>wealth</hi> waſting and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming: there is ſtretched out upon thee, <hi>The line of confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the ſtones of emptineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou art continually ſhaken with fears and indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>toſſed</hi> about as a <hi>Ball,</hi> unſtable and uncertain.</p>
            <p>Fires of <hi>diviſions kindled</hi> and burning fiercely in thee, in all thy meetings common Councel, common Hall, Nothing but <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>brimſtone; bitter and ſharp conteſts, horrible rage one against another, ſpitting fire in the face of each other;</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring for the <hi>deſtruction</hi> of one another.</p>
            <p>The wants of the poor threatning to tear out thy <hi>bowels;</hi> a <hi>heap of diſorder</hi> and <hi>confuſion, acting</hi> in all <hi>things</hi> in <hi>darkneſſe</hi> and <hi>wrath,</hi> and ſo art of the nature of the Kingdome in the deſtroyer: and a particular <hi>hell</hi> of thy ſelf and to thy ſelf: mighty in <hi>malice;</hi> rich in <hi>madneſſe;</hi> tis thy trade and buſines
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:116405:30"/>having little elſe to doe, but to deſign miſchiefe to torment thy ſelf.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. XII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Shewing the irrecoverableneſſe of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> ruine by humane waies.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>ENgland</hi> thou art loſt, for ever <hi>loſt:</hi> Thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from God who is thy life; and now thou art dead: <hi>Rejected</hi> into deſtruction. The <hi>Peace, Wiſdome, Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe of God</hi> hath left thee; and the <hi>madneſſe, wrath, injuſtice, and malice of Satan fils thee:</hi> Thou art broken like a <hi>Potters veſſell</hi> into ſhivers, into many <hi>peeces:</hi> Thou art nothing but <hi>diviſion: head</hi> from <hi>body, limb</hi> from <hi>limb:</hi> and each <hi>party</hi> hath a <hi>peece</hi> of thee; thou art by <hi>divine juſtice</hi> diſtributed and <hi>given forth</hi> into ſeverall <hi>intereſts:</hi> The King hath his part. The Parliament their part. The Army another, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and each an <hi>eſſentiall</hi> or <hi>integrall</hi> part, without which the whole cannot ſubſiſt.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſeverall principles, or ſpirits of the <hi>Nation;</hi> are by the <hi>breath</hi> of God blown into the ſeverall parts of the earth; ſcattered into the <hi>four winds;</hi> as much divided as <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt, North</hi> and <hi>South.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And all parts have diſtinct <hi>natures</hi> given to them, ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>principles</hi> of ſelf-ſubſiſtence, which ſets them a contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for their own being: yea, ſuch beings as can never be
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:116405:30"/>nulled, ſtanding upon the unmovable <hi>pillars</hi> of the <hi>decree of God,</hi> and of the <hi>constitution</hi> of the Kingdome: eſpecially in the great diviſion of King and Parliament: both muſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt. Tis as impoſſible to deſtroy Kinglineſſe wholly, or to ſettle <hi>England</hi> without a King; as tis to overthrow the firſt perſon God the Father: if Heaven would diſpence, yet the earth would not; King being as naturall unto us, as a <hi>head</hi> to the <hi>body.</hi> King is <hi>engraven</hi> in the ſpirit of the <hi>Nation.</hi> If it were conſumed to ten men they would have a King: if the Nation were ſhrunk into one Family, they would he <hi>go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned</hi> by a King.</p>
            <p>Upon the ſame <hi>ground</hi> ſtands the Parliament; you may pull Chriſt out of <hi>Heaven,</hi> as well as overthrow the <hi>intereſt</hi> of Parliament: it may be ſuſpended a while, but quite ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed it cannot; Chriſt will eternally uphold it; ſo the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will perpetually and reſtleſly require it; it being the heart and life of the Nation.</p>
            <p>The diſtinct natures or principles are ſtrongly confirmed by <hi>Covenant, Oath, conſcience, honour,</hi> on all parts, whereby the Perſons in whoſe hands theſe intereſts are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> are engaged to maintain and uphold their particulars to death.</p>
            <p>And ſo bound to maintain their own (both at a diſtance from God, and from each other) as while they ſave it they loſe it: being in the dark ſeperated from God, to continue it, is its certain death: ſo that it muſt be and they will have it; and in the way it is, it cannot but be miſerable.</p>
            <p>But theſe parties are not only thus divided one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but inplacably ſet to deſtroy one another, in deadly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition one to another; and ſo inſtead of being each others life (as they ſhould) they are each others death, ſtanding directly in the way to each others happines; each perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that they might be well if their adverſaries were gon;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:116405:31"/>There is a good and an evill in both; the good of each is hid from the other, and turned away the <hi>bright ſide, the face;</hi> and the <hi>back-parts, the weakneſſe, the foule part</hi> in view and ſight of each other. The <hi>Kings party ſay,</hi> if it were not for this Parliament and <hi>Army,</hi> the Kingdome would be happy: the Parliament and Army ſay, if it were not for <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers</hi> the <hi>Kingdome</hi> would be happy.</p>
            <p>Being deſperatly <hi>with mortall hatred</hi> enraged one againſt another, they heartily ſeeke the deſtruction of each other; and in deſtroying each other, they do deſtroy them ſelves; for <hi>indeed, they are the mutuall health and welfare of each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The KING it he could ruine the Parliament, ſhould but deſtroy his own body; himſelf in another; <hi>his own fleſh:</hi> and the Parliament in deſtroying the KING, deſtroy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>in their head.</hi> The Parliament have <hi>conquered the King;</hi> but have gotten <hi>onely</hi> this by it, to be a confuſed head-leſſe heap; and <hi>put off their naturall head,</hi> to put on another; to be <hi>headed by an Army,</hi> a <hi>faction:</hi> and if the <hi>King</hi> ſhould doe as much, <hi>and conquer the Parliament,</hi> he would be unhappy in it; and he would be the head, <hi>not of a body,</hi> but a confuſed rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; <hi>not a King indeed, but a friend:</hi> his party would <hi>Levell with him,</hi> and expect to be Kings with him: he would be in as great a confuſion without a <hi>Parliament,</hi> as the Parliament without the <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As they are broken, divided, ſet in enmity, and malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy one againſt another; ſo are the parts diſordered. The <hi>head,</hi> the King laid in the <hi>bottom;</hi> the Parliament upon him; the Army hath been, and when occaſion ſerves, can be <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permost.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Kingdome ſtands upon his head; The Parliament came forth of the King; and Army forth of Parliament:
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:116405:31"/>now the King can't come forth but it muſt bee from the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> as the <hi>Parliament</hi> comes forth of the <hi>Army.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Divided and ſubdivided; broken into King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; Parliament and Army; Army and City; City and Parliament; <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland. Scotland</hi> their diviſions; <hi>Ireland</hi> divided from both, and ſubdivided amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. But the <hi>deſtroyer</hi> hath moſt ſhewed his cunning in our diviſions; ſo perfectly and artificially are we <hi>intangled,</hi> and <hi>perplext</hi> in diſtractions, as there is no eſcaping.</p>
            <p>The KINGS party divided, and ſome fallen in with the <hi>Scotch and Presbyterian,</hi> which they perfectly hate and yet are joyned to them. Others rather chuſe to ſit ſtil; or have better love to the <hi>Independent intereſt:</hi> &amp; ther's another con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction in diſlike &amp; <hi>diſ-junction. The Parliament</hi> is divided ſome look back to the KING; others had rather ſtand againſt him; both jealous of him, yet forced to looke towards him: The <hi>Presbyterian</hi> joyning part to the <hi>Cavaliers,</hi> and part to the <hi>Independent;</hi> and both hating thoſe they joyne too: The City falling to peeces too. Thus doth <hi>God ſhake the Nations;</hi> jumbles their principles together; ſcatters them as <hi>dried bones</hi> that none knows whether to go to joyne.</p>
            <p>The King is ſhut up in his pit, in his priſon, under the Army and Parliament; he muſt make his way through their blood to come to the Crown: and when he hath done that, he muſt again ruine thoſe <hi>by whom he riſeth, the Scots;</hi> and when he hath done that he is yet but miſerable; and is worſe <hi>then where he is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Parliament muſt goe through the Kings party to their end by the Army; and when they have done that, they muſt ruine the Army and Independent, <hi>intolerable to them;</hi> and then they arrive but at confuſion.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:116405:32"/>
            <p>The Army muſt deſtroy the Kings party firſt, and then the Parliament; and at laſt it gains <hi>nothing</hi> but to be a <hi>wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The City muſt ruine the Kings party; or elſe <hi>wo be to them,</hi> and the Independent too, or elſe they can have no ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and then the Parliament and they may have leaſure to fight alone.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hambletons Scots</hi> have the <hi>Engliſh Nation</hi> wholly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy before they can come to his end; both <hi>Army, Parliament</hi> and KING; and their own Nation at home. And what then? Then there will be roome to fight with the <hi>Iriſh:</hi> ſo that wee are involved in deſtruction, ſhut up under ſeverall <hi>locks and bolts:</hi> and to get out of one, is but to be out of a leſſe into a greater or larger hell.</p>
            <p>Therefore its impoſſible to recover your ſelves by force; you may wraſtle and tug with your fates, and weary your ſelves with toyling, but by all you will but ſink your ſelves deeper; and by your falſe hipocritical and unnaturall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions of <hi>heterogeneous bodies</hi> make new matter of differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and increaſe your own miſery.</p>
            <p>Neither can a <hi>Treaty</hi> compoſe you in the condition in which you are; you are in <hi>death,</hi> and under the <hi>curſe,</hi> and all your actions are, and ſhall be accurſed.</p>
            <p>The Nation is not only broken, but as dried bones, have loſt <hi>their marrow of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, their ſpirit of Love;</hi> it hath nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>fleſh of ſoftneſſe and gentleneſſe, nor ſinews of agreement.</hi> Neither doth there appeare that wiſdome and ſkill <hi>to binde up theſe breaches.</hi> King loſt, diſabled; Nobles ſcattered, weake inconſiderable things; Commons diſtracted, hurried after their vaine imaginations. <hi>Of all the ſonnes that the kingdome hath brought forth, there is none to guide her, to take her by the hand</hi> to lead her out of this pit.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:116405:32"/>
            <p>The end of <hi>Treating</hi> at beſt, is but to ſettle the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in its former worldly eſtate: <hi>Tis looking back to Aegypt:</hi> we are in the <hi>wilderneſſe, and must on to Canaan.</hi> It were <hi>woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> if wee ſhould loſe the fruit of all our blood and miſery that we have ſuffered; and <hi>only be where we were,</hi> which will quickly fall back into the condition we are now in: No, the Divine purpoſe is of ſome higher favour to us; and ſhort of it we muſt not ſit down.</p>
            <p>Beſides, This <hi>Treaty is not voluntary but forced:</hi> not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and plaine, but falſe; each ſeeking to catch advantages, and in darkneſſe and jealouſie, fearfull and unblieving, which will blaſt them: ſin and iniquity unpardoned, the wrath of God ſtill flaming againſt the <hi>Nation,</hi> unquenchable by all the art of man; that will render all humane attempts vaine and fruitleſſe.</p>
            <p>Heer lies <hi>England as Sodom,</hi> burning in the diſpleaſure of God; <hi>in Civil bloody warres, in madneſſe and folly:</hi> The Majeſty and honour of the Mation confounded and loſt in the KING; the liberty and juſtice of it in the <hi>Parliament;</hi> the power and might of it in the Armies; the religion and truth of it in the Church; the wealth and trade in the City; the fruits of the earth by warre and unſeaſonable weather: and ALL in the loſſe of Gods favour.</p>
            <p>Heer is the <hi>Kings curſes</hi> of his people, and imprecations of judgements upon themſelves and families brought forth <hi>to the life.</hi> That mad party that cry <hi>Dam me and Ram me;</hi> that drink healths to the <hi>confuſion of the</hi> Parliament; <hi>tis done,</hi> you live to ſee it.</p>
            <p>The other ſide that have Covenanted <hi>the exterpation of Epiſcopacy</hi> root and branch; tis finiſhed fully: The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the KING <hi>their root; or</hi> the Laws of the Land out of which they grew: the Nation her ſelf, the Church, all
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:116405:33"/>rooted out: And all ſects and ſchiſmes <hi>(Presbytery it ſelf for one)</hi> pul'd up by the rootes. Your fears have brought forth, <hi>the thing you feard is upon you; The removing of the Candleſtick;</hi> the loſſe of the <hi>Goſpell:</hi> The whole <hi>Kingdome</hi> is left in Hideous darkneſſe; And the glory of it is gon from you.</p>
            <p>That <hi>perſecution</hi> feared by <hi>Independents</hi> is come; <hi>Satan, the deſtroyer</hi> is upon you, waſting, killing, impriſoning all true glory, light, righteouſneſſe, peace; And the anſwer of your many prayers <hi>for destruction upon the enemies of Chriſt;</hi> your ſelves and the whole Nation, in all parts of it, <hi>are found fighters against</hi> Chriſt; and for it are deſtroyed: You have all been <hi>bigge with this miſery;</hi> it hath been <hi>within you,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared it ſelf in your ſeveral formes of curſings; and becauſe you <hi>lov'd it, its come upon you;</hi> as <hi>a girdle about your loynes: it cleaves fast to you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thy Sores are opened from head to foot, and <hi>lanc'd</hi> to let out the filth &amp; corruption; and if you ſuffer it to come forth, you will immediately finde eaſe: <hi>He that confeſſeth his ſinnes and forſaketh, findeth mercy:</hi> If you would you <hi>cannot hide them:</hi> all your reaſons pleading your good intentions; the clearnes of your conſciences can't juſtify you; <hi>Heres one grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then your conſciences;</hi> a ſentence ſo Authoratative as will not be reſiſted.</p>
            <p>Neither can you by <hi>cunning or force</hi> eſcape out of this priſon; not the ſtouteſt of you: not your friends, Armies, multitudes; none can help you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Kings are bound in chaines of Iron, and Nobles in fetters: Such honour have all the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:116405:33"/>
            <head>Chap. XI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Shewing the method of God in curing the Nation, <hi>(viz)</hi> Firſt, to take our ſin upon himſelf.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>TIS written in your hearts, and ſpoken in your mouths, <hi>That none can ſave us but God.</hi> Tis the happineſſe of the extremity of our miſery, that wee are paſt the wiſdome and ſtrength of man; and ſo fall onely and immediatly upon the mercy and goodneſſe of <hi>God. Ceaſe from man:</hi> Behold your LORD: <hi>The LORD is our Judge; The LORD is our Law giver; The LORD is our</hi> KING; <hi>Hee will ſave us.</hi> He that hath opened <hi>hell and death</hi> to let you in, can and will open it to let you out. He hath the Keyes, <hi>and opens, and none ſhuts, and ſhuts, and none opens.</hi> All this ſin and wrath was in us in our beſt eſtate though it appeared not; tis good tis broken forth; tis in order <hi>to perfect health:</hi> our <hi>recovery was deſigned in it;</hi> and the foundation of <hi>a mighty ſalvation</hi> is laid in theſe deep miſeries.</p>
            <p>The <hi>method of our cure</hi> muſt be this,</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>to take away ſin and curſe;</hi> ſo long as they <hi>lye at the doore,</hi> there is no paſſage <hi>for mercy to come in, or man to go out:</hi> Now the only way to do this is, to lay them <hi>upon one that can beare them; The LORD Himſelf:</hi> they have lain upon the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and ſunk it, utterly deſtroyed it: But now wee ſee there is one will beare <hi>Englands ſinnes,</hi> and the <hi>ſin and curſe of the whole world;</hi> and there we muſt charge them: yea,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:116405:34"/>
               <hi>The LORD charges himſelf,</hi> and ſaies, <hi>Is there any evill in the City that I have not done? Why hast thou cauſed us to Erre from thy waies? Thou haſt blinded us that we might not ſee; and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened our hearts that we might not understand.</hi> Tis thou that haſt mingled a perverſe ſpirit amongſt our <hi>Princes;</hi> that haſt <hi>given the Nation the wine of aſtoniſhment to drinke; The cup of thy wrath,</hi> that they may <hi>Erre in judgement;</hi> that they may ſtagger and reel, vomit up their own filth; and fall, and not riſe againe: And in all this thou haſt been juſt.</p>
            <p>There hath been two great evils amongſt us, our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing divided from God, and amongſt our ſelves; <hi>and this the</hi> LORD <hi>hath done;</hi> eſpecially in the great diviſions of <hi>King</hi> and Parliament.</p>
            <p>The <hi>day dawning</hi> after this dark night of ſorrow, we can ſay of <hi>England,</hi> GOD <hi>is in thee and none elſe:</hi> In theſe <hi>clouds</hi> is the <hi>Lord</hi> and nothing but the <hi>Lord;</hi> Here is God <hi>in the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er parts of the earth;</hi> and the earth ſhall <hi>diſcloſe her blood, and no longer cover her ſlain.</hi> Verily, God <hi>is in this place, and we knew it not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou haſt alwaies dwelt in the Majeſty and greatneſſe of the <hi>King:</hi> It is thou that haſt Reigned in him; But <hi>verily thou art a God that hideſt thy ſelf,</hi> under vanity and a lye; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a poore, ſinfull, unſtable, weake creature; in a <hi>crawling worme:</hi> thou art there covered with corruption, falſhood, wilfulneſſe; <hi>made ſin; cloathed with filthy garments:</hi> ſo vailed under a thick covering, <hi>that he himſelf</hi> knew thee not: had he known thee, he would not have denied thee, <hi>and crucified the Lord of glory:</hi> he did it ignorantly; thou didſt not come forth, nor act out thy ſelfe <hi>in thy own brightneſſe and power;</hi> but didſt retyre, withdraw thy ſelf; and lye down in weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and <hi>ſo liv'd in ſinfull fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou wert in him, <hi>dwelling in ſuch thick darkneſſe;</hi> in
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:116405:34"/>ſuch <hi>stormes and tempeſts</hi> of wrath; in ſuch a thick miſt &amp; fog of wicked men; <hi>lying down there</hi> in ſuch a hel of a <hi>Dam me</hi> crue, that his own body did not know thee there. His People Rebelled againſt him and thee, when dreſſed in this defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſhape.</p>
            <p>Thou wert in him, rayſing up his heart into an abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and <hi>greatneſſe:</hi> Tis thou that ſay deſt in him, <hi>I am alone, and there is none beſides me:</hi> Ile doe what <hi>I will, and none ſhall reſiſt it.</hi> Thou wert there moſt <hi>Righteouſly,</hi> and accoding to thy <hi>nature, gathering up all thy glory into thy ſelf, keeping</hi> thy ſelf incommunicable; minding only thy ſelfe and thy owne Majeſty, and rejecting all things elſe; refuſing to ſtoop to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that is <hi>mean, or below thy ſelfe;</hi> diſdaining that any ſhould excell <hi>but thy ſelf:</hi> magnifying thy <hi>ſelfe;</hi> and being confident of <hi>thy own ſufficiency.</hi> This now we ſee darkly ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowing out it ſelf in the <hi>Kings Prerogatives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we ſee it is <hi>Thee, The LORD,</hi> that in his leaving <hi>his</hi> Parliament, leaveſt <hi>thy own Son; thy own ſpouſe;</hi> becauſe ſhe is unclean; becauſe ſhe was filthy and poluted: This is righteous in God to leave a <hi>diſeaſed body,</hi> labouring under the guilt of <hi>the Nations ſin;</hi> to give her up to be tormented, to <hi>be left deſolate for her iniquities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Kings flying from his Councell, to ſtrength; Wee now ſee <hi>Divine</hi> jealouſy, that is impatient of having his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſullied and ſtained by common hands. The indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Lord</hi> of hoſts hurried the King away in violence: and taught him to begirt himſelfe with power to uphold <hi>Royalty:</hi> yea, rather to bury it in the earth then that ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould wear the Crown. It is the <hi>Lord</hi> that ſtiffens and hardens the ſpirit of the King againſt all Propoſitions that may leſſen his Greatneſſe; here God ſaies, <hi>My glory will I not give unto another.</hi> To retain <hi>golden Royalty in the flames;</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:116405:35"/>to be a King ſtill while hated, oppoſed, denied, Is the <hi>Divine Spirit:</hi> When it is moſt oppoſed to contend for it: <hi>This the Lord doth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Kings dark and unknown waies, in his ſecret practiſes, We now ſee Our LORDS obſcuring himſelfe: when fleſhly man would finde him out to prey upon him; when wicked and rebellious man would rob him of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; he miſts himſelf in the privacy of darkneſſe; hee hath a long while concealed himſelf in the midſt of us, and ſo kept himſelf from the world (who have alwaies been in purſuite of him) becauſe he ſees they are not fit to injoy him: <hi>This is the Lords doing in the darkneſſe of man;</hi> the Higheſt Majeſty of God under the ſhamfull vileneſſes of man.</p>
            <p>In the Parliament <hi>Now,</hi> is manifeſt the Son of GOD <hi>made fleſh, and dwelling amongſt us:</hi> Thou art here our Lord incompaſſed about with infirmities; in abundance of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in temptations, feares, diſtreſſes, in ſo poor a body as thou art not known to them; they deny thee, kill thee, and know not what they do: In this forme, <hi>Thou comeſt to thy own, and thy own receive the not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou art in them, ſpeaking in ſuch dark parables, in ſuch confuſed and un-underſtood wayes, with ſuch a rabble of oppreſſing <hi>Publicans, Harlots</hi> and ſinners about thee, that thou art judged a Devil; and to mention thee here is blaſphemy to all men: Tis the cry of King and People, Away with him, away with him; <hi>he is not worthy to live:</hi> thou art here loaded with iniquity; <hi>made ſin</hi> indeed.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Parliaments</hi> aſſuming the power of the King, his <hi>Prerogative,</hi> his <hi>revenue,</hi> we hear the Lord ſay, <hi>All that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath, hath he given unto me; All power in Heaven and in Earth.</hi> The King is with us; we have his power &amp;c. Chriſt ſaies in this dark poor forme, <hi>The Father and I am one;</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is me; the words that I ſpeak are his; and the works
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:116405:35"/>that I do, He gives me to do them. I come from the Father; Thus the Son goes forth; for a while appeares amongſt men, and the Father conceals himſelfe, and is not ſeen but in the Son; and the Son challenging the honour, name and power of the Father.</p>
            <p>In the Parliaments undertaking the work of reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and failing in it, We now ſee the <hi>Lord in fleſh;</hi> coming amongſt us, and entering into <hi>The Temple, and over turning the mony changers;</hi> turning out thoſe <hi>buiers and ſellers;</hi> thoſe worldly Epiſcopall party, that turn'd religion into a trade, and worſhip into meer gaine and preferment; propheſying anew forme, a <hi>Kingdome;</hi> but at laſt, loſt in it; ſaying, I <hi>have laboured in vaine, I have ſpent my strength for nought;</hi> and ſuffering under this accuſation, that <hi>he would deſtroy the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plets</hi> &amp;c. yea, the <hi>Kingdome</hi> too; <hi>And ſo the Romans come in and take away both our Place and Nation.</hi> That he was a rebel to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> ſo crucified in ſhame; betrayed; ſold; and his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples leaving of him, doubting his word, ſaying, <hi>We thought he would at this time have Redeemed Iſrael.</hi> Our Lord is here in weakneſſe, failing in his attempts; <hi>marred in his vizage more then any man;</hi> ſo that all turne away their faces from him.</p>
            <p>In the oppreſſing and confuſed <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> We now ſee our LORD <hi>come not to ſend peace, but a ſword; to ſet Father againſt Son, and Son againſt Father,</hi> &amp;c. Setting <hi>two againſt three, and three againſt two;</hi> requiring us <hi>to leave Father and Mother, Houſes and Lands for his Name:</hi> threatning to undoe us, and to ſtrip us of all; bringing of us to nothing; waſting and ſpoiling the riches of the Nation: ſo diſolving of us, <hi>that we muſt be borne again,</hi> new-moulded in <hi>a baptiſme of bloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Parliaments endeavour to preſerve the Kingdome,</hi> to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:116405:36"/>uphold and maintain the freedome of it: <hi>wee ſee the love of Chriſt to the World and his deſire of ſaving it;</hi> we hear him ſay, <hi>Oh England, England, how often would I have gathered thee</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>zeal</hi> and <hi>rage</hi> of both parties againſt each other, we ſee <hi>darkly,</hi> come forth the <hi>wrath of God againſt his enemies:</hi> God <hi>fighting</hi> with thoſe that <hi>fight against him:</hi> the <hi>fierceneſſe</hi> of the <hi>vengeance</hi> of <hi>Heaven againſt his adverſaries: curſing them raining ſnares,</hi> and <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>brimstone</hi> upon them.</p>
            <p>Thus doth the <hi>holy God</hi> dwell with and under the <hi>roofe</hi> of <hi>ſinfull man. Thou that knoweſt no ſin, art made ſin:</hi> Thou li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt in thoſe fleſhly formes: <hi>Thou ſendest forth ſpirit and they are created,</hi> And then doth <hi>blow</hi> upon them and they <hi>dye</hi> and <hi>wither,</hi> loſe their <hi>goodneſſe</hi> and <hi>beauty,</hi> and are toſſed about as <hi>vanity, as chaffe in the wind.</hi> That thou mighteſt deſtroy them, thou commeſt into the <hi>likeneſſe of ſinfull fleſh, that thou migtest conſume ſin in the fleſh;</hi> appeareſt in fleſh, and ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it and under it, <hi>that thou mayeſt at last ſave it:</hi> And un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foldeſt the brightneſs of thy face and <hi>glory,</hi> to be in perfect and undefiled purity, in and under the vileneſſe and baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the creatures.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. XIIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Of the ſecond thing in ſaving of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: The Death of Chriſt, and our fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip in it.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>AS God <hi>bears</hi> our <hi>ſinnes,</hi> ſo he <hi>ſuffers</hi> under them, and we ſuffer in and with him, and thereby is iniquity taken away: <hi>Tis by</hi> blood that we have remiſſion of <hi>ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God dwelt in the <hi>Kingdom:</hi> The power of the King it was Gods; God was in that <hi>majeſty</hi> and <hi>dominion;</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:116405:36"/>God was in the <hi>right</hi> and <hi>freedome</hi> of the <hi>Parliament:</hi> in the peace and happineſſe of the Nation: in the <hi>wealth and honour</hi> of the <hi>City:</hi> in the <hi>power</hi> and <hi>strength</hi> of the <hi>Army:</hi> in the <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> and <hi>order</hi> of the <hi>Church:</hi> And God ſuffers in the <hi>death of all theſe: he ſuffers with us:</hi> loſes in our loſſes; not our blood alone but his is ſhed: not our <hi>goods</hi> onely waſted, but the <hi>Lords:</hi> his they are and were, and God is in union with them, and ſuffers in them: <hi>The Lord is made a curſe for us;</hi> our ſin hath brought this curſe upon God: <hi>This is a ſacrifice well pleaſing unto God:</hi> ſufficient for ever to take away iniquity, and to appeaſe divine juſtice: Though deſtruction ſhould for ever waſt <hi>England,</hi> it would never be <hi>ſatisfyed;</hi> but <hi>feeding upon the glory of God,</hi> eating ſo deep into <hi>Englands ſides</hi> as to reach the heart of God; tis time for it to ſay, <hi>I have enough:</hi> let <hi>anger</hi> ceaſe, it doth feed upon God himſelf.</p>
            <p>Ceaſe to trample upon the head of <hi>King Charles,</hi> God is there; thou tramples upon God in him.</p>
            <p>Ceaſe to confound our <hi>Parliament;</hi> Chriſt is there.</p>
            <p>Ceaſe to deſtroy the <hi>Nation;</hi> tis a holy and heavenly Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Now we are reconciled to God: we were divided by death; now one in death; or God ſo loves us and is ſo neer to us, as to ſuffer with us and for us: our friend indeed that hath layd down his life for us: The glorious love of our God is triumphing with us in and over death: God is in our <hi>miſery inſulting over it, O death Ile be thy plague,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo makes <hi>death</hi> ſweet to us; thou art now a lovely bed wherein our Lord and we, being uncloathed of life, lie down together; death rends the <hi>vail</hi> and takes us into a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked enjoyment of GOD: becauſe wee could not live together, our earthly in Gods heavenly <hi>Kingdome;</hi> therefore muſt we die together; we die becauſe we have left God, and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:116405:37"/>he comes and dyes with us; will not live without us; but comes into the grave to us, ſo that he might deliver us thence: Thou deſtroying Angell proceed no farther: The blood of God cries peace, and you <hi>Engliſh</hi> (mad to deſtroy) ceaſe crucifying the Lord of glory; every wound you make <hi>Pierces the heart of God;</hi> every ſad and grieved ſpirit <hi>afflicts</hi> God; every ſtone of ſcorne or contempt caſt upon KING or Parliament, upon one ſide or other, is flung at Chriſt: and <hi>he that opproſſeth poor England</hi> in her miſeries, or addes one dram of ſorrowes more, <hi>reproacheth his maker.</hi> Yea, If thou doeſt mock poor King <hi>Charles,</hi> poor Parliament, poor Cavaliers, or poor Round-heads; <hi>thou reproachest God in all theſe:</hi> if thou doeſt goe one foot farther, It is to <hi>make long fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows upon the back of</hi> Chriſt. If men or devils ſhould bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durate, our <hi>God is now tender, will not ſtill go on</hi> to ſmite his own <hi>fleſh and blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As God died, ſo are we dead with him; <hi>England</hi> is dead; and all her glory, greatneſſe and juſtice is ſlain. We depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from God, <hi>who is our life,</hi> cannot live; and 'tis well wee can't live in Gods abſence: If we could have ſaved this life, we had loſt it; <hi>and loſing it we ſave it:</hi> For if we had kept it, we had kept it againſt God; and now it's dead, it dyes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God; <hi>It returnes to him from whence it came; dying</hi> with Chriſt; being offered up by <hi>this Prieſt-hood;</hi> it goes with Chriſt; dead with him: and he ſaies, <hi>I go to my Father:</hi> ſo that we are fallen <hi>indeed</hi> into God; and there is nothing <hi>now</hi> but God.</p>
            <p>This is our peace; by this <hi>the wall of partition</hi> 'twixt <hi>God</hi> and us <hi>is broken down, and of twain made one new man: deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the enmity,</hi> that honour, power, dominion, that ſtood at enmity againſt God, is aboliſht, ſlaine in the ſlaying the earthly creature. That which could not endure GOD,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:116405:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>is brought downe; and wee are hereby brought into God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By death, is deſtroyed him that had the power of death, the Devill;</hi> his power and intereſt in the <hi>Nation</hi> is utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed; his kingdome of darkneſſe and wrath is broken downe: he is caſt out, and ſhall no longer deſtroy the Earth, nor deceive the Nation into theſe mad fightings one againſt another; it is now taken from him that ruled with cruelty, envy, wrath, folly, and given to Chriſt, who will Reign in Peace and Righteouſneſſe, in Mercy and Goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>And as there is a Union wrought by this death betwixt God and the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> ſo betwixt KING and <hi>Parliament;</hi> betwen all parties: and <hi>of two,</hi> or <hi>many, we</hi> by death <hi>are made one man;</hi> as truly united as head and body, as a man to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: And all Ordinances, Covenants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are aboliſht: <hi>Prerogative, Kinglineſſe</hi> is ſlain, lyes in the duſt: no KING; <hi>a Priſoner, a Captive:</hi> no <hi>Parliament;</hi> a Rout, a Scuffle, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed heap. What can you demand of the <hi>King?</hi> He hath nothing to give: you mock your ſelves and him. Why are you jealous of him? He can't do <hi>good or hurt.</hi> Why do you labour to ſave your ſelves from his power, or revenge; fear a dead power? Do you think he ſhal returne from the <hi>grave</hi> to vex you? Alas, it is not he, but Devils that trouble you: you need not fortify your Parliament with a <hi>Militia,</hi> with Acts againſt a dead power: Or, Why ſhould the <hi>King</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for a <hi>dead Crowne?</hi> or the People raiſe Authority from the duſt? How fooliſh and vaine are the attempts of his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Being dead on both ſides in the grave; <hi>Heer the wicked ceaſe from troubling; The weary Be at rest: The priſoners rest together; they hear not the voyce of the oppreſſor: The ſmall and great are heer; the ſervant is free from his Maſter.</hi> How is it, that you vex one another? It's a hel ſure; and you are Devils one
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:116405:38"/>to another: Is not the <hi>grave enough to ſwallow up enmity?</hi> Why ſhould the Parliament inſiſt upon Covenants, Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Ingagements? Or the <hi>King</hi> upon his Honour, Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Friends? <hi>The Law hath power over a man ſo long as he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved;</hi> no longer: There is no bands now upon you; neither party can require any thing of you: You have ſtood it out for your principles, for your parties; <hi>Cavaliers for</hi> KING; <hi>Rounds-heads</hi> for <hi>Parliament;</hi> till you and they are all loſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <p>All your <hi>engagements</hi> for and againſt each other, are taken away; Law is ſlain; <hi>right, property, righteouſneſſe and truth</hi> hath forſaken the Earth; it is in neither ſide: you may lye ſtil and be at peace; for all is dead for which you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend: There doth nothing live but ſhame, ſorrow, folly and madneſſe; and that is dead too, in your death.</p>
            <p>The <hi>King is dead,</hi> his Majeſty is ſlain, crucified; and <hi>lies in the bowels of the earth;</hi> that is, in his Parliament and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: he is deſcended into us, dyed into the <hi>Kingdome:</hi> And hence it is that Parliament men, Committee men, Army, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Citizens are all become <hi>petty Kings:</hi> Kinglineſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſow'd in the earth: And ſo though we have loſt our <hi>King</hi> yet we have him in us.</p>
            <p>The <hi>King</hi> is dead, and our life of Majeſty, our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome died with him; we ceaſe to be a <hi>Kingdome,</hi> when our head ceaſed to <hi>rule;</hi> and are become <hi>a herd of wilde Beaſts.</hi> He took us all into himſelf, and ſo made a rich Sacrifice of al the glory of the Kingdome in one.</p>
            <p>He dyes for us, they are our iniquities that denies us the bleſſing of <hi>government;</hi> we have the benefit of his <hi>ſuffering;</hi> it is for us: By this he comes down into the meaneſt ſubject, into the worſt condition of a ſubject; bonds: hee empties
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:116405:38"/>himſelf into us, and fills us with Royalty; and gives the loweſt to have fellowſhip with the higheſt: by his deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Throne into the Priſon, and his aſcending from the Priſon to the Throne; there is an open way and paſſage from miſery to greatneſſe : by this the pooreſt creature in <hi>England</hi> ſhal have acceſſe to the Throne for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and juſtice: And the KING ſhal acknowledge, this is my fellow ſubject, my fellow priſoner. I am, and was as low, as meane as he: This ſhall fill puniſhments with grace, and make paines and judgements acceptable from a Prince that is a Brother, a fellow-ſufferer: This is that which onely can fit a KING for Reigning, to goe by the Croſſe, to ſuffer firſt; by which trialls and temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he is for ever able to pitty ſuch as are tempted and doe ſuffer.</p>
            <p>The Parliament is dead alſo; cannot, will not, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live the KING; puts off her glory with the Kings; and ſits downe in the duſt: dyes into the <hi>King,</hi> as the <hi>King</hi> into the <hi>Parliament;</hi> goes down into his grave, follows him; and there lyes wrapt up in him the life, union and Majeſty of the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament:</hi> and as the King ariſes out of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> ſo the <hi>Parliament out of, and with the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Parliament dyes for the People; ſo conſtantly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heres to the Peoples <hi>rights, that She periſheth in the obtaining of them;</hi> and becauſe She cannot by life, She doth and wil by death free us. The Cauſe that She undertook though ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be loſt yet by her ſhamfull ſuffering is confirmed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and <hi>a Teſtimony of blood given</hi> to a work of Reformation, which is more effectual then <hi>twenty Bills:</hi> And ſo our Parliament doth us moſt right, not being able to help us, to lye downe and bear our curſe her ſelf.</p>
            <p>She dyes into the <hi>Army,</hi> gives up her Ghoſt into the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:116405:39"/>boſome; and leaves the Army Executor of her wil: dies into the People, and al dying together and tumbled into <hi>one grave</hi> of confuſion.</p>
            <p>By this death there is a perfect <hi>Remiſſion of ſinne;</hi> here is a <hi>true Act of oblivion</hi> on all ſides; a <hi>blotting out of tranſgreſſions:</hi> Hath the <hi>King</hi> tranſgreſt, hee lyes in the duſt for it; he is in your own bowels, devoured by you: if you accuſe him, you accuſe your ſelves: look upon him now as pierced by you, and you can't think of his ſins, but of your own ſhame with ſelf-piercing, ſelf-wounding hearts. Neither can the <hi>King</hi> remember the <hi>Parliaments</hi> injuries, but he muſt in thoſe thoughts be oppreſſed; they are in him, and if he ſhould <hi>think</hi> of revenge, he muſt be revenged upon himſelf; death whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly overcomes and ſpoiles revenge; and leaves it nothing at all to feed upon: Or if any party do look back, they ſee all theſe <hi>mutuall violences</hi> in the <hi>Divine wiſdome and goodneſſe, the ſting</hi> of them being <hi>taken away,</hi> with pleaſure and content; and glory in theſe marks, not of hatred, but love; <hi>glory in the Croſſe,</hi> and rejoyce in your mutuall ſufferings together, and one for another; all bitterneſs and envy <hi>being ſlain thereby:</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one (as now in the <hi>accuſer</hi>) you ſee your own <hi>good,</hi> and your adversaries <hi>weakneſſe</hi> and <hi>ſin,</hi> ſo ſhall you by this <hi>change of death,</hi> ſee all the evill as your own, and be able to beare it; every one <hi>accuſing himſelf,</hi> and <hi>acquitting others:</hi> ſo that the greateſt enmity will be <hi>against your ſelves,</hi> or any thing that makes a diviſion; and nothing remaining to be hated but enmity or hatred it ſelfe. There cannot a <hi>thought</hi> of ſtrife or enmity ariſe now, but it muſt appear in blood; in the blood of <hi>Kings, Queenes, Princes, Parliaments:</hi> enmity being ſlaine, at firſt look you do ſee death in it, and ſo abhorre <hi>to change a word with it;</hi> look upon it as a murtherer, and immediatly fly from it into each others boſomes.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:116405:39"/>
            <p>Here is away too to pay all debts, to cancell all obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on both ſides; in this pit of death muſt all be ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up. Debts are <hi>forgiven a dead man:</hi> Here is a death of <hi>the Old man,</hi> The old Quarel, the old termes of enmity; <hi>the old man and his luſts:</hi> The <hi>lustings</hi> of the KINGS party after ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, greatneſſe, preferment: the Parliament after places, <hi>Biſhops Lands,</hi> &amp;c. the <hi>Armies luſtings</hi> after arreares: the luſts of envy, malice, tyranny, oppreſſion, coveteouſnes, deſiring each others goods (the fuell of this flame in all) is buried.</p>
            <p>Thus, as before our remedies were our diſeaſes, ſo now our diſeaſes, our miſeries become our remedy: in ſaving we loſt, now in loſing we ſave: Our gain was loſſe, and our loſſe is become gain through the riches of the <hi>wiſdome</hi> and <hi>mercy</hi> of the <hi>Lord our GOD:</hi> Now we muſt ſay, we had periſht, if we had not periſht.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. XV.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Of the compleat cure of the Nation, ſhewing it in its Raiſed ſtate; and parrticularly the King.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>NOw, through the tender mercy of our God, doth the day ſparing from on high, viſit us; To give light to them that ſit in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> &amp; <hi>in the ſhadow of death; to guid our feet in the way of peace:</hi> The bright day of <hi>Englands Redemption</hi> is come; the <hi>ſweet morning</hi> of our <hi>Reſurrection.</hi> A riſe, let us go from this <hi>pit of miſery:</hi> Let us <hi>wrap up all our grave cloaths</hi> of ſhame, ſin and ſorrow; and leave them with their <hi>Father, the deſtroyer,</hi> in this <hi>dark night of hell and death.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:116405:40"/>
            <p>The Lord ſaith it, and in the power of the Lord, we doe <hi>break open Iron gates of death,</hi> and let goe theſe poor <hi>priſoners of hope:</hi> and before we goe we will ſpoile the <hi>ſpoyler,</hi> trample <hi>Satan</hi> under foot: laugh and mock at thy power: <hi>ruine</hi> thy Kingdom of <hi>darknes;</hi> take away from <hi>thee</hi> thy power to vex, wholly deſtroy thy deſtruction; <hi>Oh thou enemy, deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is come to a perpetuall end:</hi> We ſmite thee upon the cheek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone, <hi>thou canſt bite no more:</hi> Now we lead <hi>captivity captive;</hi> we were under thee; now thou thy ſelfe art a <hi>priſoner</hi> and a <hi>ſervant:</hi> thou haſt not hurt us, but done us <hi>good</hi> in deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us; thy <hi>curſes</hi> are turned to <hi>bleſſings;</hi> to our infinite ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage: Thou thy ſelf ſhall be under the burden of <hi>divine wrath; We are eſcaped as a bird out of the ſnare of the fowler:</hi> your <hi>ſnare</hi> is broken, <hi>and we are delivered:</hi> and thou <hi>falleſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the pit thou diggeſt for others:</hi> by thy <hi>wounding</hi> us wee are <hi>healed:</hi> thou haſt <hi>bruiſed our heel; but we have broak thy head:</hi> thy whole deſign of <hi>Englands ruine;</hi> and thy plots are diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and turned againſt thy ſelfe: upon <hi>thee</hi> and thy wrath as a <hi>foot-stoole</hi> doe we aſcend into the bleſſed <hi>throne</hi> of God. We <hi>lock</hi> thee up in chaines of darkneſſe, and throw thee under the earth: get thee hence and all thy <hi>darkneſſe</hi> with thee, that keeps Engliſhmen from ſeeing God in one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother: take with thee all thy <hi>bitterneſſe, rage, madneſſe, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, tyranny,</hi> all thy <hi>lies</hi> and <hi>falſhood,</hi> thy falſe <hi>Oaths,</hi> and breach of <hi>Covenant;</hi> all thy <hi>diſorder</hi> and <hi>confuſion;</hi> thy <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous plots,</hi> and all thy <hi>ſcorne</hi> and <hi>reproach;</hi> and all thy <hi>falſe accuſing Father</hi> to <hi>Son,</hi> and <hi>Son</hi> to <hi>Father,</hi> &amp;c. Thy <hi>rayling</hi> and <hi>revilings, blaſphemies,</hi> with every thing that is <hi>curſed;</hi> and goe headlong into the deep <hi>Sea</hi> of thy <hi>perdition:</hi> we wil live in heavenly peace, love and righteouſneſſe, in the <hi>light</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> of our own God. Shake thy ſelf from thy duſt cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>daughter,</hi> this <hi>cloud</hi> of <hi>duſt</hi> that darkens thee, from <hi>divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:116405:40"/>emptineſſe, barrenneſſe, vanity, instability,</hi> and aſcend into the <hi>light, majesty, union</hi> and <hi>strength</hi> of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>England</hi> is become the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of the Lord <hi>and of his Chriſt;</hi> God <hi>reigns</hi> in her; ſhe is become a holy <hi>Nation,</hi> a <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Kingdome: God is in her and none elſe: The tabernacle of God is with men: he now takes his great reign upon earth: he is come, he is come to judge the People righteouſly, and to govern the Nation upon Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The majeſty of the <hi>Trinity</hi> dwelling before in weaknes, that is ſowed, dyed, its raiſed in power; before in fleſh, now in Spirit; before covered and vailed, hiding himſelfe, now in open and naked face: We are now a new <hi>creature,</hi> a new <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>righteouſneſſe;</hi> living in the immediate <hi>brightneſſe</hi> of the face of God.</p>
            <p>God is with us, with all his hoſt of power and <hi>goodneſſe, mercy</hi> and <hi>wiſdome,</hi> to eſtabliſh us in peace and juſtice: there is nothing amongſt us but God, who is exalted alone: and ſaith, <hi>I am and there is none beſides me;</hi> and hath taken the Kingdome into himſelf; and every thing is what it is in the <hi>glory</hi> of God: now indeed the <hi>ſoyl</hi> is the Lambs, he is Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Earth: The people, the Lords, and ſhall be filled with the excellency of God in himſelf.</p>
            <p>The Lord is King; God himſelf reigns: God is upon his throne, and ſaith openly to the whole Kingdome, <hi>I am your</hi> King; you are my People; Ile rule you with a pure golden Scepter of righteouſneſſe and peace: you ſhall ſubmit to me, and receive law, honour, juſtice and protection from my ſelfe; you ſhall now ſee the beauty, ſweetneſſe and goodneſs of my government, Ile be a King to and in every one of you.</p>
            <p>And Ile reign over you in and by King <hi>Charles;</hi> I will take him out of the priſon of <hi>Satans</hi> darkneſſe out of the pit of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:116405:41"/>the world; from all his vileneſſe of luſts, of oppreſſion, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, folly, fiercneſſe, wrath; and from all his ſhame and diſhonour: from his <hi>evill counſellers,</hi> wicked ſpirits that have ſeduced him to evil; into my <hi>boſome:</hi> and turne <hi>his heart as a river of water:</hi> It ſhal no longer be mudded with <hi>evill counſellers;</hi> nor with <hi>pride, coveteouſneſſe, cruelty;</hi> but run in a pure ſtream of <hi>Divine juſtice</hi> and <hi>goodneſſe;</hi> and ſo largely and plentifully, that it ſhall flow forth freely upon <hi>you: Righteouſneſſe ſhall run down your ſtreets.</hi> A fountain <hi>of honour</hi> as wel as juſtice, that ſhal give reall, true <hi>(not titular) honour</hi> to his People; that ſhal ſtream forth <hi>Majeſty and greatneſſe</hi> as freely into the whole <hi>Nation,</hi> as <hi>the Sun doth beames:</hi> he ſhall freely communicate <hi>Royalty</hi> that it ſhal be every ones; and every one ſhal live in the <hi>view</hi> and <hi>enjoyment</hi> of it, and fully <hi>ſatisfied</hi> with it; it being truly <hi>his own:</hi> A <hi>King</hi> enlarged with the <hi>largeneſſe of</hi> God that comprehends all his People <hi>as the ſands on the Sea ſhore;</hi> and is an <hi>Ocean of goodneſſe and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe</hi> to cover <hi>thoſe ſands:</hi> whoſe <hi>Armes of love</hi> can at <hi>Once</hi> imbrace the whole <hi>Kingdome;</hi> every party and perſon: that carries every <hi>Engliſh man</hi> in his <hi>boſome:</hi> That impartially wil communicate <hi>favour</hi> to every one according to his true worth and ability to receive it: of large wiſdome, fil'd with the wiſdome of God: of quick and piercing underſtanding, to execute judgement in all cauſes: one living in the <hi>light</hi> of GOD; ſhin'd upon with the <hi>Majesty</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> that he ſhal not be deceiv'd by flatterers; but ſhal ſcatter all ſuch miſts from before the <hi>Throne;</hi> that of <hi>all places,</hi> wicked men, and wicked things ſhal fly from the <hi>Court</hi> and preſence of the <hi>King:</hi> Of ſuch tendernes, that he ſhall really bear the burthens of all his ſubjects; and every mans trouble ſhal make him reſtleſſe, that cannot be fully content til he hath fully ſatisfied all the wants of his People: That is all mildneſſe and gentleneſſe to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:116405:41"/>his own People <hi>as a Father;</hi> and terrible only to <hi>your</hi> adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries: whoſe indignation is bent continually againſt the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of his People and his childrens peace: a <hi>Lion</hi> to them, but <hi>a Lambe, a Shepherd</hi> to you: A <hi>Prince</hi> Mighty with the <hi>Mightineſſe of God,</hi> able to do you <hi>good; mighty in word and deed;</hi> able to ſave you, and to deſtroy them that hate you: A King that hath no <hi>joy or delight</hi> but the <hi>good</hi> and <hi>proſperity</hi> of his People: Tis your happyneſſe only that is <hi>his Crowne:</hi> that knows no glory but a <hi>loyall and loving</hi> People; that is <hi>King</hi> only to make you happy; and your happineſſe is his Kingdome: or, health and proſperity in the People, grows up into <hi>a lively flower of glory;</hi> a King; or breaths out it ſelfe in his Majeſty: So the KING is the breath of our noſtrils.</p>
            <p>That is indeed a King <hi>Anointed by God;</hi> by and in the <hi>grace of God;</hi> that is covered over with Divine grace; that is nothing but what God is; and hath all the Kinglines of God ſhining in him: With whom, and in whom you ſhal naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee the face of Divine juſtice; and in whom the glory of <hi>God doth take pleaſure</hi> to ſhew it ſelf; and not as another <hi>from him,</hi> but in perfect <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion; in truth and righteouſneſſe:</hi> where there is nothing to ſeperate nor part the earthly, from the heavenly King; but the earthly is in <hi>agreement,</hi> in <hi>covenant</hi> with the heavenly; living together in the ſame Spirit: The heavenly God being <hi>intire himſelf,</hi> and the King <hi>intire him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> yet both but one in true marriage and conjunction for ever; a <hi>bond</hi> and <hi>covenant</hi> that never ſhall be broken: the <hi>King in God, God in the King:</hi> The <hi>King</hi> is what <hi>God</hi> is; and <hi>God</hi> is what the <hi>King</hi> is; neither alone: God all in him, he all in God. He that oppoſeth one, oppoſth both; hee that loveth one, loveth both; exclude one, you exclude both; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one, you deny both; diſobey one, you diſobey both: This
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:116405:42"/>is heaven and earth <hi>married</hi> together in harmony and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and the King that once appeared an <hi>Image</hi> of God, a <hi>ſhadow</hi> in which he was weak, and which he hath dyed to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the evill and corrupt part left in the <hi>grave;</hi> hee is raiſed up in the very ſubſtance; <hi>in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, in Spirit, in Truth; in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall fellowſhip with GOD.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. XVI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Of the Parliament in its Raiſed eſtate.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>ALL things are made new; a new King, and a new Parliament; a new Head, and a new Body: a Heavenly body; a <hi>Hoſt of Divine excellencies;</hi> in which all the perfections of the Son of GOD ſhines. An <hi>aſſembly,</hi> or <hi>body</hi> of Chriſt; <hi>The fullnes of him who fills all in all:</hi> not only a company of weak men, But this is thy <hi>new name, The</hi> LORD <hi>is there;</hi> GOD <hi>is with us:</hi> Chriſt in glory, in Majeſty; <hi>Highly exalted.</hi> Thou in whom are hid <hi>The treaſures of wiſdome;</hi> thou ſitteſt in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell to draw forth excellent Laws for us, and to rule in the midſt of us; <hi>One choſen out of the People,</hi> in which meet in one, <hi>the life, ſpirit, and wiſdome of heaven.</hi> The LORD is here, challenging the <hi>Kingdome</hi> to be his; here is gathered the <hi>heads of the Tribes; a congregation of the firſt borne;</hi> the chief and choiſeſt <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels</hi> collected and imbodied into one Son of God.</p>
            <p>The <hi>LORDS</hi> Chriſt, he ſaith, <hi>I am here, your fleſh and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:116405:42"/>blood; one of you: I'le provide and conſtitute wholſome Laws for you in this</hi> Parliament.</p>
            <p>And this <hi>Parliament</hi> taken out of all its filth and guilt; out of all its madneſſe and diſfraction, folly and confuſion; out of the hands of the <hi>envious man</hi> that divides &amp; deſtroies; from under curſed darkneſſe, violence and oppreſſion; from the Peoples woe and curſe. I'le waſh it, and cleanſe it, and fill it <hi>with Majeſty and goodneſſe;</hi> make it a <hi>mountain of holineſſe, a City of Righteouſneſſe. Ariſe ſhine, for thy light is come, and the glory of the Lord is riſen upon thee.</hi> Thou ſhalt no longer ſit in darkneſſe: Thy Sun ſhall go down no more: thou ſhalt not ſtumble nor fall for want of light; thou <hi>ſhalt not daſh thy foot againſt a stone: The Lord ſhall be unto thee an everlaſting light, and thy God thy glory. The Sun of righteouſneſſe is Riſen</hi> in thee, <hi>with healing under his wings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou now art Divine juſtice; <hi>A habitation of juſtice:</hi> where juſtice it ſelfe ſhal delight to dwell. <hi>No unclean thing ſhall be found in thee:</hi> living alwaies in the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, thou ſhalt be ſeperated from ſinners; blameleſſe: live in a hight of righteouſneſſe above accuſation: <hi>The Lord Our Righteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Saviour of the People; thy <hi>walls ſhall be called ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and thy gates praiſe;</hi> ſending forth <hi>ſaving health</hi> to the whole <hi>Nation,</hi> into every part that is pained or diſeaſed: a univerſal remedy for all malladies; a ſkilfull <hi>Phyſition,</hi> rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly furniſht with <hi>the fullneſſe of the Spirit of</hi> Chriſt to apply a plaſter to every ſore.</p>
            <p>Thou now art all bowels, a heap of compaſſions rowl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling together; of moſt exquiſit ſenſe of any burthen that lies upon us: The Mother of <hi>England,</hi> as the KING is the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in whoſe <hi>womb</hi> our <hi>freedomes, rights, peace</hi> lyes: from whoſe <hi>brests</hi> we ſhal ſuck <hi>milke of comfort, riches, eaſe, quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:116405:43"/>justice happyneſſe;</hi> as tender of every one of your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren as of your ſelves. Thou art beautified with garments of ſalvation, honourable, glorious: the joy of the whole earth: Adorned <hi>now</hi> with ſuch excellency, that thou art a <hi>Queene</hi> indeed; a compleat Second for ſuch a Firſt.</p>
            <p>This thou art, in perfect conjunction with the <hi>Divine nature,</hi> in one Spirit with the <hi>LORD;</hi> taken into the <hi>Nature and Being</hi> of the eternal <hi>Law-giver;</hi> being one with the great Court or Councell of heaven: Really, truly, being in the <hi>LORD;</hi> and the <hi>LORD</hi> really, and truly in you; not in ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, that is deſtroyed, but in ſubſtance: not a <hi>naturall,</hi> but a <hi>ſpirituall body;</hi> not a earthly, but a heavenly, <hi>The Lord from heaven:</hi> Now a holy and incorruptible body, that cannot faile. Chriſt is compleatly himſelf in you; you are compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in him; and compleatly one <hi>Lord,</hi> one <hi>man,</hi> one <hi>body;</hi> one Aſſembly or Congregation: having the ſame Nature and Perſon.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. XVII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Of the perfect <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion betwixt King and Parliament, and by them with his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; in this new and raiſed eſtate.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THESE Two, KING and Parliament, by <hi>fleſh and Satan</hi> were divided from <hi>God,</hi> made un-like God; ſet at diſtance from, and enmity to GOD, and at enmity one from another: So now, that <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>Devill</hi> being deſtroyed, the Spirit unites them truly to God, in truth and ſubſtance;
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:116405:43"/>and as to God ſo one to another: This law oft he Spirit knits them and marries them both waies.</p>
            <p>In this raiſed eſtate King and Parliament are in moſt excellent union, joyned together in neareſt bonds of felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip as <hi>Husband and Wife,</hi> as <hi>Father and Son;</hi> God and Chriſt: In the greateſt diſtance of theſe unnaturall breaches, there hath been ſtill a ſecret tendency towards each other; your union was never ſo much ſlaine but it acted out towards an agreement: And now there is a thirſt in both after your ſelves in each other, and a reſtleſnes of ſpirit attends you till you meet; in that dark way in which you are, in hel, you are groping one after another; in a feeble way of <hi>Treating;</hi> and framing a net of ſpiders web to catch one another in; in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall formes: Theſe are too weak to hold or binde you toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; you are both pittied, that long for each other, and can't enjoy each other; eſpecially the poor <hi>Parliament</hi> whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires are after her <hi>Husband,</hi> luſting for him, and knows not which way to compaſſe him through fear and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
            <p>I ſhall but draw a vail, a curtaine aſide, and ſhew you both imbracing each other.</p>
            <p>The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> betwixt King and <hi>Parliament,</hi> and by the <hi>mediation of Parliament</hi> with the People, whom they Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, <hi>is strong</hi> and <hi>Inviolable;</hi> It is <hi>admirable</hi> and <hi>delightfull:</hi> They are one in Nature and Being; and can never be divid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: As Chriſt ſaies of the Father, ſo the Parliament may ſay; <hi>The Father in me, and in the Father.</hi> Where ever the King is, the Parliament is; and the King can't bee without his parliament and People; and where ever the Parliament is, or People are, the King is: They are one, and together, in the greateſt diſtance: the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> is ſuch, that diſtance is ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up by it, and comprehended in it. The Son comes
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:116405:44"/>forth of <hi>Heaven,</hi> and is in <hi>Heaven;</hi> is in <hi>Heaven</hi> while out of <hi>Heaven;</hi> and when alone, yet not alone; <hi>The Father is with me:</hi> So the King and Parliament are aſunder, yet together; and by their parting their <hi>union</hi> is enlarged, not broken: Their fleſhly outward <hi>union</hi> broken, but by that the inward and true <hi>union</hi> appeares and is brought forth. In <hi>truth,</hi> the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament is in the King; and acts not, moves not, but in the King; hath, not, cannot doe: and the King is in the Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and naturally doth what the Parliament doth. The King retires and carries the life and ſpirit, of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with him; and it is in perfection in him: the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment withdraws and keeps cloſe the King with her: The King takes the ſpirit of the Parliament; the <hi>Parliament</hi> keeps the body of the King; and to narrow, poor ſenſe they are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided: but ſuch is the largeneſſe of the Spirit, that delights to extend <hi>union</hi> into diſtinction; and there they are, and alwaies were, more one in truth then they have yet appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be.</p>
            <p>The former <hi>union</hi> was too weak and ſtrait, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore its ſnapt aſunder; and the <hi>LORD</hi> now ſhews ſuch a <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> as diſjunction doth confirme and multiply; while they are parted they are doubly one; each upholding <hi>union</hi> in their being diſtinct; and ſo manifeſts, that they are ſo one, as they are two likwiſe; and in being two, they are twice one; each carrying the other along with him. The King carries with him the power and ſpirit of the Parliament, it being his; and the Parliament the matter and body of kinglyneſſe, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hers: the King hath the Parliament in night and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency of <hi>forme;</hi> the Parliament hath the King in lowneſſe and groſneſſe of <hi>matter:</hi> yea the Parliament hath the <hi>KING</hi> in his hight and ſpirit; but covered over, and hid under unity and lowneſſe of the matter: ſo the King hath the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:116405:44"/>in the excellency and unity of the <hi>forme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And they ſo are in one another as manifeſts their <hi>union;</hi> both <hi>languiſhing in deſire after</hi> each other, in ſuch an abſolute neceſſity of being together, that the <hi>King</hi> can't act the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of a <hi>King,</hi> will not aſſume the work of a <hi>King,</hi> but with his <hi>Parliament;</hi> and the <hi>Parliament</hi> can't act in the power of a Parliament til they have the <hi>King:</hi> Which ſhews that the <hi>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is ſtill good;</hi> ſo ſtrong that they cannot bee but together in affection, though parted in place; and will not bee happy <hi>til they are fully together:</hi> Their <hi>love lives at distance,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is ſlain <hi>by unions being in distance;</hi> their diſtance open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>foundation of their union,</hi> and <hi>awakning the ſtrength of love</hi> to ſhew it ſelfe in <hi>re-union;</hi> ſo by a <hi>temporary diviſion</hi> comes an <hi>eternall and inſeperable conjunction:</hi> as that parting of Chriſt from his Diſciples, <hi>It is expedient that I goe from you, that the Comforter may come, and he ſhall abide with you for ever.</hi> Thus doth the <hi>Sea</hi> of the <hi>ſpirits</hi> love <hi>drown</hi> al your diviſions; and it abundantly triumphs over your breaches; flowing in upon, and in your breaches, <hi>to the utter deſtruction of that plague of enmity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You are one in originall; in <hi>one Cauſe:</hi> yea, you are <hi>the cauſe of each other:</hi> you are deſcended and derived from the <hi>ſame Father,</hi> from the <hi>ſame Heaven,</hi> and are again taken into the <hi>ſame Heaven; joynt heires</hi> of the ſame glory; fil'd both with <hi>the ſame life; begotten by the ſame Spirit:</hi> The ſame Spirit that gives majeſty and power to one, gives the ſame to the other; <hi>one fountain</hi> fils both your <hi>Cisternes;</hi> two <hi>ſtreames</hi> coming from <hi>the ſame head; two twins</hi> lying in the <hi>ſame wombe of the</hi> Spirit: and it is the <hi>ſame</hi> Spirit that lives in you both: There can be no difference betwen you, you have <hi>indeed</hi> but one <hi>minde,</hi> but one <hi>heart: Englands peace, honour, juſtice and greatneſſe, is the ſubſtance of both your lives:</hi> you haue but one
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:116405:45"/>
               <hi>ſubſiſtence;</hi> but one <hi>happineſſe;</hi> but one <hi>breath and ayre, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands joy, Englands good:</hi> you are not one <hi>now</hi> by outward Oaths and Covenants, but by inward Oaths and Covenants; by <hi>an everlaſting Covenant that cannot bee broken.</hi> The ſame <hi>God</hi> and Spirit ſpeaking both, or ſwearing both <hi>by himſelfe;</hi> bringing forth both perpetually in the ſame Oath, <hi>by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf:</hi> While he ſwears to ſave and deliver his People in <hi>England,</hi> he ſweares a good KING and Parliament: bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth himſelf, he brings forth you; or brings forth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe KING and Parliament. Being brought forth by <hi>Gods</hi> Spirit, there will not come from ſuch a <hi>fountain, bitter and ſweet waters,</hi> no diſſenting affections: and bringing forth in both nothing but himſelfe; but one and the ſame juſtice, one and the ſame goodneſſe, wiſdome, love, to the People; ther's no feare of diſagreeing: and bringing this forth, not in a dark and miſty world, where you have been ſubject to miſtakes; but in the cleare light of the Spirit; in the calmnes, quietnes, opennes, freenes of the Spirit; there can be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>pleaſure and mutuall delight in all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As you are brought forth by one, and in one Spirit, ſo by one another, as Man and Woman; The ſame Spirit producing the KING out of the Parliament, and ſo out of the People; and the Parliament and People out of the KING; <hi>As Man is by Woman, and Woman of Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>People</hi> is of the King, taken out of his <hi>ſide,</hi> and from thence formd and built: The <hi>King</hi> is Father, and we his children; he is <hi>the firſt man</hi> in the Kingdome, is before all: <hi>Adam,</hi> in whoſe loynes we all were, and from him, and of him we are: our true <hi>Civill Father;</hi> from whom we all receive our <hi>Civill beings;</hi> in whom liberty, property, peace, order, honour, authority is firſt originally, and chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:116405:45"/>and ſo from him derived to us: Eſpecially, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is taken out of him <hi>by his Writ, from his heart; is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct</hi> of the deep <hi>thoughts</hi> of his minde; which being gathered together are a <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As he is ours, ſo we his originall: <hi>Man is by the Woman:</hi> The <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>People</hi> in their fullneſſe of time, when grown up into <hi>maturity, bring forth a Government, a</hi> KING; <hi>The firſt-borne;</hi> their <hi>vigor and strength:</hi> and ſo property, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, order, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are firſt in us; and then they ariſe out of us into him: And by this continuall motion of the blood, life, and ſpirits of the body, in a <hi>circular courſe,</hi> the whole ſhall be preſerved in a lively and lovely ſtate. All the ſtrength and power of the <hi>Nation</hi> continually aſcending and deſcending; paſſing from us upward to the <hi>King,</hi> and thence removes down again to us; and ſo takes <hi>the nature of all:</hi> perfectly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhes the loweſt, and taking his <hi>meanneſſe</hi> and carries it to the higheſt, <hi>to the head:</hi> being there <hi>in-nobled and raiſed,</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries its Majeſty down into inferiour parts againe: and is the ſame <hi>River</hi> called by ſeverall <hi>names,</hi> in ſeverall <hi>places:</hi> as the Sea is one, only diſtinct by the ſhore it waſhes upon.</p>
            <p>This <hi>union,</hi> by the wiſdome and fulneſs of the ſpirit, is brought forth, not in <hi>a rude heap,</hi> but in <hi>judgement and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion;</hi> in a ſweet variety; and in <hi>ſuch harmony</hi> as they are the joy and delight of each other: <hi>as Husband and Wife; one fleſh,</hi> yet two <hi>perſons;</hi> ſo ordered and compoſed with a <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant variety,</hi> that <hi>the ſame</hi> (which were it only the ſame, and not another, would be dull and fruitleſſe) <hi>being thus varied,</hi> gives delightfull <hi>fellowſhip and profit.</hi> Such is the <hi>fullneſse</hi> of this <hi>heavenly glory,</hi> that it is <hi>One,</hi> and not <hi>leſſe</hi> but <hi>more,</hi> in making <hi>another:</hi> The King hath all power and authority, and the Parliament hath the ſame without robbing the King: the Parliament having in another way: <hi>(viz) a</hi> ſecond, <hi>ſhall
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:116405:46"/>never claſh againſt the firſt:</hi> but being <hi>one,</hi> the King hath it in the Parliament in another way then he hath it in himſelfe: and ſo his power is <hi>enriched and strengthened</hi> by it. and tis no loſſe to the Parliament to give it <hi>to the KING, her Husband:</hi> whilſt ſhe gives it him, <hi>he being hers,</hi> ſhee hath it in him, in a more <hi>excellent way</hi> then ſhe can have it in her ſelf. And for either of theſe to have it alone, <hi>would be unpleaſant, ſolitary, and burthenſome:</hi> Its delightfull to ſee it and enjoy it in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; we not ſo perfectly beholding our ſelves, or loving our ſelves, in our ſelves, as in another; ſight, love, and enjoyment requiring another.</p>
            <p>It is the content of greatnes, <hi>not to be,</hi> but to <hi>propagate</hi> greatnes; For the King to rule alone can't be ſo acceptable to him as to conferre Dignity upon his own body, his Seed. It would bee irkſome to have his greatneſſe included in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; &amp; this is the <hi>moſt</hi> proper way of his propagating himſelf, <hi>his Parliament;</hi> and ſo a <hi>Parliament is his own choiſe; his meet help,</hi> by which he is free, and without which he were bound to himſelf, and in himſelfe: and ſo to be a <hi>King,</hi> were but <hi>to be a pack-horſe:</hi> and for <hi>the Woman, the Parliament</hi> to rule by aſſiſtance (being called) <hi>in the boſome and heart of her head,</hi> pleaſes her: should ſhee be alwaies in it, <hi>and neceſſitated to it,</hi> it would be her bondage; ſhe would deſire to <hi>reſigne</hi> it up to her <hi>Lord,</hi> and her ſelfe <hi>chooſe an eaſie and pleaſant ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection.</hi> Thus divided it is encreaſed, and nothing leſſened <hi>but the burthen;</hi> which <hi>while thus equally ballanced,</hi> is no bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, but the ſafety of the whole: For the <hi>King</hi> to be the <hi>root</hi> out of which <hi>the body of the tree</hi> grows, the <hi>Parliament;</hi> and out of her the <hi>People, the branches;</hi> and to ſend forth ſap free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whereby the dody is ſupplied, and ſo <hi>every arme, branch and twigge,</hi> that it brings forth good fruit, wealth, peace, content, honour, power, al kindes of proſperity for the <hi>King;</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:116405:46"/>&amp; then the people to be the root, <hi>the Parliament,</hi> the body: the <hi>King</hi> the head or top; and the people to ſend up by the body riches, honour, greatneſſe, as ſap into the head, whereby he may bring forth fruits of Majeſty, Juſtice, Greatneſſe unto them: and ſo the burthen and the fruit is divided; and both be the pleaſure and profit ef each other: And ſo, is <hi>England</hi> a <hi>Treee of life,</hi> under which we ſhall <hi>ſit and eat the fruit of it in peace;</hi> and out of which we ſhall all <hi>grow,</hi> and <hi>bring forth fruit of righteouſneſſe</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The order and manner of this diſtribution is excellent; into a ſuperiour and inferiour; a firſt and ſecond: two without this <hi>ſubordination,</hi> would not be ſo ſafe, ſo profitable, nor ſo delightfull: But being two, ſubordinate one to another, without offending each other, <hi>yea,</hi> to the advantage of each other is <hi>exceeding delightfull:</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> the Father, hath all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; People, the Son, al diſpenced: in the firſt, its abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and intire; in the ſecond, its propagated, enlarged, ſpread-forth: The Huſband gives, the Wife receives; hee hath all, and beſtowes it; ſhe hath all, and receives it. The <hi>King</hi> ſaies, <hi>ask what you will and it ſhall be given unto you;</hi> (ſo GOD ſaies to Chriſt) chuſe what Laws and Priviledges you will, Ile grant it; That's my <hi>word and Oath:</hi> I have no <hi>nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive voice;</hi> I can't deny you. But this is no wrong to the <hi>King;</hi> for the Parliament being one ſpirit with him, can aſk no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what he is minded to give: as prayers in the Church; though <hi>GOD</hi> bee bound to give yet its no loſſe to him, becauſe his own Spirit aſks, for we know not what to aſk: So the KING is the originall of aſking, and gives the deſire of the thing: that which moves the inferiour to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is moſt excellent in the ſuperiour; and in this is the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the King, hee ſhall ſtill call, <hi>ask of ME;</hi> and ſhall ſtill out-goe the deſires of the Petitioners, and give more
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:116405:47"/>then they can aſk; his heart being more large towards his Spouſe or Childe, then his Spouſe or Childe can bee to it ſelfe; and that minde that is in the Spouſe or Childe, of good to it ſelfe, is in the Father before it was in the Son, and more excellently: Neither can the Sonne aſk any thing in this ſpirit, that can derogate from the Father; for thereby he ſhould prejudice himſelf; and weaken, or leſſen that power that conveighs good to him, and ſo wrong himſelf moſt, to wrong his head or fountaine from whence he is ſupplyed: Neither is it any wrong to the Son to have it this way, but tis the moſt perfect way of having it by aſking it of another; for thus, there is a ſtock and treaſure in which is ſtore layd up that is the Sonnes riches; the ſureſt and ſweeteſt way of having, is by the eaſy way of asking: Tis the excellency of it, that it's a gift, and that tis free; or that it hath the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſtamp of love and Authority upon it; by which it is not a ſtolne and forced, but lawfull and pleaſant favour: Tis a free and ingenious ſubordination; where the inferiour hath power to chuſe what it will; and chuſes to have it in that way, and not in another; and hath that freedome in aſking that is powerfull; <hi>The woman hath power over the head,</hi> to command by love; and to ſay as Chriſt, <hi>I will</hi> have it ſo: and then tis moſt acceptable to the Father, <hi>when it is moſt boldly and freely ask'd:</hi> it being the great joy of the head to have the wife <hi>confident in his love:</hi> And in this way there is, and ſhal be <hi>a river of pleaſure</hi> running betwen King and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; or <hi>from King, and Parliament, and People;</hi> wherein they ſhal do nothing <hi>but pleaſe one another:</hi> The fulnes of the one, compleatly anſwering the largeneſſe of the other.</p>
            <p>And the KING having to give what ever the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament or People can deſire; and deſiring them to receive as much, as they deſire him to give; and taking more
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:116405:47"/>pleaſure in <hi>creating greatneſſe</hi> and <hi>freedome</hi> in them, then in poſſeſſing of it himſelf; it being his nature and place to give forth, and without their receiving <hi>honour</hi> from him he were not a King: and it being as <hi>pleaſant</hi> to the <hi>People</hi> to receive it from a <hi>King:</hi> it would not <hi>content</hi> them to have it in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but their <hi>Kings gift</hi> ſets the price upon all <hi>favours</hi> they doe <hi>enjoy;</hi> its therefore ſweet becauſe their <hi>Lord</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowes it upon them.</p>
            <p>This is the <hi>floriſhing</hi> eſtate of <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> in their <hi>reſtored life;</hi> living now in the <hi>glory</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> and in <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> As <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Christ</hi> are of themſelves; are in each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and neither without each other; but the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of both is <hi>compleated,</hi> in their <hi>dwelling together</hi> in the third the <hi>Spirit:</hi> where they doe continually delight in each other, in beſtowing themſelves upon each other, and are moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in <hi>fellowſhip:</hi> ſo 'tis a heavenly <hi>bleſſedneſſe</hi> for <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Body</hi> to be thus <hi>united,</hi> and to <hi>give</hi> and <hi>take</hi> largely and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to communicate themſelves to each other.</p>
            <p>The <hi>King</hi> in proſperity, in <hi>health, strength</hi> and <hi>pleaſure,</hi> is in <hi>breaking</hi> forth his <hi>Majeſty</hi> upon his <hi>Nobles,</hi> that have affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to his <hi>greatneſſe:</hi> thence to derive it to the <hi>People;</hi> this is a full King in hight &amp; bredth: and a <hi>People aſcending through the Lords</hi> into the <hi>boſome</hi> of the King; is a People in hight and depth: the body in proſperity and pleaſure: three <hi>states</hi> in one, and one in three; in perfect <hi>agreement,</hi> and in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat <hi>unity:</hi> all make up but one <hi>fulneſſe,</hi> one Kingdome. Thus each is a <hi>Heaven</hi> to himſelf, and a <hi>Heaven</hi> to the other: and this conjunction by this <hi>righteous law of Spirit;</hi> the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Heavens,</hi> being all in the <hi>light</hi> and face of the eternall <hi>majeſtty:</hi> This is the <hi>great</hi> and main <hi>pillar</hi> of <hi>Englands</hi> happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; the foundation of our <hi>comfort:</hi> which as its moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in its ſelf, ſo it will effectually change the whole
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:116405:48"/>Kingdome into its <hi>forme:</hi> all <hi>parts</hi> muſt follow the <hi>conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of King and Parliament; yea, all are included in it; in this our whole <hi>happineſſe lies:</hi> The body being thus in <hi>health</hi> it cannot but ſend forth <hi>nouriſhment</hi> into every part: not a man in <hi>England</hi> but ſhall preſently finde a reviving upon this <hi>agreement;</hi> a new <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>love, joy, comfort, trade,</hi> and <hi>proſperity</hi> is <hi>immediatly</hi> diſperſed into the whole <hi>Nation:</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one <hi>leaping</hi> for <hi>joy</hi> in the <hi>goodneſſe</hi> of God, and the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of the Nation.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. XVIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Of the Cure of the People of the Land by this Death and Reſurrection.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THE God of the whole Earth delights to doe <hi>great things,</hi> and to fill the whole earth with his <hi>glory:</hi> The <hi>great</hi> favour of <hi>divine preſence,</hi> of love and peace, is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for <hi>Princes</hi> alone; but to be communicated <hi>generally</hi> to all People, <hi>That all the ends of the earth may ſee the ſalvation of our God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You the People of <hi>England</hi> have ſinned, <hi>Wee have all like ſheep gon aſtray; but God laies on him the iniquities of us all:</hi> Wee ſee the zeale of Chriſt under your blinde <hi>rage</hi> one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another: Chriſt in you in <hi>weakneſſe</hi> and infirmity: The Lord ſaith of you, <hi>You are my People, all my children:</hi> your <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, relations, comforts, and perſons</hi> are the Lords: not one <hi>Engliſh</hi> man or woman, but carries the Lord with him and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:116405:48"/>in him. The Land-Lord is the Lord of the Earth; the Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is the Son holding of the Father all he hath. The buyer, the ſeller; the rich the poor; Maſter and Servant; Father and Son; Huſband and Wife, are all but various breakings forth of God and Chriſt, and the ſeverall enjoyments they have of each ether; and paſſing from one to the other by and in the Spirit. Miniſters and People, Townes, Corporations, Manufactures, Markets, Graſing, Feeding, all but the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant flowings forth of the fulneſſe of Chriſt; pleaſed to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it ſelf in ſuch formes.</p>
            <p>You are all one Common-wealth of God and Chriſt; and in you all doth Chriſt ſuffer; in that deadnes, diſorder, ſpoil, confuſion that is amongſt you, doth the body of Chriſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. Tis the blood of Chriſt that gives life to all theſe things; and in the ſpilling of them his blood is ſpilt: With him you ſuffer, as he with you: The <hi>glory, riches, peace</hi> and <hi>comfort</hi> of <hi>England</hi> is become a <hi>troubled Sea,</hi> yea, <hi>mare mortuum,</hi> a <hi>dead</hi> Sea. There is no life in any thing you doe: no joy in your labours; no comfort in your lives; no hope of enjoying what you have: a <hi>Chaos,</hi> a <hi>great grave</hi> is <hi>England</hi> become, wherein is caſt all her riches.</p>
            <p>But by this death, is Satan the Prince of death overcome; the author of your miſeries; the deſtroyer of the earth; that fils you with wanes, ſuits quarrels; that ſowed the tears of ſtrife amongſt Gods huſbandry: that hot fiery Serpent that provoaked thirſt to drunkenneſſe; that <hi>empty, hungry fiend</hi> that led you to <hi>gluttony;</hi> that filthy one that wrought brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in your families; diſcontents in your relations; waſting in your eſtates; that curſed all your bleſſings; denies you joy, mirth, ſports, recreations: Thou enemy of man art ſlain; and with thee darkneſſe, blindneſſe, miſtakes, accuſations, treacheries, lies, falſhoods, that vexed Engliſh men: Theſe
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:116405:49"/>hatefull quarrels between <hi>Round-head and Cavalier,</hi> are dead and buried; with all your tranſgreſſions one againſt another; and all will and power to miſchief one another: That <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wall is broken down</hi> that kept you at diſtance from God, and from each other; that made you dark, ignorant and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in your way: And you are now raiſd in a new life; <hi>The old heaven and earth is fled away,</hi> becauſe it was corrupt; <hi>and we have a new heaven and a new earth, wherein dwels righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi> In all your waies, buſineſſe, trade, ſports, neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, dwels <hi>the God of righteouſneſſe: they are all in God, and God in them; the goodneſſe of God flows forth in them;</hi> and all of them ſhall bee filled with the peace, joy, and life of God: <hi>Truth ſtall ſpring out of the earth, and Righteouſneſſe look downe from heaven: The Lord ſhall give that which is good, and our Land ſhall yeild her increaſe.</hi> You are ſow'd in ſin, in darknes; and ſhall riſe <hi>now</hi> light and holyneſſe: and with you truth it ſelf: The true and living God ſhall ſpring up in <hi>every thing:</hi> The truth of <hi>God</hi> filling all your fields with corne; paſtures, with graſſe; <hi>that which is good,</hi> God Himſelfe: your corne ſhall be better then <hi>Manna, Angels food;</hi> you ſhall feed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually upon the <hi>bread of life:</hi> you ſhall lye down quietly in the <hi>armes of God, and none ſhall make you afraid: God Reigns, let the earth rejoyce; let all that is in it be glad:</hi> you ſhall have mirth, plenty, wealth, food, rayment, and <hi>GOD all in all:</hi> You ſhall be Govern'd by God in peace and righteouſneſſe; the wicked one ſhall be deſtroyed for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Sonnes ſhall be as plants</hi> grown up in their youth; our <hi>Daughters</hi> as corner ſtones, polliſhed after the manner of a <hi>Palace;</hi> our <hi>Garners</hi> full of all manner of ſtore; our <hi>Sheep</hi> ſhal bring forth thouſands and ten thouſands in our ſtreets; our <hi>Oxen</hi> ſtrong to labour: there ſhal be no breaking in of <hi>trouble;</hi> nor going out of <hi>comfort: no complaining in our streets: Happy
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:116405:49"/>are the People that is in ſuch a caſe; yea happy is the People whoſe God is the Lord.</hi> This is the Great happineſſe, <hi>God is our God, and we his People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>ye may ſit under your own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine, and under your own Figge-tree;</hi> which is, the love of God ſhadowing you, and feeding of you: <hi>Let the earth be full of the knowledge of the</hi> LORD, <hi>as the waters cover the Sea:</hi> there ſhall be none bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren of the <hi>grace of God</hi> amongſt you; not a dark corner of the Earth for cruelty to dwell in; but all ſhall bee enlightened with the joy and peace of God: ſuch a power of light and heat ſhal ſhine <hi>from the Sun of righteouſneſſe,</hi> as ſhall melt the <hi>churles</hi> heart into liberality; the <hi>Land-lord</hi> ſhall not rack you; nor the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurer</hi> grinde you; <hi>Taxes</hi> and <hi>Exciſe</hi> ſhal not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe you: The <hi>rich</hi> ſhall not be a priſoner to his wealth, nor the <hi>poor</hi> for want; he that hoorded corne ſhall bring it forth; the buried mony ſhal riſe; trade ſhall revive; the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry ſhall be fed; the naked cloathed: all happy, but he that refuſes and reſiſts this grace, <hi>the Devill.</hi> You ſhall all <hi>praiſe the Lord, from the riſing of the Sun to the going down of it:</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the <hi>King,</hi> in the Parliament; all their <hi>honour, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and dominion</hi> is yours; you ſhall have the comfort and benifit of it; and from them ſhall you receive flouds and ſtreames of <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> that none ſhall want: the rich ſhall be <hi>freed from the curſe</hi> in his wealth; and deſire no more: the poor ſhall be ſatisfied and have <hi>enough:</hi> every one, and every thing ſhall be filled<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And your railings ſhall be turned into <hi>ſongs;</hi> your fightings into <hi>daunces;</hi> your feares into rejoyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: live in love, <hi>in the face of God, as brethren;</hi> as owe <hi>family;</hi> lying in the wombe of one happy Mother, <hi>England; a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice; the Land of Emanuel;</hi> rejoycing in the proſperity of each other: and the <hi>heavens ſhall bleſſe you;</hi> the God of heaven ſhal ſhine on you: <hi>Chriſt,</hi> The true Heaven is open to you: <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:116405:50"/>Magiſtrats</hi> look gently upon you in love, ſmile on you: and theſe lowring, frowning <hi>clouds</hi> that have vexed you with exceſſe of raine, ſhall be ſcattered; and theſe heavens ſhall favour you with ſeaſonable weather; you ſhall have all bleſſings <hi>of heaven and earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, the People are <hi>recovered from ſlavery under Satan, and wicked men;</hi> into a <hi>freedome to live in the face of God:</hi> into freedome with, and union to their <hi>King,</hi> their <hi>Parliament;</hi> and <hi>amongst themſelves;</hi> and ſo are free-borne; <hi>a Nation borne in one day;</hi> a Royall and Princly race; a bleſſed and happy generation; Borne of GOD, and of their KING.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. XIX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> The reſtoration of the Miniſtry, by Chriſts bearing their ſin, and by his death and reſurrection.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THE Miniſtry hath been deeply defiled, and wofully accurſed; they lye under great ſinnes, and heavy judgements: But here is <hi>balme</hi> for them, a <hi>Phyſitian</hi> will cure them; a <hi>fire</hi> will pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify the <hi>Sonnes of Levi:</hi> you are the <hi>LORDS</hi> portion; GOD who ſaid <hi>you were not my People,</hi> will ſay, <hi>you are the People of the living God: Idol Shepherds</hi> are you; but the <hi>GREAT Shepherd</hi> is ſeeking after you; and will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore you.</p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:116405:50"/>
            <p>The Lord is under your ſinnes; bears your iniquities un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Luciferian pride</hi> of Epiſcopacy ſeeking to advance themſelves into worldly greatnes; into Princes favour; into Lordlineſſe: it being broken in peeces, we ſee under it, the Kingly and Prieſtly Office of Chriſt in union: the Son exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf from a poor miniſter a <hi>Carpenters Son,</hi> to <hi>ſit upon a Throne, far above all principalities and powers:</hi> In their <hi>pomp</hi> and <hi>ſtate</hi> of living and worſhipping God in an eaſy, rich, and brave way, is darkly repreſented the <hi>glory of the Church, Zion ſucking the milk of the Gentiles:</hi> having <hi>Kings and Queens nurſing Fathers and nurſing Mothers: and bowing to the ſoles of her feet:</hi> Chriſt in <hi>glory,</hi> under this <hi>abominable filth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> rigid and harſh yoak of Government forcing the mindes of men into a obſervance of their Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation: We now ſee the ſeverity of Chriſt and his ſtrength and power; his <hi>heat</hi> and <hi>zeal;</hi> not contented with a cold for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality; but requiring every <hi>Sacrifice</hi> to be <hi>ſalted</hi> with <hi>fire:</hi> a ſmoaky and dark ſhadow of the <hi>baptiſme of the holy Ghoſt and fire:</hi> Chriſt in power, under miſerable <hi>weaknes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Independents</hi> uniting their <hi>Churches</hi> cloſe into one intire body, and keeping of them under their own imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate care; and not ſuffering them to acknowledge any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther power: we ſee there lyes in it the <hi>pastorall</hi> care of Chriſt <hi>carrying his Lambs his boſome: heavenly union:</hi> Chriſt keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his <hi>Spouſe chast</hi> to himſelf; his perſonall and immediate <hi>governing of them,</hi> and his abſolutenes and Lordlineſſe over them: Chriſt abſolute, and his people independent, living only in and with himſelf.</p>
            <p>In their ſharp oppoſing one another, being intolerable one to another; is the <hi>zeal</hi> of the Lord of hoſt ſeen; his <hi>jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſy that is impatient, of having his Spouſe taken from him:</hi> their <hi>perſecuting</hi> one another; a ſhadow of thoſe ſtormes and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:116405:51"/>tempeſts wherewith he perſecutes them that take his <hi>Spouſe</hi> his People from him.</p>
            <p>In all theſe there are ſome particular excellencies of Chriſt ſcattered; they have gotten each a peece of the <hi>ſeamles coat of Christ:</hi> or elſe they could not be a rent or ſchiſme, but in all his <hi>viſage</hi> is ſo marred, his <hi>form</hi> ſo <hi>uncomly,</hi> that he is there <hi>unknown to any,</hi> even to themſelves.</p>
            <p>Chriſt bears their <hi>ſhame</hi> upon his <hi>own body on the tree: in their ſhame and repoach he is reproached:</hi> ſuffers <hi>deeply</hi> for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſuch a filthy <hi>ſhape,</hi> both from themſelves and others: all the <hi>honour, beauty, order, uniformity</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> is the Lord, <hi>his face vaild and covered:</hi> and now tis a <hi>ruinous heape,</hi> he lies <hi>buried in it,</hi> under <hi>diviſions, factions, hereſies, reproach:</hi> by all this his <hi>true body</hi> is <hi>broken, pierced, ſlain:</hi> This is your <hi>ſacrifice,</hi> O yee <hi>Priests, this blood must waſh you, and make an atonement;</hi> and it is ſufficient to <hi>take away your ſinnes though as red as ſcarlet;</hi> and put you again into <hi>white garments;</hi> this will ſatisfy Gods <hi>wrath,</hi> and then the <hi>rage</hi> of the Nation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, and the <hi>wrath</hi> one <hi>against</hi> another will <hi>dye; Chriſts body is dead;</hi> and you are <hi>dead;</hi> you are <hi>ſpirit-leſſe, life-leſſe,</hi> a meer <hi>carcaſſe, rotten ſepulchers;</hi> That which you fear is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you; the <hi>Witneſſes are ſlain by the Beaſt coming out of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe Pit: The carcaſes lies in the ſtreets of the great City, ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, trampled upon:</hi> your ſhame un-buried; <hi>where our Lord was crucified.</hi> Diſſolved and broken amongſt your ſelves, from the People, and moſt from the Lord: your live in a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable world, and not in <hi>Heaven,</hi> which only is true life: and with you dies the <hi>falſe Prophet,</hi> the <hi>deceiver;</hi> the <hi>Father of lies</hi> and all the <hi>deluſions</hi> of the <hi>devil,</hi> and all <hi>inſulting pride,</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veteouſneſſe, worldlineſſe, malice, perſecution, and vaine <hi>glory:</hi> and by this fire of God upon you ſhall you be purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and cleanſed: By death the <hi>partition wall is broken down,</hi>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:116405:51"/>betwixt God and you, betwixt your ſelves, and betwixt you and your People. Of two, God and man, <hi>heavenly</hi> and <hi>earthly prieſthood,</hi> made one <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> one new man: The <hi>vail is rent,</hi> and you are now admitted into <hi>the holieſt;</hi> and of many kindes of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> you are one <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> one tribe, one body in many members; one Chriſt: and you and People are one <hi>Clergy, one lot and inheritance;</hi> the <hi>people</hi> Prieſts with you, and you people with them; all the Lords People holy: their <hi>jealouſy</hi> and <hi>enmity,</hi> your <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>loftineſſe</hi> being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God will not ſuffer his holy one to ſee corruption:</hi> But will <hi>raiſe</hi> you up together with <hi>Christ: Levi</hi> ſhall never want a man to <hi>miniſter before him: If you can break the covenant of the day and of the night, that there ſhould be no more day nor night in their ſeaſon, then may alſo my Covenant bee broken with Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid my ſervant, &amp;c. and with the Levits the Priests my mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters:</hi> The night of their calamity ſhall be followed with a day of rejoycing: And though <hi>the Sun have ſet upon the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, yet it ſtall riſe again; David</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> ſhall have heires: Chriſt ſhall have Kings and Miniſters; Kings <hi>propheticall</hi> or <hi>prieſtly,</hi> anointed with fulnes of <hi>ſpirit</hi> for both; and Prieſts <hi>Regall,</hi> or <hi>royall,</hi> to govern the houſe of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now Joſhua thou great high priest, and thy fellowes men won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at: Ile take away thy filthy garments from thee, and will cloath thee with change of rayment; Ile remove thy iniquity off that land in one day; and bring forth the branch.</hi> The Lord and all his twigs growing out of him: full of the Spirit of God; <hi>in the compleatneſſe and fulnes of the ſpirit; ſeven eyes upon one ſtone;</hi> much <hi>light</hi> and underſtanding: The Lord himſelf ſhall be the <hi>Temple, ministers, people, gifts,</hi> &amp; all, &amp; we ſhall all <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> in the houſe of <hi>God</hi> for ever: now are you <hi>Divines indeed; holy men, men of God, one with the holy divinity, ſhining</hi>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:116405:52"/>in the brightnes and majeſty, in the wiſdome and judgement of God; <hi>Anointed with holy Oyle; cloathed with beautiful gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of righteouſneſſe, truth and peace.</p>
            <p>Now raiſd out of the duſt as <hi>the ſtones of Zion; as dried bones</hi> reſtored to life by the Spirit of the <hi>LORD:</hi> God ſends a plentifull rain, ſhowers of righteouſneſſe, whereby thou wilt confirme <hi>Levi,</hi> thine inheritance when it was weary: The Lord gives the word, <hi>Ariſe, and great is the company of them that publiſhed it. Though ye have lain among the pots;</hi> Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin Prieſts, that have ſerved for the belly; Now, <hi>as the wings of a dove, covered with ſilver, and her ſet hers with yellow gold:</hi> Winged now with the Dove, the Spirits ſtrength, in the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and excellency of ſilver and gold; by heavenly and holy gifts, we ſhall fly aloft; and live alwaies in the clearnes and light of God; not in the baſeneſſe and foulneſſe of the world. Chriſt aſcended on high, and will give liberal gifts, all kinds; Biſhops, Preſbyters, Independents, Apoſtles, Evangeliſts, Paſtors, &amp;c. yea, <hi>for the rebellious alſo, that the Lord God may dwell amongſt them:</hi> God ſtreaming himſelf forth in all varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Offices and Officers, none in vaine; all filld with grace and power.</p>
            <p>Now in this reſtored condition all one with God, indeed ſpirituall and heavenly, <hi>of pure gold:</hi> And one with, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, <hi>as Stars of ſeverall magnitude,</hi> moving in there diſtinct <hi>Orbs:</hi> all glorious lights, yet differing in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent variety one from another in glory; and all pleaſant and uſefull one to another: And in union with the State, or <hi>Kingdome:</hi> You were divided, you kept them from medling with Spirituall things; and they in requitall and revenge, excluded you from Civill things; you both in your dark and worldly ſtate, made lawes againſt each other: The heavenly, or ſpirituall men, muſt not medle with earthly affaires; they
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:116405:52"/>defile them; nor <hi>earthly</hi> men <hi>act</hi> in <hi>heavenly</hi> or ſpirituall. Thus were you cruell, and unkinde to your ſelves and to each other; one <hi>ſetting up an Heaven without an earth,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an <hi>earth without a heaven.</hi> Theſe in the Lord are <hi>marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together in perfect union;</hi> the ſame Lord being by the ſame <hi>ſpirit King and Prieſt,</hi> and adminiſtring his Church and <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> together: they are joynd in the King, and muſt run down in fellowſhip together into the lower parts: <hi>Now truth ſprings out of the earth:</hi> You ſhall have God and Chriſt in the truth of the Spirit, <hi>ſpringing up in all your civill affaires;</hi> in all your Lawes, Statutes, cuſtomes, nothing elſe but heavenly truth: and all your buſineſſe, civill and naturall ſhall be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Lord; bleſſed <hi>Ordinances of Heaven:</hi> you ſhall be in all of them in the light of God, and <hi>miniſter in Gods preſence: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the horſe bridles, upon the pots, upon all things written holineſſe to the Lord: And righteouſneſſe ſhall look down from Heaven:</hi> Heaven ſhall ſhine forth to you righteous lawes: You ſhall ſee the ſame things done in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that are done in the earth: looking in each others face and anſwering one another: heer in <hi>THIS</hi> world earth will be no burden to Heaven, being new; and <hi>Heaven no trouble to</hi> earth, no <hi>ſtranger,</hi> when ſhee ſhewes her <hi>face</hi> and looks out ſhe is the ſame <hi>thing:</hi> and both <hi>joyning together, ſalvation ſprings forth of them:</hi> the Earth by her <hi>fellowſhip with Heaven</hi> brings forth <hi>good fruit: peace, righteouſneſſe</hi> and <hi>justice</hi> for the Land: and the <hi>Earth</hi> without <hi>Heaven, brings forth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but cold, dead Lawes:</hi> and <hi>Heaven</hi> without <hi>Earth</hi> but <hi>airy phanſies:</hi> both in <hi>conjunction</hi> make a compleat <hi>happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſhall we meet together all Sorts in a <hi>generall aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly,</hi> in the <hi>light of Heaven,</hi> as <hi>golden candleſticks; The holy one walkes in the midest of us, emptying the golden Oyle,</hi> by <hi>golden
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:116405:53"/>pipes</hi> from his <hi>golden ſelf,</hi> into his <hi>golden veſſels,</hi> his <hi>miniſters:</hi> And in this <hi>holy aſſembly,</hi> ſitting in the light of God, all things ſhall be manifeſt to us; wee ſhall ſee the whole forme of the houſe of God; all the <hi>doors, windows and pillars</hi> of it; nothing of its <hi>statutes and ordinances</hi> ſhall be hid from us: no error ſhal go undiſcovered, unrefuted; all that have gon aſtray ſhall be brought back; the ignorant ſhall be inſtructed; the oppoſing and diſſenting convinced; and the obſtinate rejected, and caſt out: ſuch a harmony and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of hearts and mindes in this love and light, muſt needs bring forth bleſſed fruit: What ever is true in any <hi>religion,</hi> we ſhall owne; what is falſe, we ſhall judge: The darkneſs of Popery ſhall fall before our light; we ſhall undermine the <hi>Kingdome of darkneſſe,</hi> and ſet up truth in that beauty and majeſty as ſhall gain all hearts; upon ſuch firme pillars as none can move her.</p>
            <p>Wee feare not Papiſts, nor all their ſtrength; we ſhall need no Lawes againſt them, but <hi>The Law of the Spirit of life;</hi> which wee know will over-come them: The Gates of our Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhall be open <hi>night and day;</hi> let who will come in or go out: <hi>No <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleane thing ſhall enter</hi> into us; But all the KINGS of the Earth; all the wiſdome, ſtate, pompe and glory of <hi>Rome;</hi> and all the World, muſt bring their glory to this City, this <hi>New Jeruſalem:</hi> And all the Nations upon Earth that ſhall be ſaved, <hi>ſhall walke in the light of it.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="chapter">
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:116405:53"/>
            <head>Chap. XX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Of the reſtoration of the Army, Levellers, and City of London.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THE Army is but a particular part, and that temporary, and occaſionall; and is by this bright ſhining of the Sun of <hi>Righteouſnes,</hi> melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into a generall peace and unity, but lying under a particular condemnation, it ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a particular diſcharge. And we know thy imployment is ſo irkſome and unpleaſant to thee, To be the kingdomes Gaoler, to keep war in, and peace out; or to ſtand <hi>in the way to the Tree of life, with a flaming ſword;</hi> to keep men from the injoyment of their liberty, KING, peace; though thou art commanded to it by God (theſe things being yet forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the people) yet thou wilt be glad to be releaſed from it; that thou and all other may come into the Paradiſe of God, and feed together upon the fruit of Divine peace and love.</p>
            <p>There is, under thy aſſuming power over the Kingdome, <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> and all; and in thy maintaining thy Military power above, and againſt the Civill; in thy ſeeking thy owne ſubſiſting, and attempting to bee the <hi>Kingdomes</hi> Lord and reſtorer: The <hi>Lord</hi> cloathing himſelf with zeal, as with a garment, incompaſſing himſelf about with flames of fire: <hi>A Man of War, a Lord of Hoſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Caſting away his Fatherly Government, becauſe of the Nations rebellion in all parts againſt himſelfe, and ruling us with a Rod of Iron. God marching before us, out of Egypts ſlavery, into
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:116405:54"/>a Wilderneſſe; turning us from a Civil Government into a Wilderneſſe; and incamping in the mideſt of us; and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtering Laws to us; <hi>as at ſinai:</hi> in thundering and lightning, clouds and darknenſſe; ſo terrible, that makes all tremble: A <hi>yoke that neither we, nor our Fathers are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to beare:</hi> And ſo we ſee Gods ſeverity, under mans ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities: And becauſe it is the Lords Rod, we kiſſe the Rod, and love you for it.</p>
            <p>Death is proper for this adminiſtration: The <hi>Lord, our Husband,</hi> the Law dies; wee were bound to honour you ſo long as you lived in the power and goodnes of God; The whole Kingdome bowed before you; while you led us ſafely through the Wildernes: But <hi>Moſes</hi> cannot bring us into <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan;</hi> but muſt only have a <hi>view of it,</hi> and dye at <hi>mount Nebo:</hi> This power is weak through the fleſh, and cannot do it; if you contend now to effect any thing, it is but the Devil ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>for the body of Moſes;</hi> you are labouring to ſet up an honourable carcaſſe; or to call back life into a dead body: Chriſt did come into it, and hath offered it up in his owne body, and naild this power faſt to the Tree; you are dead, fixt to the tree of ſhame, by the curſe with your Lord; and by death you ſhall over come more then ever you overcame by life; ſubmitting to death, your wils, reaſons, luſts; your ſeeking a worldly Kingdome; your deſire of lording it over others by force of armes, with all your projects, are ſlaine; and all enmity in you againſt others, and others againſt you.</p>
            <p>Death hath <hi>disbanded</hi> you; eaſd you of your helliſh and wrathfull imployment: Reconciled you to all, and all to you; brought you from being Turkiſh Janiſaries, to bee <hi>Engliſh men:</hi> You are diſolved into a body of love; into GOD: you lye downe in the Eternall.</p>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:116405:54"/>
            <p>By this your arreares are paid; you are nothing, you are dead, and you can require nothing; you, and your demands are fallen to the ground; your ſervice is dead, and nothing is due to it, but to be buried, and all your miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, in forgetfulneſſe. Who do you require arreares of? The Kingdome is dead; the ſword reignes, and therefore the Kingdome is free: if you will be paid, take <hi>blood, want, ſpoile, confuſion, ruin;</hi> that's all that is left of the <hi>Kingdome;</hi> pay your ſelves of that. Do you expect it of the <hi>Parliament?</hi> That is dead too. Poor Parliament, you have eat it up your ſelves in greedines of pay, you tore her bowels out; and you can have no more.</p>
            <p>But all anger is paſt, there remaines nothing but love: you are dead, and live with Chriſt: come forth of your graves; ſtand up in the reſurrection of Chriſt, in union and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with Chriſt. <hi>The Lords hoſt;</hi> now the Lord is in you; and you pitch your tents about the Lord; and are the arme of God, ſtretched out for his owne defence, and for the pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhing of tranſgreſſors; living in the ſtrength and Spirit of the Lord: and now, mighty and powerfull to execute Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine pleaſure: Now you are under <hi>the Captain of our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> and at once intereſted in the ſalvation of the <hi>Nation;</hi> and of Chriſt, our Saviour.</p>
            <p>Now we can pay you arreares: you never ſtuck upon ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reares till you ſunk into the earth, into poor earthly mindes; riſe you again into ſpirit, you will count it your honour to help <hi>England freely:</hi> Mony and a Saviour, cannot ſubſiſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. That Spirit of Chriſt that once acted in you to let goe the priſoners, <hi>Englands freedome and juſtice,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>price or reward;</hi> that ſpirit ſhall revive in you: and then you will ſcorne to be mercenary.</p>
            <p>I know you diſdaine to keep <hi>Englands</hi> woundes open
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:116405:55"/>to ſuck her blood: you have hazarded your lives for juſtice and freedome, and can't now inſiſt upon pay: you are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy your ſelves, and have the worth of all with you: if you deſire pay enter with us into <hi>Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>naan</hi> and you ſhall have <hi>Vinyards that you planted not; wels that you diged not: A land flowing with milk and hony;</hi> ſuch mercies and bleſſings as you could not expect: The Lord is Judge, he will <hi>audite</hi> your accompts, and pay all that he owes you: Religion flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the purity of it; peace and righteouſneſſe as Rivers and Seas; the ſweet, holy unmoleſted enjoyment, of your <hi>own</hi> families and eſtates, in the preſence &amp; under the <hi>govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of the moſt high: You ſhall now ſubſiſt in our <hi>bowels,</hi> be diſolved into the Church and <hi>Kingdome,</hi> which is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of Chriſt; <hi>Terrible as an Army with banners:</hi> terrible to the world and the God of the world; to the prince of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and ſo wee ſhall diſband you into ſpirit and power; the whole Nation ſhall be Souldiers <hi>able to draw the ſword of the Spirit againſt all forrain power;</hi> amongſt our ſelves wars ſhall ceaſe from the earth: you muſt <hi>beat</hi> your <hi>ſwords into plowſhares, and ſpiers into pruming hooks:</hi> to your honeſt trades again; there will need no Iron or ſteely wrath, but to plow up your own hearts, and to cut down enemies within your own breſts. all our <hi>Townes</hi> and <hi>Cities</hi> are <hi>gariſoned</hi> with a heavenly hoſt, and we have <hi>ſalvation</hi> for our <hi>wals</hi> and <hi>bulwarks; we ſhall lye down in peace and none make in afraid:</hi> while we need force we ſhall uſe you, but not in civil wars; you muſt be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and only imployed in ſervice againſt ſtrangers: if you delight to ſit down by the ſtill ſtreames of <hi>Englands</hi> peace, and feed in our green paſtures of eternall love, you ſhall: if your valour makes you deſirous of <hi>military</hi> actions, we ſhall finde enemies abroad to imploy your ſwords againſt: and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:116405:55"/>when you under take ſuch expeditions the Lord ſhall goe with you: you ſhall have Angels ſpirits that ſhall make you invincible where ever you goe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Levellers</hi> grew out of the Army, and are again ſhrunk into the Army, and therefore we will now joyne you to the Army, being mingled together. In your endeavour to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe your <hi>Democracy,</hi> your <hi>popular</hi> Government upon the Kingdome; over-throwing and overturning all powers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the People: <hi>we hear the voice of one crying in the Wildernes</hi> (<hi>England</hi> is become a Wilderneſſe) <hi>all fleſh graſſe</hi> (all pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is corrupt) the Spirit of the Lord hath blowne upon it and its withered: This is <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> that exalts the <hi>valies</hi> and brings down the <hi>hils:</hi> he brings all into the waters the People; God is in theſe <hi>Levellers</hi> caſting the Mountains into the depths of the Seas, plunging all into a confuſed People; not ſuffering <hi>one ſtone to lye upon another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thy place is to be in the Wilderneſſe, and not to come into the City: to expire and dye ſpeedily, to decreaſe, that he that comes after may increaſe: Thou art beheaded, thy devices are fallen to the <hi>ground:</hi> a <hi>muſhrome,</hi> thou wert little, and art nothing. <hi>What went you out to ſee? A reed ſhaken with the wined:</hi> growing out of the <hi>mire</hi> of the Nation: <hi>or a man clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with ſoft rayment?</hi> People got into Kings houſes. In this ſtate thou art <hi>vaniſht,</hi> loſt, and raiſed in the Spirit of Chriſt, the divine and eternall love of God: and in this <hi>Kingdome</hi> there is a perfect Levell: The People the originall of the Parliament and King, by a free giving up themſelves and and their eſtates to the Parliament and King, are in the King and Parliament, and fully pertake of the royalty and power of both, and are leveld with it: The People give ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory to the King, and ſo higher then hee, or he their Subject: He that gives is greater then he that receives:
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:116405:56"/>heer all the people are one with that ſpirit that is <hi>kingly</hi> that Anointing that makes <hi>Chriſt King:</hi> and ſo called <hi>mine Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> living all in the liberty of that ſpirit that makes Kings: and are moſt perfectly content in the Kings greatneſſe, being that which themſelves conſtitute: making it themſelves, they live in it and enjoy it: And the King is levelled to the people by his ſufferings or humiliations, and by his love taking in every Subject to himſelf: humbling of himſelf, to be but the Kingdoms Servant, and wearing his Crown only for the happineſſe and good of the people, living together, and brought into one body, head, and member. The eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall love is the <hi>Leveller,</hi> Divine Charity that lifts not up it ſelfe, but is lifted up; and being lifted up, drawes all after it.</p>
            <p>I rejoyce in the healing thy breaches, oh <hi>London,</hi> thou ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable City: Thy iniquities have been great, there is a righteous one under them that will carry them without the City as a ſcape Goat into the wilderneſſe: we ſee the Lord in thee in thy greateſt filth; in thy violent enforcing powers above thee to thy own minde, in conſtraining the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to thy will, by bold petitions urged with tumults: we ſee darkened and ſhadowed the interceſſion of the Son of God, who with violence wreſts from his Father favour for himſelf and his people: he comes with boldneſſe to take what he asks, and ſaies, <hi>I will;</hi> and the power that Saints have in Chriſt <hi>to command God in prayer.</hi> In thy ſiding with the Parliament againſt the King, and thy free powring forth thy ſelf for her: We ſee the exceſſive love of Chriſt to his Church, who is raviſht with love, and for her forgets all things elſe: In thy ingroſſing the riches of the Kingdome into thee; thou art a ſhadow of Chriſt, who treaſures up wealth and riches of glory in the City of God for us.</p>
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:116405:56"/>
            <p>But thy glory is gon, thy true life; the beautifull preſence of God hath left thee; and thou art burning in flames of wrath, jealouſies, envies, diviſions: thou art waſted into a <hi>ſceleton;</hi> thy trade obſtructed by Sea and Land; thy People filled with rage; thy bowels pained with fierce conteſts of parties, pulling various waies; quite reſtleſſe; an unquiet Sea, in continuall agitation. The Lord dyes in thee; the <hi>LORDS</hi> delight; thou wert his Spouſe: thy glory and greatneſſe, it was the <hi>LORDS;</hi> he ſuffers in thy ſuffering, and is covered in thy aſhes; lyes under the burthen of all thy wants; is pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with the neceſſities of the poor: And thou art in the duſt of confuſion; a ruinous heap; the ſeat and place of vexation; lying in a thick cloud of darkneſſe. But his fire purifies thee; in theſe flames thou loſeſt thy filthy pride, coveteouſneſſe, malice, revenge, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt not periſh utterly; <hi>The voice of God is heard in thee</hi> to revive thee: thou ſhalt be built again: <hi>Thy foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhall be all of precious ſtones</hi> &amp;c. The glory of God ſhall ſhine in thee: thou art now the City of God; a Righteous Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: this is thy name, <hi>The Lord is there:</hi> The Lord diſplaies his glory in the mideſt of thee: <hi>The new Jeruſalem</hi> indeed, in truth, in Spirit, in perfect union with GOD; a heaven, and ſo in union amongſt your ſelves; <hi>Peace within thy wals, and plentiouſnes in thy palaces:</hi> a City at unity in it ſelf; there ſhall not be the leaſt found of diſcord in thee: Thy nature is love, light and holines; <hi>The City of the great King:</hi> made happy by the preſence of the <hi>King,</hi> and all the <hi>state</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome:</hi> Now open thy armes of <hi>Divine love,</hi> and take in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy imbraces the glory of <hi>England: Kings, Princes, Nobility, Gentry, Miniſtry, Judges, Lawyers, with all the wiſdom, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, power and excellency</hi> of heaven and earth; let all flock
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:116405:57"/>together; in one God, one Chriſt, one Spirit; one City, and thouſands of thouſands of Saints and Angels dwelling in thee. Nothing ſhal be heard in thee but mirth and joy in the Lord our God; praiſes of the Great <hi>King: Open thy gates, thy everlasting doors, that the King of glory,</hi> the Lord of Hoſts, with all his hoſt of Princly powers, <hi>may enter in:</hi> And all the riches of the World ſhal flow into thee in thy trade, natur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and abundantly: the wealth of both <hi>Indies,</hi> and all parts, ſhal ſeek unto thee, and offer up it ſelfe to ſatisfy thee: thou ſhalt be crownd with bleſſings; all contents and pleaſures ſhal continually run dawn thy ſtreets; and all in the ſight and face of the holy God; in the pure River of life.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. XXI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Of the admirable fullneſſe and compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this reſtoration, ſatisfying all intereſts.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>ALL <hi>the works of God are perfect, found out of all them that take pleaſure therein:</hi> The greateſt and higheſt, are reſerved for us, in this later, and great <hi>day of God;</hi> wherein it pleaſeth the LORD to appear in his fulleſt, and moſt excellent glory: this of <hi>Englands</hi> ſalvation is a ſweet bud of it; a little taſte of that infinite Majeſty that is now breaking forth, in the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious appearing of God. In this buſineſſe, the Lord ſatisfieth his own Intereſt, who is <hi>Alpha, and Omega; the first, and the</hi>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:116405:57"/>laſt: and this is the rock of our pleaſure <hi>that thou art pleaſed,</hi> and ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>Thou <hi>reigneſt,</hi> thou art <hi>King:</hi> this is thy due, all power and dominion is thine; tis thy <hi>right</hi> to have all, all are thine, for <hi>thee</hi> they were created and made, <hi>King,</hi> Parliament, Lords, Commons, Miniſters, People, all ſorts, all ſides, all parties are the Lords, and thou wilt <hi>reign</hi> over and in all: from Sea to Sea, from one end of the Earth to the other, as <hi>lightening ſhining</hi> from Eaſt to Weſt: ſo is thy <hi>Kingdom;</hi> and thy <hi>glory</hi> is now due to thee, that thou ſhouldeſt appear not in weakneſſe to ſerve men, but in thy <hi>great Majeſty,</hi> in thy <hi>highest</hi> honour thou muſt now ſhew forth plainly thy ſelf in thy utmoſt &amp; <hi>moſt enlarged goodneſſe,</hi> power &amp; wiſdom: <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> now will ſerve thee but to be <hi>ALL IN ALL:</hi> To be <hi>All</hi> thou art in Heaven, <hi>in all</hi> the Earth, to bring forth <hi>all</hi> thy riches to fill every creature, <hi>all glory</hi> in <hi>all things:</hi> Thou art <hi>all</hi> in Earth as well as <hi>all</hi> in Heaven, <hi>all</hi> in <hi>King,</hi> in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in People, there is nothing but thy ſelf in theſe; thou art Biſhops, Presbyters, Independents, <hi>all</hi> theſe, and <hi>all</hi> in theſe; <hi>all Majesty,</hi> power, <hi>glory,</hi> juſtice, in the <hi>King;</hi> and <hi>all</hi> the ſame in the Parliament, and <hi>all</hi> that too in the People: thou art <hi>all</hi> the labour, ſtrength<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> riches, freedome in the People, <hi>all</hi> this in the Parliament, <hi>all</hi> the ſame in the King, <hi>all</hi> night and <hi>all</hi> lowneſſe: Thou art <hi>all</hi> wiſdom, Authority, Government in Biſhops; <hi>all</hi> care, zeal, labour in Presbyters; <hi>all</hi> love, union, abſoluteneſſe in Independents: and <hi>all</hi> theſe in every one; thou art the ſame in <hi>all, ALL IN ALL: All</hi> in darkneſſe <hi>all</hi> in light, <hi>all</hi> in weakneſſe, <hi>all</hi> in ſtrength: <hi>all</hi> that every part is, <hi>all</hi> the wholl is, <hi>all</hi> the wholl in every part: and <hi>all</hi> Heaven, <hi>all</hi> Glory, <hi>all</hi> peace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>all</hi> quietneſſe, <hi>all</hi> love, <hi>all</hi> goodneſſe in <hi>all</hi> theſe parts and wholl: Leſſe then this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and near union and <hi>mariage</hi> will not ſatisfie thee;
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:116405:58"/>
               <hi>being</hi> thy ſelf ſatisfied, thou doeſt ſatisfy <hi>all;</hi> and <hi>being plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> thou pleaſeſt <hi>all:</hi> thy content, contents every one, becauſe thou art <hi>all:</hi> art content it ſelf in <hi>all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou haſt <hi>ſhaken all Nations, and the deſire of all Nations is come:</hi> We have been ſhaken into peeces, and every peece ſhaken out of all order and peace. Thou art good that thou doeſt but ſhake only; rends, that thou mayeſt make way for thy ſelfe to enter, and for all to enter with thee into every part. What we deſire we have: we can deſire nothing but the Lord: nothing is deſirable but the Lord; <hi>the Lord we have,</hi> and in the Lord wee meet with every deſirable thing: the <hi>deſire ſatisfied, which if a tree of life.</hi> God was our deſire, which is now interpreted; being brought forth into performance and enjoyment: God the bottom, and top; the deſire, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, meeting in one Spirit and Kingdome: GOD the root in our deſires grown up into the fruit, attainment.</p>
            <p>The <hi>intereſt of this whole Kingdome, in this reſtoration, is ſatisfied;</hi> and that conſiſts in; Firſt, PEACE; a ſure <hi>Peace;</hi> a well grounded <hi>Peace:</hi> here you have the richeſt jewell of <hi>peace</hi> that heaven hath; the <hi>Peace of God:</hi> The union and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of Father, Son and Spirit in one; this is our peace, and a well grounded peace, ſettled and ſure; that is laſting and durable; a <hi>threefold cord</hi> that cannot be broken.</p>
            <p>We are one with God, <hi>reconcil'd to</hi> God; we dwell toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſame houſe; he hath married us: one in God; one as God; one amongſt our ſelves, as he is one: All in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Head, the KING; all in the Son, the Body, the <hi>Parliament:</hi> All in Spirit in combination; acting and living together in their juſt and lafull rights; and in <hi>perfect fruit of righteouſnes, love and peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The Nation deſires SETTLEMENT, after her ſhakings, heres everlaſting Settlement, upon ſure
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:116405:58"/>foundations; <hi>The ſure mercies of David;</hi> upon the rock of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: he <hi>who was, is, and ever will be:</hi> thoſe pillars upon which <hi>England</hi> ſtood, made cleare, and bright; and the Kingdome ſettled upon them: Now <hi>the world is establiſht</hi> in eternity, ſo <hi>that it cannot be moved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, The <hi>HONO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R OF THE NATION:</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured indeed; For <hi>glory doth dwell in our Land:</hi> our <hi>Nation</hi> now <hi>is the very throne and ſeat of Divine glory; a Royall Nation;</hi> filled with Princely ſpirits: the <hi>Kingdome it ſelf</hi> raiſd from the <hi>grave</hi> of luſts, luxury, coveteouſneſſe, oppreſſion, baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and beaſtlineſſe, into the <hi>nobleneſſe and wiſdome of the Spirit of God: England</hi> firſt brought forth into that excellent and perfect <hi>righteouſneſſe, liberty and justice</hi> that ſhall bee a <hi>copy</hi> to other <hi>Nations; a Mother,</hi> that ſhall bring forth <hi>ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, The SETLING OF RELIGION; of the <hi>true Orthodox, ancient Proteſtant Religion;</hi> and the <hi>rooting out ſects, heriſies, popery:</hi> This doth it compleatly and fully. We now ſhall have <hi>ſound doctrin,</hi> meaſured by <hi>the ſcriptures of truth; the golden line</hi> of truth <hi>it ſelf:</hi> truth derived from the <hi>bowels of eternity:</hi> and conſtantly preſerved and kept in the <hi>worst ages,</hi> free from defilement; <hi>giving teſtimony of it ſelf</hi> ſucceſſively, in the darkeſt times; and now breaking forth in undeniable, and indiſputable authority and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: Not <hi>peeces,</hi> but a whole <hi>body of Divinity; divinity it ſelfe;</hi> not in ſhadow, but the body of it; not maim'd, but intire and whole, from the higheſt head and glory of God, to the loweſt part of hell: and all the variety of eſtates, in <hi>Christ, in Angels, in men;</hi> with their <hi>fallings and riſings, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendings</hi> and <hi>aſcendings,</hi> fully and plainly brought forth. The Sun ſhall ſhine ſo clearly, as ſhall diſcipate theſe miſts of error that are amongſt us; with ſuch power as ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:116405:59"/>the madneſſe and diſorder of peoples judgements, into a beautifull Uniformity; <hi>by power of the Spirit of God, and in ſatisfaction to every minde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, Another Publick intereſt is, <hi>LIBERTY</hi> from all oppreſſing powers: this we have here reſtored; <hi>a glorious li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty;</hi> in which all <hi>Engliſh men</hi> ſhall live under Authority as children, not ſervants nor ſlaves; ſome ſhall rule as Fathers, others ſhall obey as Sons: Nothing but <hi>love, goodneſſe, and gentleneſſe in both;</hi> both to command and obey, ſhall be ſweet and delightfull: no Laws but <hi>the perfect Law of liberty,</hi> which the ſubject ſhal chooſe and deſire. A KING <hi>free and enlarged into the hearts and eſtates of his people; living in all they are and have,</hi> &amp; <hi>they pleaſed to have it all the Kings; every one hating that</hi> which will not be the KINGS, <hi>and Common wealths;</hi> count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that baſe and unworthy, that is not every ones as well as his own; and that <hi>only to be rich, which is free for all:</hi> and ſo men free to part with, as well as to injoy; eſtates free as well as perſons; and men <hi>not ſlaves to men, nor to their wealth:</hi> no, not to <hi>propriety;</hi> which is the greateſt bondage to ſerve them ſelves and their own wealth: That's true wealth, <hi>Common wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the People <hi>free, living in the boſome of the</hi> KING; <hi>in his authority and greatneſſe:</hi> they have a true right to it, as they have anything; <hi>Tbe Court is their Fathers houſe;</hi> the <hi>Throne</hi> their own home; where every ſubject dwels, and lives in the <hi>Kings honour and preſence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixtly, <hi>In this we have</hi> A RIGHT <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDERSTANDING be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween King</hi> and <hi>Parliament:</hi> The wiſdome of God to ſhew us a <hi>way of peace;</hi> the <hi>true light</hi> ſhining from heaven upon us: the <hi>night</hi> of our miſtakes <hi>is paſt; The prince of darkneſſe is thrown down;</hi> &amp; we are <hi>tranſlated out of a kingdome of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, into the Kingdome of God;</hi> in which we ſhal alwaies have the <hi>true wiſdome to guide us.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:116405:59"/>
            <p>Seventhly, Here likewiſe have we AN ACT OF OB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIVION; whereby all tranſgreſſions <hi>are blotted out; all carried in to the depth of the Sea:</hi> where <hi>ſin,</hi> if it be ſought for, <hi>it ſhall not be found:</hi> ſuch a fullneſſe of pleaſure and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction as will not admits <hi>a thought of revenge;</hi> if we ſhall remember paſt things, it will bee with joy and thanks to each other; for in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rting, we have ſaved one another: wherein we have done evill to any, it is turned to their good; The KING will thank the <hi>Parliament</hi> for riſing againſt him; and the Parliament thank the KING for lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of them: There is GOD, and perfect good in <hi>all</hi> that every party hath ſuffered.</p>
            <p>HAPPINES <hi>it ſelfe; England</hi> now hath a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of the riches of Heaven and Earth in one bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe: <hi>England; a glorious Land;</hi> the Land of God; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding in ſtore, trade, juſtice, peace, amity. We are fallen, but (as hath been expected) <hi>We RISE AS ONE MAN: England</hi> acted by one head, one ſpirit, is become <hi>one man:</hi> every one <hi>loving</hi> another as himſelf; &amp; <hi>riſing</hi> againſt the COMMON ENEMY, the Devil, the deſtroyer; who is, and hath been our only enemy; wee hate none but him: and by this RISING, wee free our ſelves from him.</p>
            <p>As this ſatisfies the <hi>publick,</hi> ſo every <hi>particular intereſt,</hi> or <hi>all intereſts are here ſatisfied,</hi> and brought into one <hi>interest,</hi> which is the <hi>true nature of an interest;</hi> to be in others <hi>a joynt, or common ſubſistence:</hi> every part made cleane and right, and <hi>ſo inter-weaved</hi> into one <hi>intire garment; which is the excellency of Divine works,</hi> they are large &amp; ſave all; thats a humane and deviliſh deſigne, <hi>that ſaves one by the ruin of another;</hi> but that is Gods way to ſave all ſo, <hi>as the ſalvation of one is the ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of another:</hi> Now here you ſee all contented.</p>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:116405:60"/>
            <p>The KING (as all have ſworne and prayed) advanced into honour and greatneſſe; freed from priſon <hi>from chains of darkneſſe</hi> wherein he hath been held; brought out of a low <hi>dungeon of wrath</hi> and heavy <hi>affliction,</hi> to the <hi>higheſt Throne of Majeſty:</hi> Perſon, and Office reſtored from blackneſſe and foulneſſe, to <hi>ſplendor and brightneſſe,</hi> into the Majeſty of God: and that performed which the Parliament often promiſed, A GLORIOUS KING; a KING in the <hi>glory of God;</hi> or the <hi>glorious God;</hi> the Immortall KING <hi>Reigning in man, and over men: Sir,</hi> this is your true intereſt; tis your life and ſoul; I know tis your heart, though yet <hi>lying hid:</hi> Tis the Key will unlock your ſpirit, and bring it out into the light and liberty of God; unlock your underſtanding, after <hi>ſeven times</hi> have paſſed over you, you ſhal returne to your <hi>Throne,</hi> and true Majeſty ſhall be given to you; and your <hi>Nobles and Kingdomes</hi> ſhall honour you; all ſhall freely bow to you; and you ſhall command and <hi>Reign</hi> againe, to the terrour of your adverſaries, and joy of your friends: now the <hi>priſon doors ſtand open to</hi> you, and you ſhall returne to your <hi>Royall Parliament</hi> and <hi>City</hi> after ſeaven yeares baniſhment.</p>
            <p>We have now a King in whom we can confide<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as in <hi>God;</hi> now the LORD lives in him tis impiety and wickedneſſe to have a thought of diſtruſt concerning him; the <hi>ſure juſtice and righteouſneſſe of God</hi> inhabits in the Throne, as its proper place.</p>
            <p>We have a King according to our own hearts; hee lives in our hearts; ariſes out of our hearts; and our hearts give him his dominion: hee hath all we have, and hath not too much, becauſe he hath us too; and nothing but what we free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give: one <hi>higher by the head then all the People:</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the wiſdome of the whole in him; of the largeſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and therefore King becauſe he doth in true worth
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:116405:60"/>excell any in the Nation, and is of all men fitteſt to <hi>reign:</hi> fitted by his <hi>great ſuffering,</hi> and Gods fulneſſe dwelling in him.</p>
            <p>This is the <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EENS interest</hi> ſhe may return to the <hi>King,</hi> there is no fear now, ſhe cannot hurt either Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or <hi>Religion</hi> both being in ſuch a condition as cannot be hurt: beſides living in this <hi>light,</hi> of <hi>all</hi> ſhe ſhall moſt love the Parliament; it being the ſame with her ſelf the <hi>Kings Conſort,</hi> and ſhe being the ſame with it, concurring together in ſeverall wayes to help, and honour the <hi>King:</hi> if ſhe ſhould attempt any thing againſt it, it would be <hi>againſt the King and her ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Parliament adminiſtring about the affairs of the <hi>kingdom,</hi> that the <hi>King may enjoy his Queen and Family</hi> with greateſt plenty, honour, eaſe and pleaſure: and the <hi>Queen adminiſtring</hi> in the domeſticall affairs of the <hi>King</hi> about his Perſon, <hi>that the king may enjoy his Parliament and people in greateſt content and freedom:</hi> The Parliament in buſineſſe of State, a <hi>Queen</hi> lying in the boſome of the <hi>king; and the Queen</hi> in private and perſonall affairs a Parliament: and ſo Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Queen intereſted, joynd in one intereſt; And for her <hi>religion</hi> we are now ſo far from being afraid of it, that we rejoyce in it, and in her great intereſt in the Papacie: For as the Papiſts had by her <hi>deſigns upon us:</hi> ſo now <hi>(the ſtreame being turned)</hi> we ſhall by her <hi>deſign upon them,</hi> and over-runne the whole Papacie with <hi>light and truth,</hi> ſhe ſhall be the <hi>doore</hi> by which we ſhall enter into all the riches and honours of the Papacie, and without injury to them, we ſhal ſpoyle them of all their <hi>glory, or rather bring a glorious fire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them, that ſhall out-ſhine theirs; and burn up theirs into it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>PRINCE</hi> his <hi>Interest</hi> is here ſatisfied, he is indeed
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:116405:61"/>one <hi>with the Parliament; they &amp; he are brethren deſcended both from the loyns of the king,</hi> and are one in various forms: each being the glory of the <hi>king,</hi> &amp; the ſtaffe of his age, <hi>Chriſtened</hi> at the ſame <hi>Font</hi> the Spirit of Chriſt: both the hope and joy of <hi>England,</hi> both being the glory of the King, propagated unto eternity, a never failing off-ſpring, and flouriſhing in the vigour and youthfulneſſe of the Son of God: both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted into Chriſt, or the <hi>interest</hi> of Chriſt, and ſo of each other. The LORDS who have loſt their Nobility, ſunck in diſgrace, ſcattered, and almoſt buried in diſhonour: by this ſhall be reſtored, not to airy empty Titles, but to true Nobility: The Lord doth appear <hi>Lord of Lords:</hi> your Lord, owning <hi>Lordlineſſe</hi> and filling of it with himſelf, as well as <hi>king of kings,</hi> and as he ſets <hi>a Crown of pure gold</hi> upon the head of the <hi>King:</hi> ſo Coronets of pure Gold upon yours, you ſhall ſhine as ſtars in this Firmament, in wiſdome, holineſſe, juſtice and goodneſſe, and be in affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to the <hi>King;</hi> that head ennobled with heavenly Majeſty, fit to be about <hi>the Throne,</hi> and advanced to be the ſhoulders and breſt of the Nation, next the head.</p>
            <p>The Kings party are here fully ſatisfied: to ſee their <hi>King</hi> reſtored to the honour and greatneſſe of his Anceſtors, his Progenitors: which is into <hi>the glory of God the great king,</hi> the Kings true Father: They that contend for KNOWNE LAWES, by this the Laws are <hi>known by God,</hi> brought out of the duſt of the earth in which they were trampled upon and reſtored into the brightneſſe and life of God: And now we ſhall ſee the whole body of the Engliſh Lawes interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and opened to us by the wiſdome of God, and all drawn forth into life and power by the Spirit of God, as we ſee the <hi>fundament all Law of King and Parliament</hi> written in the face of God and Chriſt by the Spirit.</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:116405:61"/>
            <p>You ſhall have <hi>Religion</hi> in the OLD WAY; in the <hi>good old way:</hi> DIVINE SERVICE; wherein every part of it ſhall be irradiated with the Beams of <hi>Divinity,</hi> and in every thing you ſhall ſee the <hi>Face of God,</hi> and have fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with the <hi>Divine Nature:</hi> Religion ſhall be adorned with Solemnity, State, Pomp, Glory, Eaſe, Muſick, all Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Earthly together, ſuch as may allure and pleaſe the mindes of men, and there ſhall be nothing harſh or rude in it: yea, rudeneſſe it ſelf ſhal have its comlineſſe. You ſhall have your ſports, pleaſures, <hi>we will ſing together in the hight of Zion: young men &amp; maids daunce together</hi> without offence or iniquity, all in the innocency, holineſſe and joy of God: your whole life a courſe of pleaſure; all things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea labour and pains ſhall be <hi>recreations:</hi> God <hi>recreating</hi> all things, or making all things new, they ſhall be ſweet and delightfull: you ſhall have your Holy-dayes: yea, your whole life ſhall be ſpent in holy-daies, a continuall reſt, the great <hi>Jubile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You the more civil and ſolid of that party, that ſincke into a retired condition in theſe tempeſtuous times, that lie quietly and patiently in your graves of your owne and the Kindomes ſufferings; your reſurrection is come, and you ſhall revive, and in a new ſpirit act for, and in the proſperity of the Nation.</p>
            <p>And you mad Lads ſhall SWEARE: <hi>Now the Lord lives in truth, righteouſneſſe, and judgement,</hi> and know him preſent with you; <hi>ſweare</hi> by the <hi>eternall God,</hi> the Spirit filling every oath with truth: you ſhall curſe your enemy the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil with all plagues to the pit of hell, and ſo dam him and ram him in, that he ſhal no more come forth to trouble you: you ſhall eate and drink freely, and forget <hi>your ſelves and your ſorrow,</hi> and in it be filled with the Spirit of the Lord: be raiſd into high mirth and jollity, drink ſo freely of this
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:116405:62"/>
               <hi>new wine of the kingdome,</hi> till you are drunk out of your own <hi>wits</hi> into the Princely Spirit of God, and then ever ſpeak and act things of love, worth, bravery and excellency: This is the KINGS HEALTH his <hi>ſaving health,</hi> his union with God, God with him, <hi>drink</hi> of this health freely: and the whole Kingdome ſhall PLEDGE; be bound to <hi>fill it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,</hi> and drink down this heavenly liquor of the Majeſty of <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>King</hi> into them: and the whole people ſhall ſay, and <hi>ſee it performed,</hi> GOD SAVE THE KING: The King is ſaved in God: <hi>and God the ſalvation of the king.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This reſtoration fully ſatisfies the Parliaments <hi>Interest,</hi> gives her high PRIVILEDGES: She is called to an honourable ſtate to live in the <hi>Lord Chriſt,</hi> to ſit with <hi>Chriſt in heavenly places,</hi> to be one with the Son, the body of God: to be <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> above the mother of us all; and therefore FREE, <hi>free</hi> with God, and in God with the King: <hi>free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> to enter into his heart and boſome, to lye there conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually: <hi>The king ſhall greatly deſire thy beauty:</hi> Thou now haſt POWER as well as liberty, to make Righteous Lawes in perfect Righteouſneſſe that ſhall ſtand for ever: ſuch a King and ſuch a Parliament as we have long beg'd, to agree together in juſt things: and in both we ſhall reap the fruit of our <hi>prayers;</hi> which though they were <hi>ſowed in weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and now ſeem dead and rotting in the earth, yet ſhall <hi>riſe in power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The great <hi>Interest</hi> of the Parliament, the COVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NANT is here fully ſatisfied: The end that we looked upon, HAVING THE GLORY OF GOD IN OUR EYES: that glory is now manifeſt: God in <hi>glory.</hi> All Popery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> rooted out and the root of it, Satan; a tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and perfect REFORMATION. God once for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Kingdome <hi>after himſelf</hi> in his owne likeneſſe, in
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:116405:62"/>which it corrupted, he hath taken down the old forme, and ſets up a new; <hi>reformes us</hi> in State and Church: now we ſhall have doctrin and diſciplin, according to the WORD OF GOD; the true and eternall Word; the Word it ſelf brought forth: and according to the example of the BEST RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORMED CHURCH, <hi>The generall aſſembly in heaven &amp;c.</hi> We have the KING in honour; the KINGDOMES, heavenly and earthly UNITED; and a ſtrong bond that will binde theſe three, and all the <hi>Kingdomes</hi> of the earth in one life, law and peace. By this <hi>THE POWER OF GODLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NES</hi> is ſet up; <hi>Godlines, likeneſſe of God;</hi> in Spirit, <hi>in Power;</hi> or God himſelfe: all things elſe being but a forme. We have here PROPRIETY, <hi>God, our own God;</hi> we reſtored to him, and hee to us; his own Vineyard: Every one ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy what he hath in peace; and coveteouſneſſe, the root of oppreſſion deſtroyed: every one ſhall have enough; every one ſhall bee ſatisfied; have ſo much as hee hath ability to beare: and others ſhall freely part with that which hath been burthenſome to them ſelves; none have more then they want, and all that they want; all in ſuch a condition, place, office, as they are fit for, as they are capable of: Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one having a minde to his condition, and a condition to his minde; every one by Divine wiſdome ſo diſpoſed as he ſhall reſt in it, and not move after others; there being no diſcontent but in hel, which is in perpetuall motion after e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing and attains to nothing.</p>
            <p>THE LORD SHALL BE ONE, AND HIS NAME ONE in both Kingdomes: There is now but one LORD; all gathered into Chriſt; hee is LORD in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; and <hi>his name written</hi> upon every thing in Church and State; <hi>nothing but the Lord</hi> ſpoken and done amongſt us: <hi>in heaven and earth,</hi> in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland:</hi> The Spirit of
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:116405:63"/>the Lord running through theſe Kingdomes, and through all perſons in it, ruling over all in, and by himſelf; the whole ſhall be called by this <hi>Name, The Lord;</hi> and ſo not only one man, <hi>but one Lord;</hi> there being nothing but <hi>the glory and righteouſneſſe of the Lord</hi> amongſt us.</p>
            <p>This is that which we have deſired, and attempted, to ſet up THE KINGDOME OF CHRIST, THE REIGN OE THE SAINTS; The holy God, holy Chriſt, holy Spirit, with holy men and Angels, Reigning together.</p>
            <p>This rich LO RD, filling all Magiſtracy with juſtice, all People with love, our Miniſtry with truth, our hearts with heavenly joy, all our Laws with life and light, our Cities with unity and wealth, our Villages with plenty, our Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies with content, our Perſons with happineſſe, our King <hi>eſpecially</hi> with honour, glory, ſafety, eaſe of heart, clearneſs of underſtanding, a ſweet injoyment of his <hi>Queen</hi> and <hi>Children:</hi> the <hi>Parliament,</hi> LORDS and COMMONS, with perfect agreement, majeſty, goodneſſe, love of the King and peoples proſperity.</p>
            <p>This is a true PERSONAL <hi>TREATY,</hi> wherein King and <hi>Parliament</hi> and all the people are together one perſon, one body, living in one Spirit.</p>
            <p>Thus the Lord is <hi>Englands</hi> deſire, and <hi>Englands</hi> joy; him we ſought for, him we finde. God gives us all that we <hi>deſir'd, and more then we could ask or think of,</hi> and that too in a more excellent way then we could imagine. <hi>Tis the Lords doing, and tis marvellous in our eies: Tis the day of the Lord, we will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce and be glad in it.</hi> Tis thy ſelf <hi>O God, Englands life and ſoul;</hi> and <hi>England is thy delight, thy firſt-borne</hi> of all the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the earth: Tis thy ſelf, out <hi>ſaviour and ſalvation:</hi> Tis thy juſtice hath took vengeance upon our inventions, and
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:116405:63"/>ſaved in that vengeance: Tis thy power triumphing in our weakneſſe; thy mercy rejoyces in our deliverance; thy wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhines forth: that brings light out of darkneſſe; turnes mourning into rejoycing; makes our <hi>Tragedy</hi> end in <hi>a Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy:</hi> a ſeaſonable deliverance, now when all miſeries and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions are met together in our bowels, a cleare Sun to break forth <hi>of a ſuddain,</hi> out of ſuch blackenſſe of darkneſſe as covered us.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt carried us through death to life; yea, through thy own death to thy own life: Tis by blood wee are ſaved, by the blood of Chriſt. Thou haſt done all things well, thy workes are all excellent and perfect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let the People praiſe thee, O God; yea let all the People praiſe THEE.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:116405:64"/>
            <head>Poſcript.</head>
            <p>THeſe are the Leaves of the tree of Life; that will give a new life to this Nation; and will heale all her deadly maladies: but the leaves, not the fruit; yet effectuall: It's written here weakely, it ſhall be mighty in operation: imperfectly expreſſed now, but fully, and accurately, will it write forth it ſelf in action. Tis death to reſiſt them; <hi>The rebellious do dwell in a dry land,</hi> in hel: Particular perſons may be confounded, the Nation is the Lords and ſhall be recovered; hee that oppoſeth, all the evils of the Kingdome ſhall gather into his heart; and hee ſhall bee the common ſhore into which the Nation ſhall empty forth all ber plagues; wrath and deſtruction leave the Kingdome, and dwell there; thou ſhalt ceaſe tormenting the Nation, and torment them that reſiſt: You ſee the <hi>Leaves,</hi> I know you deſire the <hi>Fruit:</hi> that is indeeed the life of all; you ſhall ſpeedily injoy it: all the glory and happineſſe of this Nation beer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and of all the Nations of the earth and heaven too, ſhall, in its higheſt perfection, dwell in every particular ſoul: This, and every peece of it, and more ten thouſand times then this, ſhall in the purest and fullest glory of Father, Son and Spirit, Grown every Saint; and fill his <hi>ſoul, body, relations, calling, buſineſſe, recreation,</hi> and <hi>all;</hi> with the Righteouſneſſe and Light of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and the Face of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Page 2. line 21. <hi>for</hi> were <hi>read</hi> weare. p. 16. l. 25. <hi>for</hi> Mame r. Name. p. 45. l. 2. <hi>for</hi> ſee &amp; their r. ſee their. p. 55. l. 16. <hi>for</hi> Mation r. Nation. l. 22. <hi>for</hi> them ſelves and families r. himſelf and family. p. 57. <hi>for</hi> Chap. 11. r. Chap. 13. p. 81. l. laſt, <hi>for</hi> a ſecond r. as a ſecond. p. 82. l. 29. <hi>for</hi> dody r. body. p. 88. 13. <hi>for</hi> ſtall r. ſhall.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:116405:64"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAPTER, I.</label> SHewing the happy and flouriſhing condition in which the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of England once ſtood, and the ground of it. <hi>pag. 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. II.</label> Shewing the kingdome of England in its corrupt and decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning estate. <hi>pag. 6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. III.</label> Shewing the kings errours. <hi>pag. 10</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. V.</label> Shewing the Parliaments errours. <hi>pag. 18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. VI.</label> Shewing the judgement upon the Parliament. <hi>pag. 26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. VII.</label> Shewing the ſinne and puniſhment of the People of both partyes. <hi>pag. 29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. VIII.</label> Shewing the wickdneſſe of the Miniſtery, or Clergy, and their judgement. <hi>pag. 32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. IX.</label> Shewing the iniquity of the Army, and its judgement. <hi>pag. 39</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. X.</label> Shewing the state of the Levellers. <hi>pag. 45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. XI.</label> Shewing the judgment of the City of London. <hi>pag. 47</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:116405:65"/>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. XII.</label> Shewing the irrecoverableneſſe of Englands ruine by humane wayes. <hi>pag. 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. XIII.</label> Shewing the method of God in curing the Nation. <hi>(viz.)</hi> firſt, to take our ſinne upon himſelf. <hi>pag. 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. XIV.</label> Of the ſecond thing in ſaving of the Nation: The death of Christ, and our fellowſhip in it. <hi>pag. 62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. XV.</label> Of the compleat cure of the Nation, ſhewing it in its raiſed ſtate; and particularly the king. <hi>pag. 69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. XVI.</label> Of the Parliament in its raiſed eſtate. <hi>pag. 74</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. XVII.</label> Of the perfect union betwixt king and Parliament, and by them with his People; in this new and raiſed eſtate. <hi>pag. 76</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP XVIII.</label> Of the cure of the people of the Land by this death and reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. <hi>pag. 87</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. XIX.</label> The restoration of the Miniſtrie, by Chriſts bearing their ſin, and by his death and reſurrection. <hi>pag. 90</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. XX.</label> Of the reſtoration of the Army, Levellers, and City of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. <hi>pag. 97</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. XXI.</label> Of the admirable fulneſſe of this restoration, ſatisfying all Interests.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:116405:65"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
